<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A familiar treatise laying downe cases of conscience, furthering to perseuerance in sanctification. By Thomas Cooper, preacher of Gods word.</title>
            <title>Converts first love, discerned</title>
            <author>Cooper, Thomas, fl. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 250 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120771</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855965</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855965</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19293)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1231:04, 1512:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A familiar treatise laying downe cases of conscience, furthering to perseuerance in sanctification. By Thomas Cooper, preacher of Gods word.</title>
                  <title>Converts first love, discerned</title>
                  <author>Cooper, Thomas, fl. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 92 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Beale, for William Welby, and are to be sold at his shop, at the signe of the Swan in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A greatly expanded version of STC 5697.5: Cooper, Thomas.  The converts first love, discerned.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A preseruatiue against apostacie.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 5703.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 5703 on UMI microfilm reel 1512.</note>
                  <note>Bodleian Library copy imperfect; title page lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library and the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1231 #4 (Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.) Library copy), and at reel 1512 #6 (Bodleian Library copy, identified as STC 5703; lacks title page).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FAMILIAR TREATISE, laying downe <hi>CASES OF CONSCIENCE,</hi> Furthering to perſeuerance in SANCTIFICATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Thomas Cooper, <hi>preacher of Gods word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Iohn Beale,</hi> for <hi>William Welby,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the ſigne of the Swan in Paules Church-yard. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21476:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21476:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, MY HARTIE Wel-willers, the Ladie <hi>Rumney,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Springham,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Slany,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parkhust,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Clarke,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Vincent, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Moſley, and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Thaire, <hi>and the reſt of my Christian auditors, and</hi> louing neighbors, grace, mercie and peace from God the Father, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, bee multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull, and dearely beloued in the Lord Ieſus: It is the mercie of the Lord, that wee are not vtterly conſumed, becauſe his compaſsions faile not. Hath not our long proſperitie hardened our hearts, and lulled vs in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie? And when we ſay, peace and ſafety, may not a ſudden destruction come vpon vs, as the trauaile vpon a woman with childe, and we ſhall not eſcape? Doe not our impudent and deſperate ſinnes, daily call downe for vengeance againſt vs, in that we put the euill day farre from vs, that wee may ſtill approach to the ſeat of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, hardning our hearts yet more and more that we cannot repent? And is not the enuious man buſie to ſow tares, now wee are aſleepe? Are not our aduerſaries watchfull and dil gent in their malicious and bloody practiſes againſt the Church of God, practiſing daylie the ouerthrow thereof? will any thing ſerue their turne
<pb facs="tcp:21476:3"/>
but to roote cut and destroy, and are we generally any better then ſuch trees as are able to bee hewen downe, and caſt into the fire? Hath this vnprofitable fig-tree for all this dreſsing and fencing, for all this lopping and donging, yet brought forth fruit worthie of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? Surely though we ſhould neuer ſo much ſtand v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our iustification with <hi>Saul,</hi> that wee haue fulfilled the Commandements of the Lord, that we are an holy people, the Lord ſhall finde no iniquity in vs, &amp;c. yet the bleating of the ſheepe, and lowing of the oxen: the ſparing of <hi>Agag.</hi> and reſeruing of his offals, is a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious euidence to conuince our hypocriſie. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though we flatter our ſelues with <hi>Agag,</hi> that the bitterneſſe of death is paſt, becauſe happilie the Lord in great patience hath yet waited vpon vs, and put off many deſperate blowes, that might haue light heauilie vpon vs: yet certainly when hee ſees a conuenient time he will execute vengeance, and wound the hairie ſcalpe of all thoſe that goe on in their wickedneſſe. And is not this a ſpeciall euidence, that we goe on in our ſinnes, and intend not repentance, becauſe we either hate to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and haue caſt the word behinde our backes: or els heape vp teachers according to our own luſts, which may prophecie of new wine and ſtrong drinke, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhall be as to day, or much more aboundant? And is it not a fearefull argument of the wrath of God, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to ſeaze vpon vs, in that wee haue choſen and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the world, that thirſts after our blood, and haue caſt out that ſword which ſhould ſtand in the gappe, to turne away the vengeance? What then is the reaſon that we are not vtterly conſumed that our aduerſaries the Papiſts, haue not had their deſire? Surely they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:21476:3"/>
not ſay, where is now our God? becauſe they ſhal not blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme that great &amp; glorious Name of our God, which is called vpon of vs: And therfore, not vnto vs oh Lord, not vnto vs, but vnto thy Name giue the glory, euen for thy truth &amp; righteouſnes ſake. Thogh we are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the leaſt of Gods mercies, thogh we haue deſerued to be ouerwhelmed with all his plagues, yet the Lord is worthy of all praiſe and glory: and therefore he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vs, that we might glorifie him: and ſhall not the Iudge of al the world do right? wil he puniſh the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with the wicked? muſt not <hi>Lot</hi> be taken out of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> before the vengeance be inflicted? ſhall not euen <hi>one</hi> be a means to ſpare the Citie for his ſake? Behold, here another ground of the patience of God, euen the holy ſeed that yet remaines the Lord hath a litle flocke which is as deare vnto him, as the apple of his eye: this hath hee choſen it vnto him in Ieſus Chriſt, before the foundations of the world were laid. This he hath made glorious through his beautie, which he hath ſet vpon it: this he hath promiſed to bee with vs to the end of the world &amp; can any thing be againſt vs if the lord be with vs? ſhall not he make our enemies our footſtool? ſhal not the lord tread Satan vnder our feet? bleſſed be God in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that hath made bare his mighty army in the ſight &amp; acknowledgment of our enemies? Did not the papiſts once acknowledge that God was become a luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran? do they not feel to this day, that he that keeps Iſrael doth neither ſlu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber nor ſleep? hath not our God watched ouer vs, when wee haue ſlept in ſecurity? hath not hee foght for vs, when our carnal weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue bin confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? hath he not got himſelf the glory of al our deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſo we might at length giue him the glory of his
<pb facs="tcp:21476:4"/>
free mercies, that ſo we might not be afraid of any euill tidings, that ſtill we might feare, and depart from euil while the wicked rage, &amp; are careles? ſurely howſoeuer the pit is digged for the wicked, and the conſumption decreed ſhall paſſe ouer to the confounding of hypocrites howſoeuer ſinner in <hi>Sion</hi> ſhalbe afraid, and feare ſhall take hold of the hypocrits, when Gods wrath approcheth yet ſhall the vpright heart then lift vp their heads be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their ſaluation draweth neere. The purging of the Church of hypocrites ſhalbe the preparing thereof to greater glorie and ſafetie, and the anointed of the Lord ſhall gaine more honour and ſecuritie, when the Lord Ieſus ſhalbe more aduanced vpon his holy hill of Sion. And are not our enemies haſtening hereunto? hath not the patience of policie enraged them more and more, and doth not their wickedneſſe ſo breake out, that it can no longer be endured? Is it not time together with the ſafety of our ſoules, to prouide alſo for the ſecuritie of our liues and ſtates? Bleſſed bee the Lord for the vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance and courage of the ſtate. Oh, bleſſed bee our God for his watchfulneſſe ouer vs, were not all our building and watching elſe in vaine? And is it not then more then time to keepe our God waking by our prayers and teares? Is it not his time to awake out of ſecuritie, that ſo we may make our peace with God, that he may ſtil for his glory preſerue the peace of his Churches, that he may ſtill preuent and confound the enemies of his Church? And could I now hold my peace in this day of good ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, when the Lord hath euen againe giuen vs our liues for a prey, and pluckt vs as a prey out of the teeth of the deuourer? Haue I not vowed a yeerely remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, for that great deliuerance from the gunpowder
<pb facs="tcp:21476:4"/>
Treaſon? and doth the glorious Lord ſtill giue new oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to reuiue that great deliuerance? Are not his mercies renued euery morning vnto his, ſo great is his faithfulneſſe, and ſhall not we renew our thankfulneſſe by renewing our repentance? Shall wee not remember from whence wee are fallen, by remembring from whence we haue been deliuered, that ſo we may iuſtifie the free mercie of our God in our great deliuerances: and renewing our right in Ieſus Chriſt that ſo we may recouer our firſt loue, and be enabled to walke worthy of the mercies of our God, in ſtrengthening the things that are readie to die, and continuing with all patience and perſeuerance, that no man take away our Crowne from vs? Are not our earthly Crownes often ſhaken, that ſo we may bee ſure of the heauenly inheritance, which cannot bee ſhaken, that ſo we may haſten from this priſon, to that citie which is aboue? And hath not our gratious God giuen vs euen Eagles wings, that we may mount vp from the loue of this world, that we may flie away from the entiſing vanities theeof, &amp; ſo come to that eternall reſt? May we not liue by faith in the experience of theſe ſo ſtrange and vnexpected deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances: that he which hath deliuered, doth all ſtill deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, yea for his Names ſake will deliuer vs from all vnreaſonable men, yea from euery euill worke, that ſo we may be made meet for that glorious inheritance? And ſhall not this litle ſparke yeeld ſome light hereunto, till the depth of miſchiefe being further diſcouered, the candle may be lighted, and ſet vp vpon the hill, to direct all to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to further the Saints in their iourney to the heauenlie <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> ſurely as it pleaſeth God to lend oportunity and libertie, ſo ſhall I
<pb facs="tcp:21476:5"/>
not be wanting by Gods grace, from that light, to kindle ſuch a torch, that may either burne vp all the ſtubble of Popery, or elſe may ſufficientlie warne vs to auoid the danger thereof. Meane while I haue thought good to take this occaſion, to maintain the ſoundnes of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſtanding and recouery out of any decayes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that ſo wee may bee thereby fitted to thoſe further mercies which the Lord hath in ſtore for vs. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it hath pleaſed God to make you instruments (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) of my ſetling in the Citie, and exerciſe of my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I haue accounted it my duetie to conſecrate theſe firſt fruits of my ſetled labours vnto you: beſeeching the Lord to giue you vnderſtanding in all things: and to preſerue you blameleſſe and vnſpotted in theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill times, vnto the day of Ieſus Chriſt, to whoſe gratious protection I doe moſt hartily commend you, resting in him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips poore remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer at the throne of Grace, THOMAS COOPER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21476:5"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, WISDOME TO DISCERNE HIS E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate aright, and grace to grow for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to perfection.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued in the Lord Ieſus, it is a moſt <hi>dangerous,</hi> and yet very <hi>eaſie</hi> and <hi>plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible deluſion,</hi> to <hi>conceit</hi> vnto our ſelues an <hi>eſtate in grace,</hi> when as yet we remain the bond ſlaues of Satan. And it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>difficult,</hi> and yet moſt <hi>neceſſarie</hi> triall, to diſcerne our conſtant abiding and proceeding in this eſtate of grace. For (to paſſe by theſe who make a mocke of conuerſion, as being a <hi>touch of noueltie,</hi> a <hi>brand of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie,</hi> and <hi>imputation of hypocriſie</hi>) who is there almoſt that flatters not himſelfe to bee in the fauour of God, and ſo intereſſed in his grace? And hath hee not many ſuch pretences and colours hereunto, which may ſo abuſe his iudgement,<note place="margin">Galat. 6.5.</note> that he may <hi>thinke himſelfe to bee ſomewhat, when he is nothing;</hi> and ſo refuſing to bee found in Chriſt, by being loſt and emptied in himſelfe, thereby become worſe then nothing? Better neuer to haue beene borne, then ſo to be deceiued. Oh how the wiſedome of the fleſh prooues heere enmitie againſt God!<note place="margin">
                  <p>Rom. 8.7. Iohn 9 43. Occaſions to conceiue a falſe conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Complexion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Natures im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </note> Is not this the iudgement vpon the world, that <hi>they which ſee not, might ſee; and that they which ſee might bee made blinde?</hi> Conſider firſt, I pray you, how <hi>nature</hi> occaſions this deceit. Is any leſſe badlie diſpoſed by the benefit of his <hi>complexion?</hi> Is any reſtrained from <hi>ſome act</hi> of euill by <hi>natures impotencie</hi> and <hi>deformitie?</hi> Behold, euen theſe to the naturall man prooue very <hi>dangerous
<pb facs="tcp:21476:6"/>
ſtumbling blockes</hi> to reſt in nature, as affoording ſome ſhew of good, more then is of others of an harder conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as breaking out leſſe into groſſe euils, then ſuch who by natures ability are more prone and prouoked thereto, and ſo to reiect the holy meanes of conuerſion: and is it not esteemed a ſufficient meaſure of goodneſſe, to bee leſſe euill then others, howſoeuer the deſire and fountaine of corruption be the ſame in all? Is not the ſeeming good which by natures benefit ſhewes foorth in the world, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted currant holineſſe, and thereby excludeth the true power of well-doing?</p>
            <p>For is this any more then what brute beaſts may boaſt of? Is the heart leſſe euill, becauſe the hand cannot act, nay is it not more rebellious, the leſſe it hath it deſire? do not ſuch wiſh for, and talke delightfully of what they cannot doe: will they not ſport themſelues in others that can do the ſame? will they not take their fill, if power be reſtored? or is the heart the better, becauſe through benefite of complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we are ingenuous, ſociable, &amp;c. are not theſe fitter matter for Satan to worke on, to draw vs into fellowſhip in euill, to make vs inſtruments to deceiue our ſelues and others?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Education.</hi>
               </note>Eſpecially, if to this ſhew of natures righteouſneſſe, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation</hi> be adioyned, whereby the minde being informed in <hi>knowledge,</hi> and reſtrained by <hi>ciuilitie,</hi> natures <hi>euill</hi> is heereby more kept vnder, and it <hi>ſeeming good,</hi> ſet out more ſaleable and beautious to the ſinister iudgement: howſoeuer now nature being puft vp hereby, hath gained no other then a <hi>weapon of vnrighteouſneſſe,</hi> to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his word, to commit ſinne more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, by how much it is enabled to couch it more cloſely, and ſmooth it more cunuingly; yet this with the world paſſeth for a <hi>currant conuerſion;</hi> Muſt we not onely not doe euill, but alſo doe good, and can wee doe any good of our ſelues, vntill we be in Chriſt? and will we hunger of Chriſt, vntill we deny our ſelues: eſpecially if ſome ſuch change now appeare in the outward man, whereby wee may either
<pb facs="tcp:21476:6"/>
differ from the rudeneſſe and groſſe abuſes of our parents, or differ from the barbarous and deſperate ſprouts of our childhood, and vntamed youth? Is it not hence conceiued that we are now conuerted, ſeeing now our childiſh and youthfull vanities are reſtrained, ſeeing wee are growne more ſober and regular: although all tends to no better then ciuill honeſtie, to fit vs for the world, that ſo we may more hopefully and eaſily ſwallow the baites thereof? al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though when wee are from vnder the rod, wee breake out more deſperately into all groſſe wickedneſſe, or elſe at the beſt exchange our ſinnes, from wantonneſſe to coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, from frowardneſſe to ambition, encreaſing ſtill in our luſts and plotting the ſatisfying thereof, that wee may ſet vp our reſt in the world, and caſt care away.</p>
            <p>And if now the Lord ſhall giue the wicked their deſire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Reſtraining ſpirit.</note> in affoording them ſo farre the vſe of his bleſſed Spirit, as to <hi>reſtraine</hi> yet more inward corruption, by it power, and terrour, that ſo they may be fitter for ſuch outward proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as they haue eſpecially made choice of in this life, and ſo renounced their intereſt in Heauen: And withall may frame better to ſocietie, both of the <hi>good,</hi> to whom now they ſhall doe leſſe hurt, as alſo of the <hi>euill,</hi> whom by this meanes they may prouoke to good; that ſo Gods go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the world may bee more beautifull and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and his will more righteouſly accompliſhed in the elect and reprobate. Is not this <hi>reſtraint</hi> apprehended, as <hi>a great conqueſt ouer corruption;</hi> and ſo a <hi>conuerſion</hi> hence <hi>vainely</hi> concluded, ſeeing the inward heart is no whit renued, but onely the corruption reſtrained from the outward act? Nay, is not corruption <hi>more inraged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly,</hi> the more it is outwardly bridled and ſmothered? and ſo ſinne made out of meaſure ſinfull: as being more <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable,</hi> the more it is curbed:<note place="margin">Rom. 7. <hi>Note.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>breaking out more deſperately,</hi> when the bridle is reiected: as <hi>ripening</hi> more dangerouſly, the more it boileth within: and ſo <hi>ſealing vp</hi> vengeance more certainely, yea more <hi>fearefully haſtning</hi> it, as proceeding to <hi>deſpight the ſpirit of grace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.27.28</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21476:7"/>
               <note place="margin">5. <hi>Spirit of illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi> Math. 7.</note>And what though the Lord beſtow on the wicked <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent graces of his Spirit,</hi> inabling them to <hi>teach others,</hi> to doe <hi>wondrous things,</hi> furthering them ſo farre in the ſhew of holineſſe, as that they ſhall ſeeme for a time to <hi>outſtrip the ſincere profeſſor?</hi> May they not teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">1. Cor 9.</note> and yet themſelues bee <hi>reiected?</hi> May they not doe miracles, and yet heare, <hi>I know you not?</hi> May they not begin in the Spirit, and yet end in the fleſh? and can they continue that haue taken no roote? can they call on God at all times, that haue made the world their hope and their belly their Gods can theſe earth wormes endure any thing that may purge out their droſſe, and prepare them to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note place="margin">Iob. 27. Gal. 6.10. 2. Tim. 3.</note> who ſew to the fleſh, and ſhall they not of the fleſh reape corruption? Shall not <hi>the candle of the hypocrite bee put out?</hi> Doth not this <hi>faire ſhew of the fleſh, deceiue,</hi> and <hi>prooue deceiued?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. <hi>Afflictions,</hi>
               </note>What ſhould I tell you of that change that is wrought by afflictions? Will not the wicked in their troubles ſeeke the Lord diligently? Muſt not the vileſt forbeare, when they cannot otherwiſe chuſe? And is it any maſterie, not to reuenge,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 2. Pet. 2.</note> when power is not in our hands? Will not the ſwine that is now cleanſed, returne to the mire againe? Is it charity, then to forgiue the world, when we ſee no <hi>time</hi> left for execution of malice? Is it patience, to forbeare when we can neither will nor chuſe? Is it obedience, to tremble vnder the whip? to feare God onely for his iuſtice, and not to loue him for his mercy?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7. <hi>Proſperitie.</hi>
               </note>Oh but wee are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of trouble, and reſtored to <hi>great happineſſe.</hi> Behold, wee are bleſſed on the earth: and are not wee then truely bleſſed? Is not this a marke of holineſſe, to bee proſperous in the world? Would God bleſſe our labours, if we did not ſerue him? May not this change from affliction to proſperitie be a certaine euidence of an inward change from worſe to better, and ſo prooue vnto the fleſh a conceit of <hi>conuerſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely, if the world bee Iudge, the caſe is quickely ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Who is the good man, but the rich man? Either his
<pb facs="tcp:21476:7"/>
riches ſhall be the cloake to hide his faults by greatneſſe, bribery, cunning packing, friendſhip, &amp;c. or his euill by the <hi>flattery</hi> of the world ſhall be accounted good, he will not doe ſo for his credit: he needs not ſteale, oppreſſe: he hath wheren it hall: his couetouſneſſe is thrift; his pride, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; his prodigality, bounty; his looſeneſſe, liberty and prerogatiue Hath he not power of all in his hands? And may he not doe what he liſt? Is not his luſt a law, his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample a rule and warrant? He feares no trouble; therefore he deſerues none. Who can ſay <hi>Blacke is his eye?</hi> becauſe, who dares ſay ſo? Nay, who will not ſay, blacke is white, if it may pleaſe him? Thus proſperity makes a conuert, if the world may giue in euidence.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially if our fulneſſe in the world be graced with ſome ciuill calling, whereby we are honoured of the people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>8.</hi> Ciuil calling.</note> and taken vp with imploiments; is not idleneſſe now much preuented, and ſo ſuch ſinnes as doe accompany the ſame? Doth not credit now reſtraine, where conſcience can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not? Is there not now a cloake for ſinne, and countenance for iniquity? What defence is fathered hence for neglect of ſpirituall duties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What opportunity offered, to colour oppreſſion and deceit? What pretence for licentiouſneſſe, and exceſſe in the abuſe of the creatures? What <hi>wrapping</hi> vp of abuſes, where there is fellowſhip in euill? Is not here a glorious maske, for ſincerity and religion, where out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward honeſty in a ciuill calling becomes a warrant of <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe,</hi> ſeeing our <hi>faith is ſhewed by workes?</hi> Are we not true and iust in our dealing, doe we not pay euery man his owne, doe we not helpe our neighbour by truſting him with our goods, being ſurely for him, do we not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine good neighbourhood, by feaſting one another, and making peace among men. And what more obuious and commendable then our ciuill imploiments, ſo beneficiall to the Common-weale ſo neceſſary for our priuate, ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull in the iſſue, as who (in opinion) more bleſſed? What is it, if not godlineſſe, that is ſo plentifully recompenced in this life? If now the wicked eat the labours of their hands,
<pb facs="tcp:21476:8"/>
and drinke their wine in bowles, may they not ſacrifice to their nets? May they not crie ay me vnto their ſoules, Oh well is thee, and happy ſhalt thou be? Thus ciuill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiment with worldlings is accounted religion: and to be morally iuſt and true in contracts and bargaines, goes cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant with men for ſtanch and ſound holineſſe.</p>
            <p>But if we enter into Gods ſanctuary, and by the rule of the word determine hereof; Is not the Lord good vnto all, and doe we know loue or hatred by theſe things. Eccl. <hi>9.1.</hi> Nay is not proſperity the portion of the wicked. Pſal. <hi>17.14.</hi> Are they not hereby fatted vp to the day of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Ierem. <hi>12.3.</hi> Is not an hypocrite in affliction, an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt and mocker in proſperity. Is not a proſelite in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, an Apoſtate and Blaſphemer in affliction. Haue not the beſt loſt by proſperity, and are not the worſt made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable thereby? doth it not vſually peruert and ſpoile them of what they ſeemed to haue had, breaking all bonds of ciuill honeſty, and ſo makes them worſe then bruit beaſts, without vnderſtanding. Doe not the poore receiue the Goſpell, when the rich and mighty are ſent empty away, becauſe either they cannot come, or come with their outward man: their hearts runne after their couetouſnes: Is the word entertained with ſuch, otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſtate or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plement, or elſe to make them merry. To condemn the raſhneſſe and folly of ſuch as will reproue, or to deride their flattery, that will call light darkneſſe, muſt it not dance after our pipe, and ſerue our luſts, to harden vs in ſinne and ripen vs to vengeance. Is not thus the proſperity of the wicked their deſtruction,<note place="margin">Prou. 1. Pſal 55. Ier. 48.11.</note> and not their conuerſion? Doth not the old ſent remaine in <hi>Moab,</hi> becauſe he was not changed from veſſell to veſſell, but enioyed conſtant proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity thereby, was ſetled on his lees, and rooted more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately in natures dregges, thereby exerciſed more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and deſperately the luſts thereof?<note place="margin">Oſe 4.7. Pſalm 78. Oſe 5.</note> Can the change of the outward eſtate change the inward man from worſe to better? As they were increaſed, ſo, did not Gods people rebel againſt him, who in their afflictions ſought vnto him
<pb facs="tcp:21476:8"/>
deceitfully? Is not here a change from better to worſe? we fawne on God till we haue our deſires, and when our turne is ſerued, then depart from vs Lord, we will not the knowledge of thy waies, what profit ſhall we haue if we ſerue the Almighty. Iob. <hi>21.15.16</hi> We haue now no need of God, and therefore it is in vaine to ſerue him.</p>
            <p>As for walking in a ciuill calling,<note place="margin">Ciuill honeſty no euidence of conuerſion.</note> howſoeuer this (being ſanctified by the <hi>ſpirituall</hi>) may be a meanes to lay vp a good foundation againſt the day of Chriſt. <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>6.19.20</hi> yet to the naturall man there is not a more dangerous outward meanes to exclude grace, then the greateſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of honeſty that is ſeene therein. For is it not the grace of this calling <hi>to reſt in it ſelfe,</hi> for good ſucceſſe, without inuocation of Gods aſſiſtance, or reference to his bleſſing? Is not our purſuit hereof a priuiledge to exempt from holy duties, We muſt liue, and therefore we cannot be bookiſh. We haue no leaſure to the Church. Or is it not enough to come when we may haue leiſure? Is it not ſufficient that we are not Papiſts in profeſſion, though we are Papiſts in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and prophanation to; yea groſſe Idolaters in making our belly our God, the world our confidence: Is it not meritorious that we giue almes, and receiue our maker once a yeere. Pſal. <hi>15.4.</hi> that we are no whores nor theeues, we doe no body any wrong: we liue of our own, doth not this vtterly exclude religion in the family? doth it not ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all loue to the power of religion? doth it not extinguiſh all ſenſe of inward corruption. Is it not to ſticke in the forme of Religion, and ſo to renounce the power thereof. Is not this to ſay in our hearts there is no God, ſeeing he is onely in our lippes and not in our raynes, do we not deny him in our liues, and carnall worſhip, who is a ſpirit and will be worſhipped in ſpirit and truth: howſoeuer we boaſt that we know him enough? And doe our mouthes otherwiſe acknowledge him then at beſt, by prophaning his great name, and blaſpheming it ordinarily in our daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication? Nay, is it not a price propoſed to incourage di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in theſe worldly buſineſſes, euen licence to prophane
<pb facs="tcp:21476:9"/>
the Sabbaths, to deſpiſe the word? &amp;c. And what if men keepe touch and day in paiments and contracts? What if a little eie ſeruice be vſed in the outſide of their wares. Is it for conſcience to God, to whom they deſire to approue the truth of their hearts, or onely a care for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of trading, and mutuall commerce, which without this outward ſeeming equity muſt needs be aboliſhed? Who will truſt, or ſhall be truſted, if word be not kept? But is it kept any further, then may cleere from touch of mans law? Is promiſe <hi>kept here to our hinderance,</hi> ſo we may winde out by the arme of fleſh? Is the ſubſtance of our wares any thing leſſe then anſwerable to the ſhew? Is not God robbed of his glory, while we ſacrifice to our labour and wit? <hi>Is not this great Babel, which I haue built for the honor of my name?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.1.</note>Surely as theſe outward things are common to all: ſo no man knoweth loue or hatred, either by proſperity or aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. Well may a good man (by right vſage) make theſe good vnto him; but theſe of themſelues may well make him worſe: otherwiſe they haue no power inwardly to better him Onely it belongeth vnto God (through the miniſtery of his word) to conuert the ſoule, as tendring (to this end) vnto vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 1. Per. 1.18.</note> not corruptible things, as <hi>ſiluer</hi> and <hi>gold,</hi> which make outwardly happy in this life; but <hi>the precious blood of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>as a Lambe vndefiled, &amp; without ſpot,</hi> whreby we are cleanſed from all our ſinnes, and redeemed from our vaine conuerſation, receiued by the tradition of the fathers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8. <hi>Profeſsion Practiſe.</hi> Math. 7. Luke 8, Mark. 6.25.</note>But harken I pray you, vnto a further plea of the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite: <hi>Haue we not heard thee teaching in our ſtreets?</hi> Nay, <hi>Haue we not taught in thy name? Haue we not receiued the word with ioy, and done many things</hi> accordingly? Can the beſt doe more? Doe not we in many things offend all? Is not this a ſufficient euidence of an effectuall conuerſion?</p>
            <p>Surely where the grace of God which bringeth ſaluation to all men,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> hath appeared effectually, there it teacheth
<pb facs="tcp:21476:9"/>
vs, not onely to eſchew all euill, in thought,<note place="margin">Math. 5. Act. 15.19.</note> warde and deed; but on the contrary to proſecute all good, both <hi>1. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly</hi> in heart and minde, as being <hi>purified by faith,</hi> whereby with conſtant purpoſe we cleane vnto God, and alſo <hi>2. outwardly</hi> in the life and conuerſation: <hi>Iam. 3.1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 11.23.</note> 
               <hi>Epheſ. 1. Rom. 12.1. 1. Cor. 6.</hi> yea <hi>generally and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally, hauing reſpect to all Gods commandements: Pſal. 119.7.8.</hi> and <hi>conſtantly,</hi> alſo continuing and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, yea <hi>increaſing</hi> in grace, and <hi>finiſhing</hi> our courſe, that no man take away our Crowne: <hi>Reuel. 3. 1. Cor. 15.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Profeſsion and ſome practiſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of true conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. 2. Cor. 2.14. Ioh 15. Pſal. 119. Ezech. 33.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 31. Heb. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>58. Epheſ. 3. Colloſ. 1.2. Pet. 1.8.9. 2. Tim. 4.3. Phil. 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore ſeeing the word of God muſt be a ſauour of death vnto death, vnto ſome who are to bee renounced, and made inexcuſable thereby; hence is it, that though they receiue it <hi>1.</hi> with <hi>ioy,</hi> as being rauiſhed with the ſweetneſſe thereof; yet being not <hi>mixed with faith,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes vnprofitable; yea a witneſſe aegainſt them, and ſo the ioy of the hypocrite laſteth but a moment, hee is like to bee beaten with more ſtripes, becauſe hee knowes his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will, and doth it not: <hi>Math. 12.47.</hi> yea though it commeth alſo to paſſe, that for carnall reſpects, as vaine-glorie, credit, ſatisfaction of others, whom they deſire to be like, the hypocrite alſo may <hi>do many things</hi> according to the <hi>letter of the word,</hi> though not anſwerable to the power thereof; nor from the purpoſe of his heart, renued by the holie Ghoſt; but executing therein the luſt of his heart, as ſpirituall pride, hypocriſie, &amp;c. Yet neither ſhall he be able to continue in any ſubstance of well-doing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath no root; how ſoeuer for his credit and profite he muſt ſometimes ſhew religious, yet by reaſon of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of companie, change of times and occaſions, he muſt euen for the ſame ends of credit and profite, caſt off his viſour of holineſſe, and ſo appeare in his true likeneſſe, to the ſatisfying of ſuch, to whom nothing but groſſe and deſperate wickedneſſe will giue any contentment. This is certaine, that as the hypocrite in his beſt deuotions,
<pb facs="tcp:21476:10"/>
aymes onlie at carnall ends, ſo in his beſt worſhip he faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons himſelfe to the world, and meaſures himſelf by it loue: either he muſt only goe, and ſo farre as the time will beare, or his leaders go before, or fleſh and blood will brooke; and it is his wiſedome to turne with the time, to be ruled by his betters, to bee indifferent to all ſtraines, that ſo hee may gaine by all. Nay doth not this neceſſity lie vpon the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, that howſoeuer for a time he muſt gloſe and fawne vpon the truth, while it is his pack horſe to further him to promotion, riches, &amp;c. yet when by plunging himſelfe into worldly courſes, he muſt neceſſarily croſſe in his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward actions, the power of that truth which he makes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of, and ſo thereby wound and gall his conſcience: muſt he not now for his credit abaſe and vilifie that truth which before hee ſo magnified? as being either too ſeuere and preciſe becauſe he cannot reach it:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> or being fooliſhnes and madneſſe: and therefore he is now more wiſe, more ſober, then to be guided by it. you muſt pardon his former folly and giddineſſe: he will do no more ſo; he will be more wiſe, moderate, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And all this but a colour to hide or eaſe his wounded conſcience, which not being able to endure the power of the word, muſt therefore in wiſedome reiect it; and ſo flie vnto carnall Phyſicke, to purge out melancholie, and yet ſtill vnder pretence of Chriſtian libertie, that hee hath knowledge enough, and yet more deſperately to deceiue himſelfe hereby and others, as preſeruing an opinion of his righteouſneſſe, as if hee were vniuſtly chalenged, and therefore may iuſtlie except againſt this euidence, and ſo preuenting ſound repentance, and thereby, caſting off the bridle, giues libertie to ſinne, and ſo haſteneth vengeance.</p>
            <p>This is the iſſue of an hypocrites ſuppoſed conuerſion, anſwerable euen vnto the meaſure thereof: which being not rooted in the heart, nor aiming at Gods glory, no maruell if the glory of an hypocrite prooue his confuſion. And is hee not iuſtly deceiued in this fancie
<pb facs="tcp:21476:10"/>
of regeneration? Is he not hereby excluded from the power of conuerſion, becauſe hee reſteth in the ſhadow thereof?</p>
            <p>But to admit a true conuerſion: Is the combate now at an end? or not rather now begun? Is there any place here for idleneſſe, ſecurity, remiſneſſe in our calling? Surely though the foundation ſtandeth ſure in reſpect of God,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.19 2 Pet. 1.10</note> who knoweth who are his; yet it lieth much in vs, either to make ſure and beautifie the building, by being watchfull and diligent in well-doing;<note place="margin">2 Phil. 12 Pſal. 51 Pſal. 73 Malach. 3</note> or elſe by our negligence and ſecurity, to deface and interrupt it, yea many times to our <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>feeling,</hi> euen vtterly to ouerthrow the ſame. For proofe heereof, take wee wiſely a ſcantling of the times wherein we liue, and then lay we thereto ſuch expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience as this Treatiſe affoordeth.</p>
            <p>Concerning our times it may not bee denyed, but that our meanes might haue yeelded ſuch a growth in holineſſe as by the time wee might all haue been tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of others, in regard of our aboundant meaſure of knowledge: yea we might haue been leaders to other Nations in the power and practiſe of godlineſſe, hauing by Gods mercy ſuch liuely preſidents of ſanctification ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs: And therefore, as wee ſtand only vpon our name, and credit of profeſſion, it muſt be aſſumed, that ſeeing we haue had ſuch meanes, therefore the Lord ſhall finde no iniquity in vs, that were ſhame and wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">Oſe 12 1 Reg. 22</note> ſeeing God hath a few names among vs, that walke in white, and keepe themſelues vndefiled from the great offence. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when went the ſpirit of God from vs vnto them? why ſhould they that haue had the ſame meanes yeeld alſo like fruit of conſcionable obedience? why ſhould not we ſtand vpon our holines with the beſt: ſeeing we haue found out riches in all our labours: God proſpereth vs in our affaires abroad, and all is peace and huſht at home;<note place="margin">Zach. 11.5 Reuel 31 7</note> and therefore bleſſed be God, for we are rich, and increaſed with goods, and haue need of nothing: Thus as the bountifull loue could doe nothing vnto vs which he hath not done, ſo if
<pb facs="tcp:21476:11"/>
our owne words will be taken,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saul.</hi> 1 Sam. 15 Eſay 66.5 Ioh. 26.1.</note> wee haue fulfilled the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of our God, all the Congregation is holie, whatſoeuer we doe, let the Lord be glorified, we thinke we doe God good ſeruice, in casting out of the Synagogues. Thus continuance of gratious meanes brings vs to a forme of godlineſſe and the forme of godlineſſe prouokes vs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the power thereof, that ſo we might be more inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe we cannot plead ignorance nor iuſtly chalenge our God of any failing towards vs: and haſten hereby vpon vs the iuſt iudgement of God, becauſe we hate that in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whereof we aſſume the glory, and deny that in our obedience, which we arrogate as our chiefeſt hold in the fauour of God, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord. And ſhall not then our glory be our ſhame, becauſe we are earthly minded; and doth not our ſecuritie in this eſtate, preſage ſpeedie vengeance? And is not the ſickle alreadie put in? haue wee not ſharpened the ſword that threatens our deſtruction? ſhall the Lord repent him of any euill he intends towards vs, ſeeing wee harden our hearts daylie, and will not repent? Will the Lord be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto vs, ſeeing mercie and compaſſion is baniſhed from among vs? Euery one ſeekes his owne, and not each others good, our mercies are plaine cruelties, our tables ſnares, our loue to the fleſh the betraying the ſoul? thus leſt we ſhould be counted non proficients, we preſume of practiſe anſwerable to the meanes, And hereby we would ſeeme to haue hit the iuſt meaſure of holineſſe, becauſe wee compell others to our meaſure, and ſtent them by our line, as if wee were abſolute paternes to them of godlineſſe, as if whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer were beyond our compaſſe, were ſuperfluous, and exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant. If now it pleaſe God to awaken the conſcience of any that hath bene ouertaken with the deceitfulneſſe of the time, or otherwiſe damped with the ſecurity thereof: ſo that he beginnes to bethinke himſelfe, and remember whence he hath fallen: is it not the policie to ſtoppe his mouth with offals of the world, to drowne him in pleaſure, to ariue away melancholie, to drink away this hart qualms
<pb facs="tcp:21476:11"/>
or play it away, in abuſe of Chriſtian libertie. Or if yet the Lord maintaine his controuerſie, by the terrors of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to bring to repentance: Oh then the cry is, that he is mad, or deſperate, a foole, or an hypocrite. Thus are the hearts of Gods children more caſt downe, whom the Lord hath humbled, and all to maintaine our ſeeming hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, all this to harden our hearts, that we may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. And haue we not to this purpoſe in great eſtimation, many accurſed and damnable engines of Satan, the rather yet to harden the heart, by making a mocke of ſinne? What ſhall we conceiue of that common practiſe? let no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue: ſinne muſt not be dealt withall in earneſt, loſt our confidence be confounded: or if it muſt bee dealt withall, then let vs heare of it in ieſt, it muſt bee taught vpon the ſtage, and yet made matter to ſport with, that ſo wee may account it but a ſport, that ſo the foole may make a mocke of ſinne ſurely, though bleſſed be God, ſinne goes not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controuled, and that by Gods holy ordinance to conuince and confound the ſame: yet is not the ſacred word of God made a ieſt of too: a ſubiect for ſtage playes, a by-word at tables, that ſo we may yet more deſperatly ſcorne the ſame and ſo yet further harden our hearts, that we may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. And though the glorious Lord hath euen from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen auenged his cauſe againſt thoſe horrible Theators of all abomination, burning one of them to the ground, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting daylie the markes of his wrath vpon them, by madnes, epilepſie, &amp;c. yet will not the filthy bee filthy ſtill? Muſt they not ſtill remaine to be factors for Popery: brokers for Atheiſme, and bauds to all odious wickedneſſe, so ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the pride of our holy mountaine; to nouzle in ſecurity; as if wee now had leiſure ſtill to play, as if ſtill wee might doe nought elſe, but eat and drinke, and riſe vp to make our ſelues merry with ſurfeiting on the ſinnes of others. And hath Satan compaſſed in vaine by theſe his wiles? Is not Popery encreaſing, and growne to ſome hope to build <hi>Iericho</hi> againe. Doth not cloſe Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme abound generally, the Lord is acknowledged in word,
<pb facs="tcp:21476:12"/>
but in our works we do deny him? Doth not groſſe and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable Atheiſme raigne aloft in our curſed blaſphemies of God in taking his glorious Name in vain:<note place="margin">Iude 15</note> Is not this the crown of our pride to draw neer vnto God with our lippes, when our hearts are far from him: and is not our glory our ſhame:<note place="margin">Eſay 29 Iob 3</note> becauſe we with the ſame mouth breath out curſing &amp; bleſſings? Is not this another bitter fruit of this accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed tree, to pretend what we are not, nor euer meane to be? And hath not deſperat prophaneſſe hence got his ſtrength? Is not liberty giuen hereby to all licentiouſneſſe? Doth not Popery on the one ſide ſatisfie the fleſh whiles it pretends to haue it in no eſtimation, nouriſhing the pride of the fleſh in voluntary deuotions, iuſtifying and ſatisfying the luſts of the fleſh, vnder a pretence of wiſdome, notably diſcouered, in auricular confeſſions, in indulgences, voluntary vowes, counſels of perfection, &amp;c. pretending perfection, to cloak ſin, that we may not be chalenged for it, confeſſing ſin, that we may commit it more greedily, vowing continence &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, that we may enioy the contrary more ſecretly, &amp; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pardon for ſinne, that we may practiſe it more ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And doeth not Atheiſme on the other ſide encreaſe the ſcore, giuing the bridle more deſperately vnto ſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord is hid in the clouds, and will neither do good nor euill, becauſe he forbeares, therefore he is like vnto vs, he likes of our ſinne: or els we ſay in our hearts, there is no God at all: no hell for ſinners, but to be hindered in ſinne, no Heauen, but this, to ſatisfie the luſts of the fleſh: And doth not hypocriſie now make vp the meaſure, preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming on Gods mercy, that we may ſinne continually, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending infirmities, that we may be borne withall howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, resting on the forme of godlineſſe, to cloake any deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate wickedneſſe: Therefore we ſhall be deliuered, though we haue committed all theſe abominations; becauſe we are Christians, the iuſt Temple of the Lord is with vs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhall ſee no iniquitie, and ſtinting Religion to fleſh and blood, that ſo fleſh and blood may take it ſwing, and thereon be moſt religious,<note place="margin">Iob 9</note> becauſe it doth it beſt, it cannot
<pb facs="tcp:21476:12"/>
do otherwiſe, it doth what others do: It acknowledgeth no failings, and therefore it makes vp it meaſure: therefore ſinne remaines vpon it, becauſe it ſees no ſinne, it acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth no iniquity. And doth not the kingdome of Satan ſwarme hereby, and therefore ſhall not the hypotrites bee beaten with more ſtripes: The Lord make vs wiſe to ſee the plague, and hide our ſelues. Hath not the Lord been as a moth vnto Iſrael, and to the houſe of Iudah as rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: haue we not a name of peace, and yet behold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diuiſions and heart burnings on all ſides, <hi>Ephraim</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and both againſt <hi>Iuda.</hi> Doe we not boaſt of aboundance, and yet behold ſcarſitie, our wealth moltereth away, and wee know not how we enioy outward peace on all ſides, and yet are impoueriſhed hereby, whereas our neighbours are inri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with continuall warres, we ſow much, and reape litle, and what we bring in is put into a broken bagge: Doth not the iuſt Lord ſecretlie blow vpon vs, becauſe wee preferre not Ieruſalem before all our mirth. The Lord giue vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding in theſe things. Haue we not a bleſſed peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able gouernment, and yet ſtill remaine diſcontent? Haue we not aboundance of the Goſpell, and yet grow worſe and worſe. And is not this an argument of inward rottennes: Though our pretences are glorious, and meanes to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet haue we for the moſt part, yeelded any better fruit then moathie rottenneſſe, fained ſhewes without inward ſoundnes? Bleſſed bee God in Ieſus Chriſt, that yet the meanes are continued vnto vs, is not there yet hope of our repentance? is not this the way ſpeedily to effect it: euen to lay the axe to the roote of the tree. Behold how the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit here deales with this Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and take this for thy glaſſe to behold thy preſent ſtate in: diſcerne wiſely what thou haſt receiued, &amp; if thou haſt left thy firſt hold, learne to take holde again by vnfained repentance. It is no ſhame to be chalengd of failings for the beſt ar not without &amp; it ſhalbe thy wiſdom to reform the leaſt ſeing otherwiſe thy God may come againſt thee. For thy better enabling herein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21476:13"/>Peruſe this <hi>treatiſe enſuing:</hi> let it be in Gods feare, a <hi>touch-ſtone</hi> vnto thee, to make triall of a <hi>ſound conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and take it as a <hi>preſeruatiue,</hi> to keepe thee in the power of godlineſſe, that ſo thou mayſt not leaue thy firſt loue. If by <hi>pride</hi> or <hi>ſecurity</hi> thou haſt bene left to thy ſelfe, and ſo haſt left thy former meaſure: view thy ſelfe diligently in this preſent glaſſe, and vſe it as a meanes for thy recouerie and perſeuerance. If by ſecond thoughts, thou haſt now gained more light: glorifie God for any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and comfort thy ſelfe, that thou maiſt alſo encreaſe yet remember that we are ſtill to grow: and therefore, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect not what may be ſaid, ſeeing my health and ſtudy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foords only breuitie, and my manifold afflictions might haue occaſioned a decreaſe, or at leaſt haue cut off all liberty to impart my ſtore vnto thee: and therefore bleſſe God the rather, for this lengthening of dayes and do not diſtaſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſmels of the ſmoake, leaſt if thou feare affliction, thou ſhalt find no comfort herein. And let me againe aduiſe thee, not to ſtare vpon the colour which happily may bleare thine eyes, but to looke into the woofe, to humble thine heart. Neither miſconſtruing what may be well digested, left thou bee peruerted by a ſtumbling blocke, nor deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the pearle,<note place="margin">Math. 22.14</note> becauſe it is vnpoliſhed, leaſt thou looſe the nut, becauſe thou canſt not crack the ſhell. Though many are called, yet but few are choſen: and therfore if few digeſt this pill: let them not condemne the phyſicke, but their own il-diſpoſed hearts.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6, 7</note> Thoſe that can get meat out of the eater and ſweetneſſe out of the ſtrong, let them praiſe the glorious Lord,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12</note> who bringeth light out of darkeneſſe, and not ceaſe praying vnto our gracious Father, that he would turne our darkneſſe into light, and enable vs to worke while yet wee haue the light: that ſo we may approue our ſelues the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the light, and be prepared to that light which ſhall neuer be changed into darknes. Euen ſo be it. <hi>Come Lord Ieſus. Come quickely.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In whom I reſt thine vnfainedly, THOMAS COOPER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21476:13"/>
            <head>PARTICVLAR OBSERVATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Caſes, and Conſcience treated herein.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The ſupplie of a powerfull Miniſtery, is a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious meanes of reformation.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Caſe. How to diſcerne our eſtate in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of God, by the vſe of the word.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The beſt haue their infirmities, and are ſubiect to grieuous ſinnes.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Why infirmities abide in the Saints.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Caſo. How nie our eſtate in ſanctification by infirmities.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Sinne to be ſtriuen againſt, though we cannot poſsibly ſubdue it wholly in this life.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Sinne is to be reprooued.
<list>
                     <item>Caſe <hi>1.</hi> How to reprooue ſinne.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Triall of our estates by enduring reproofe.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> The leaſt ſinne in the Saints is ſufficient to make the Lord to come againſt them.
<list>
                     <item>Caſe <hi>1.</hi> Why God chasteneth ſinne in this life.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> How God puniſheth ſinne in his children, which he hath puniſhed in his Sonne.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> How to make peace with God in our corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and try our eſtate in grace thereby.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5. Queſt.</hi> How the Church may be ſaid to leaue her first loue, ſeeing ſhe is commended before, that ſhe fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Sinne of omiſsion to be ſeuerely reprooued.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> The Elect muſt goe forward, and perſeuere in grace.
<list>
                     <item>Caſe <hi>1.</hi> Why perſeuerance and growth in grace is neceſſary.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:21476:14"/>
                        <hi>2.</hi> How to grow in grace:
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> By auoiding Apoſtaſie.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> What are the meanee of Apoſtaſie, namely,
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> Corrupt iudgement. It markes on the left hand, and on the right.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2.</hi> Corrupt practiſe. It man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and ſignes, and that on the left hand, and on the right.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Motiues to prouoke vs to conſtancy in well-doing.</item>
                     <item>Meanes to enable vs to grow and encreaſe.</item>
                     <item>Meanes to preuent Apoſtaſie in the ſenſe of our fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</item>
                     <item>Markes of triall, that we haue thriuen in grace.</item>
                     <item>Doct. <hi>8.</hi> Euery true conuert hath a firſt loue.
<list>
                           <item>Caſe. The markes of firſt loue.</item>
                           <item>The reaſons why God vouchſafeth his firſt loue vnto thoſe that are conuerted vpon their firſt calling.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Doct. <hi>8.</hi> The Saints may leaue their firſt loue.
<list>
                           <item>Caſe. Meanes whereby firſt loue is loſt twofold.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Withdrawing that which may cheriſh: what this is:</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Adding that which may coole. What theſe are.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Namely <hi>1.</hi> Spirituall Pride, how this cooleth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayeth loue, and how to remedy it: what is falſly reputed ſpiritual pride, &amp; the remedy.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Carnall policie, by what meanes this abateth firſt loue:
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> How a friend to Religion.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> How our enemie.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Proſperitie, how firſt loue is hereby decayed, and it remedie.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Abuſe of Chriſtian libertie, how this decayes
<pb facs="tcp:21476:14"/>
this loue, with the remedie.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> A corrupt and dead miniſterie, that this alſo cooleth firſt loue, and by what meanes, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the remedie. Here obſerue</item>
                     <item>Falſe imputations of leauing firſt loue.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Caſe 1. In the right vſe of their Christian libertie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> By enioying proſperitie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> By vſe of ſpiritual wiſdome in auoiding of trobles.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Faith how and when to be giuen account of, and to whom.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> How to diſcerne inward ſufficiencie, to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen profeſsion of faith in the time of trouble.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> How to diſcerne an outward calling to witneſſe to the truth in perilous times.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Wherein we may be ſilent, and how.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Names &amp; habits, whether in affliction they may be changed in times of perſecution, and how far. That</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Apparell may be changed, and how farre. Other imputations of leauing firſt loue, as</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Diſcretion in reproouing ſinne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Outward and inward afflictions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Honeſt prouiſion for the familie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Libertie in the vſe of things indifferent.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Whether want of former feelings of ioy, may be an imputation.</item>
               <item>Caſe That we haue left our firſt loue.</item>
               <item>Gods prouidence and reſolution of iudgement herein.</item>
               <item>Iuſt occaſions of this want of feeling of comfort from our ſelues.</item>
               <item>Caſe. How to behaue our ſelues in this want of ioy.</item>
               <item>Meanes to reſiſt tentations that ariſe from this want of comfort.
<list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:21476:15"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> To remember the ſuffering of Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> And his glorious conqueſts.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> That this is an argument of the ſoundnes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> That theſe inward buffetings preuent outward baites of pleaſure.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> That God is able to deliuer vs, proued by many reaſons.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> That he will deliuer vs.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> That the time is not paſt.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> That the ſtronger tentations, the ſhorter and and more comfortable iſſue.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> This is a means to try &amp; renue ſound repentance.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>10.</hi> God knoweth what is fitteſt for vs.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>11.</hi> Satans tentations preuented by accuſing of our ſelues.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>12.</hi> That we are not the greateſt ſinners yet.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>13.</hi> It is not vnpofitable to conceiue our ſelues to bee the greateſt ſinners. To this end,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>14.</hi> Call to mind former mercies.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>15.</hi> That God differs our refreſhing in great mercy.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>16.</hi> That we muſt not iudge our ſelues by our tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or condition therein.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>17.</hi> That al the ſaints haue drunk of this cup vnto thee</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Doct. <hi>9.</hi> That the Saints may leaue their firſt loue.
<list>
                     <item>Caſe. The ſymptoms therof: And effects of the ſame.
<list>
                           <item>Meanes of recouery.</item>
                           <item>How farre they ſhall recouer.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Doct. <hi>10.</hi> That the Saints ſhall not fall finally.
<list>
                     <item>Caſe. How farre they may fall.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Difference between lukewarmnes, &amp; leauing firſt loue And betweene leauing of firſt loue, and looſing it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21476:15"/>
            <head>A PRESERVATIVE <hi>againſt Apoſtacie.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVELAT. 2.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Neuertheleſſe I haue ſomewhat againſt thee: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt left thy firſt Loue.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr bleſſed Sauiour, hauing by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of his Apoſtles planted diuers Churches in <hi>Aſia:</hi> directeth his ſeruant <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt, to write vnto each of them, for their further ſtrengthning in the faith. And, becauſe the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Occaſion and coherence.</note> was both famous for the outward glorie, and inward gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof, as alſo in a ſort the peculiar charge of the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 1.</note> therefore doth hee firſt ſend greeting to that Church; giuing very iuſt and true teſtimonie vnto her of the great graces of God beſtowed vpon her, and her profitable vſe of them, in the ſecond and third verſes. And that ſhe might not be ouercome of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall pride, to which in regard of ſuch excellent graces ſhe might be ſubiect; yea, was ſo tainted therewith, as that it wrought in her ſome ſecuritie, and therevpon remiſſeneſſe: hee therefore giues her notice of this her decay and cooling in the fourth verſe: telling her that <hi>He had ſomewhat againſt her, becauſe ſhee had left her firſt loue;</hi> both therein expreſſing the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her fall, by the excellencie of the thing wherein ſhe failed, namely, her firſt loue; as alſo, ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauating this her fall, by the iuſt eſteeme therof in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21476:16"/>
iudgement of her Sauiour Chriſt: namely, that it gaue occaſion for him, that was her aduocate, now to come againſt her, and to haue a controuerſie with her, as an enemie;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſe.</hi> 4 1. <hi>Lament.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 31.</note> and thereby giuing her to conceiue in what a fearefull caſe ſhe ſtood, hauing him now to be againſt her; who if he were on her ſide, ſhee need not feare who were againſt her; who being againſt her, all other things, though with her, muſt neceſſarilie ſerue to her further condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Summe and ſenſe.</note>So that theſe words, doe containe a deſcription of ſome declination in this Church of Epheſus, with ſome arguments, to lay this her eſtate more cloſely to her heart, that ſo ſhee might be preuented of further Apoſtacie, and ſo by repentance recouer her ſelfe againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Scope and intent of the Spirit of God herein.</note>And the drift and purpoſe of the Holy Ghoſt herein, is by this ſeaſonable reproofe to preuent further apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie, and ſo by raiſing vp this Church againe out of this decay, thereby to lead her forward gratiouſly to perfection.</p>
            <p>Wherein firſt we may behold the ſingular wiſdome and mercie of God vnto this poore decaied Church, that intending heartily the recouerie thereof, and ſo to bring it forward in grace, he doth gratiouſly ſupply vnto it the effectuall meanes of it raiſing vp againe. And though hee was abſent in bodie, yet by his ſpirit and word he plies it conſcionably, and calls vpon it by his mightie word to awake out of it ſleepe, and ſtand vp from the dead that Chriſt may reuiue it againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The ſupply of a powerful miniſterie is a gratious meanes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</note>Whence we may obſerue, That where the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues a powerfull Miniſterie to his Church, there howſoeuer there may bee ſome decaies and groſſe corruptions, yet there is hope in Iſrael concerning this. Either the Church viſible ſhall recouer it former glory and beauty, or at leaſt the elect ſhall hereby be bettered and furthered to perfection.</p>
            <p>This we ſee to be manifeſt in the Church of Corinth,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21476:16"/>
which though it was degenerate not only into many foule corruptions in life,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> but alſo to many errors in doctrine: yet ſo long as the bleſſed Apoſtle by his faithfull and zealous labours watched ouer the ſame, and reproued it for it faylings, as 1. Cor. 3. 1. Cor. 5. &amp;c. it gratiouſly reformed many grieuous euils, and ſo was kept on foote in the power of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>This alſo is apparant in the Church of the Iewes: which though it fell away to many horrible corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and groſſe idolatrie; yet by the Miniſterie of the Prophets it was eftſoones reclaymed, and attayned at ſeuerall times, many glorious reformations, as in the times of <hi>Aſa, Ezechiah,</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> 2. Chron. 15. 2. Chron. 30.31. 2. Chron. 34. &amp;c. yea it was not paſt hope of recouerie, it was not vtterly giuen vp to that abomination of deſolation, vntill it had vtterly reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the word of the Prophets, and grew to perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch, as ſought to reclaime them, as appeareth 2. Reg. 18.14.15. 2. Chron. 36.14.15.16. And the reaſons hereof are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the power of the word is Gods onely ordinance, as to plant a Church, ſo alſo to water, and increaſe the ſame to perfection, 2. Pet. 1.1, 2. Epheſ. 4.5.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Church of God, hath as much or rather more need of the word after it is planted, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther growth thereof, then it had for the firſt founding and eſtabliſhing of the ſame. And that,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe, hauing now taſted how ſweet the Lord Ieſus is, in his holy ordinances, it will now more hunger and thirſt after further comfort, till it be made meet for that glorious inheritance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, No Church at the firſt planting, can be ſo perfectly ſet in order, but that ſtill it may and ought to grow and increaſe: though happily the Forme thereof may be perfect, yet their ſubmitting to that Forme, muſt be wrought by degrees, they will not at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21476:17"/>
the firſt ſo eaſily digeſt the ſtrictnes thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Eſpecially if wee conſider, that now Satan will ſteppe in, by all meanes to hinder our ſubiection to the ordinances of God: either labouring to diſtract or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioint,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4, 5, 6.</note> by inward diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; or by outward perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſee king vtterly to ouerthrow. And haue we not then ſtill need of the Word within, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſe all differences? had we not need of the word to quench all the fierie darts of Satan, to preuent his ſtratagems, or elſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found them?</p>
            <p n="4">4. And ſeeing we muſt daily grow and increaſe to perfection, can wee thriue without daily food? muſt we not neceſſarilie fall away, and pine vtterly, vnleſſe we be ſuſtained conſtantly by this comfortable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note>And therefore, Firſt they are here reproued that conceiue that the Word indeed is neceſſarie for the planting, &amp; gathering of a Church, but when it can go alone, they conclude it is needleſſe, or at leaſt indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, we may doe well enough without it: wee may haue it for ſtate, and ornament, to maintaine the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward name, but for vs, wee haue knowledge enough, wee are ſure of our eſtates, we feare no dangers, and therefore let vs preuent none.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This ſerues for reproofe of the ordinarie Miniſterie, that eſteeme places of Charge, rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of former paines and ſtudie, then any neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie bonds to tie vs to further paines. Either being painefull only in the Vniuerſities &amp; Seminaries to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their ſeed, but neglecting to ſcatter it, &amp; ſo grow idle when they are called into the Vineyard; or if for credit and profit they will take paines at their firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into a Charge, that they may gaine an opinion of learning, and ſo ſettle them for their further aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, yet are after willing to frame to the preſent ſtate of their people, nouzeling them in ignorance, that ſo they may rule them better, and encouraging them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21476:17"/>
in any groſſe prophaning of the Sabaoth, vnder pretence of Chriſtian libertie, and good neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, that ſo they may bee more eaſily and fully fed by them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Alſo here is met withall, that damnable and Atheiſticall Poſition, <hi>That we may haue too much knowledge, too much Teaching,</hi> That it puffes vp the people, and makes them new fangled. Seeing the truth is, that though the people were better be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, then with that which is mixed with poyſon and trod vnder our feet, for indeed there is too much of that; This generally excuſeth for, or excludeth that which ſhould bee wholeſome: ſo wee haue rather iuſt cauſe to complaine of the want of the other, we ought rather to wiſh that all Gods people could prophecie: we ſhould pray that the Lord would ſtill thruſt out Labourers into his Vineyard, and thruſt out thoſe loyterers and deceiuers of their ſoules: we haue iuſt cauſe to feare, that the Lord hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie with the Land, becauſe the people periſh for want of knowledge, we cannot haue too much of the grace of God, and therefore ought ſtill to haue the Word dwel plentifully with vs to conuay the ſame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Here is matter of inſtruction, to try our eſtates by: That if we are not wearie of the Word, if wee deſire to haue it dwell with vs, not onely in the Church, but in our Families too, to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Guide</hi> of our waies, and <hi>Iudge</hi> of our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to bring vs to daily repentance, this is a ſound euidence, that we were conuerted by it; this is a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious pledge, that wee are growing to perfection. Are wee not hereby taught to cleaue vnto the Word, that ſo by it we may be led along to the full meaſure of the age of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we may hence alſo haue ſome coniecture of the prouidence of God to his Churches, that if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb facs="tcp:21476:18"/>
vnto them the power of the word, howſoeuer they may be tainted with many groſſe corruptions, and fallen away fearefully from their former ſtanding: yet there is hope that they ſhall recouer againe, if they ſubmit in any meaſure to the power thereof. But if once they ſhal begin to put the word from them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13.46.</note> &amp; ſo the iuſt Lord remoues their Candleſtick: though hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily they haue indured the word with much affliction, and eſteemed indeed the ſame as their greateſt croſſe and trouble, as ſtill ſpeaking no good, but euill vnto them: yet now they ſhall finde, what they falſely fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered on the preſence of the word, ſhall iuſtly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them by the abſence thereof; they ſhall be firſt expoſed to the deluſions of falſe Prophets, that being hardned in their ſinne, they may make vp the meaſure thereof: and when the meaſure is made vp, the ſickle ſhall be put in, the wrath of God ſhall lay them deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and roote them out from the face of the earth. And ſhall we not then mourne when the Bridegroom is departed, and the Candleſticke remoouing? may we not herein ſee the plague and hide our ſelues, that ſo wee be not ſwallowed vp with the common deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</hi> Of <hi>comfort.</hi> 1. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of our eſtate to come.</note>Laſtly, hence is matter of exceeding comfort vnto the Saints, not only concerning the certaintie of their eſtate, ſeeing the Lord will neuer leaue them deſtitute of his word, or elſe in ſteed thereof will giue them the Annoynting to abide with them for euer, and to keepe them to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. For ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our eſtate preſent and future in this life.</note>But if in ſuch times of renouncing the power of the word, they ſhall yet make it the delight and ioy of their hearts, cleauing faſter vnto it, the more the world ſeekes libertie, and louing the feete of them that bring theſe glad tydings, howſoeuer in the world they are eſteemed monſtrous perſons, peſtilent fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, not worthy to liue &amp;c. howſoeuer happily, they may endure reproch, and vndergoe many worſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21476:18"/>
afflictions, yet ſhall the word which they obey, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſound comfort vnto them, and alſo preuent more grieuous iudgements: that when the Lord ſhall bring the conſumption decreed vpon the mockers and deſpiſers, then ſhall hee ſet a marke vpon theſe mourners, to ſaue them out of the common wracke, and ſo reſerue them to more glorious and peaceable times. Pſal. 119. Eſay 28.19. Ezech. 9.6.7.</p>
            <p>Thus doth the Lord mercifully ſticke to his Church in the needfull time. And is there not great reaſon ſo to doe? Yea certainely.</p>
            <p>Behold this glorious Church of Epheſus, now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed in her zeale, and if ſhee be once downe, ſhee is like to runne amaine: Though ſhee was planted in perfection, yet ſhe walked not according to that rule, but grew remiſſe in her zeale and loue to the Brethren, and ſo left her firſt loue vnto her God, and ſo is here chalenged thereof by her beſt beloued Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Whence we may learne ſecondly this leſſon.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Doctrine.</hi> The beſt haue their infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and are ſubiect to grieuous ſins.</note> That as the beſt Church, ſo the beſt Chriſtian hath, and may haue ſome infirmities and corruptions; as appeareth by thoſe places: 1. Ioh. 1.9. Iames 3. 2. Chron. 8.36. and by the examples of the beſt: <hi>Dauid,</hi> 2. Sam. 12. commits murder and adulterie; <hi>Peter</hi> denies his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Matth. 27. <hi>Moſes</hi> did not giue glory to God in beleeuing his word; <hi>Noah</hi> was drunken,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Manaſſeth</hi> an horrible Apoſtata, and bloody perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous, &amp;c. Numb 20. Gen. 38. Gen. 9. Thus haue the Saints of God been ſubiect to infirmities, and that not before their conuerſion only, but euen after alſo; as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the name of all the reſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth for himſelfe in the ſeuenth to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans 19.20.21.22.</p>
            <p>And ſurely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.8. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.23.</note> ſeeing the Lord Ieſus hath ſatisfied the wrath of his Father for vs, in fulfilling the Law, and vndergoing the penaltie thereof: and ſo continues daily our Interceſſor and ſuretie, to anſwer vnto the iuſtice of God for our offences, and to obtaine pardon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21476:19"/>
for them: ſo that there is no neceſſitie that we ſhould be freed quite from ſinne, and ſo perfit, as to fulfill the law of God, ſeeing the Lord Ieſus hath performed this already, and therefore for vs to vndertake the ſame, were to intrude into Chriſts office, and ſo to rob him of his glorie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> Therefore that ſome infirmities and corruptions do remaine in vs, ſeeing now the guilt and puniſhment, yea the dominion and rage of ſinne is taken away by Chriſt. It is very conuenient and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that firſt:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſons.</hi> Why infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties remaine in the Saints. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note>1. That Gods free mercie, may be daily aduanced in the pardoning of ſinne, Pſalm. 51.12, 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the merit of Chriſt Ieſus, may be glorified, in ſatisfying for ſinne, Iohn 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That our ſaluation may be better aſſured vnto vs, in the daily experience of Gods loue, in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe and healing of our particular corruptions, 2. Pet. 1.8.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the graces of the ſpirit may be exerciſed in the daily reſiſting and conquering of ſinne, Epheſ. 6.11, 12, 13. 1. Pet. 4.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the power of God may be perfited in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 2. Cor. 12.8, 9. 2. Cor. 4.7, 8.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And the Lord onely might haue the glory of his works in vs, Rom. 4. 2. Cor. 12.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That we may be daily humbled in the ſenſe of our infirmities, and ſo preuenting pride and ſecuritie, we may forget that which is behinde, and haſten to that which is before, Phil. 3.13.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And ſo the conſcience of our daily infirmities, proues a gratious meanes to preuent Apoſtacie, As</p>
            <p n="1">1. Being occaſions daily to ſuſpect our ſelues, and feare our eſtates, and ſo to renue our repentance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To be more watchfull ouer our waies, by how much we are ſubiect to fall.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To redeeme the time and entertaine all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to preuent ſinne, and make ſure our election, ſo to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21476:19"/>
haue our accounts alwayes readie againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And are we not hereby made more compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate towards our brethren, as being ſubiect to like temptations with them. Galath. 6.1. Geneſ. 38.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Doe not the wicked hereby take offence, who ſeeing the infirmities of the Saints; and from thence, their chaſticements, take hence occaſion, to condemne the generation of the iuſt, and to ripen their ſinne by <hi>adding affliction to affliction,</hi> Zach. 1. Pſal. 73. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Are not the Saints prouoked dayly to renounce their owne righteouſneſſe, and flie vnto Chriſt, liuing the life of faith, and contenting themſelues with ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of Gods grace: 2. Cor. 12. Abac. 2.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And ſeeing, that as long as they liue, they ſhall be ſubiect to infirmities: therefore alſo hereby are they weaned from the loue of this life, and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures thereof, which are no better then fuell to their ſinne.</p>
            <p n="13">13. And alſo, prouoked to hunger and ſigh after their diſſolution, that ſo they may be deliuered from this bodie of ſinne: Rom. 7.24.</p>
            <p>And this ſerueth, firſt for <hi>reproofe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſes.</hi> 1. Of <hi>reproofe.</hi> 1. of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</note> and that firſt of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> that boaſteth of merit and perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not acknowledging that to be ſinne which is, and counting that good which is euill, robbing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Chriſt of his glorie, and himſelfe of the aſſurance of his ſaluation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Of the prophane Protestant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Prophane Proteſtant.</note> that flatters himſelfe in his ſinne, with this, That all haue their faults, and the beſt hath ſome infirmities, and therefore he will liue in his ſinne; he hopes to be ſaued as wel as others: what need we make ſo much adoe?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The ignorant Protestant</hi> is heere condemned;<note place="margin">3. The igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> who though in generall he confeſſe that he is a ſinner, yet denieth that he hath in particular broken any of the commandements; he is no whore, no theefe; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21476:20"/>
himſelfe by the letter of the law, and in truth thereby denying that he hath any ſinne at all.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">4. The car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note>4. <hi>The carnall Protestant</hi> is heere alſo conuinced, and that in many reſpects:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that he hates to be reproued; whereby hee would be conceiued righteous, and without fault.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he will not ſtriue againſt his corruptions, becauſe he cannot wholly be rid of them: pleading it to be impoſſible, and ſo in vaine to be attempted. Whereas it is:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Sinne to be ſtriuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt though we cannot fully and wholly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due it in this life.</note>1. The commandement of God to ſtriue againſt ſinne, though it ſtill remaine. Col. 3.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By ſtriuing we conquer ſome groſſe ſinnes, as ſwearing, whoring, &amp;c. ſo that wee neuer fall into them againe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wee by this ſpirituall fight doe weaken and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the force of all ſinne, and ſo dayly get ground thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Wee by taming of ſinne, make it ſeruiceable vnto vs; by outward corruptions, purging out ſecret abominations; ſo that all doth turne to our exceeding good.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And ſo continuing in this ſpirituall warfare to the end, we fight the good fight of faith, and finiſh our courſe with ioy: 1. Tim. 6. 2. Tim. 4.</p>
            <p>And hence proceedeth the iuſt condemnation of the times wherein we liue, wherein, though iniquitie abound and is ripe to the harueſt, yet the crie is, all is well, let no man reproue, or it is but our infirmitie, and ſo we muſt be borne with. So the hypocrite either ſees no iniquitie at all, or if the groſſeſt ſinne breake forth, yet it muſt be but an infirmitie, that ſo he may be hardned therein, that he cannot repent.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">5. The weake Proteſtant.</note>5. <hi>The weake Protestant</hi> is here reproued, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemes his caſe ſingular, when he is ouertaken with any groſſe ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Vſe, of <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi>
               </note>Secondly, this ſerues for inſtruction, and that many wayes: as,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21476:20"/>1.<note place="margin">To reſt onely on Chriſt.</note> To teach vs to reſt wholly on Chriſt in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our ſaluation, and to eſteeme all as dung in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of him; to deſire to be found in him, not hauing our owne righteouſneſſe, but the righteouſneſſe which is of faith: Philip. 3. verſ. 8.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. To be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with inward cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions.</note> Wee may hence learne to be abaſed and truly humbled; not with outward afflictions, which may breed worldly ſorrow, but with our inward corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which may cauſe godly ſorrow to repentance: 2. Cor. 2. Iames 4.8, 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And ſeeing the beſt hath his infirmities,<note place="margin">3. To be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate to others.</note> here is a notable meanes, to teach the proudeſt to haue com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſion, to put on meekeneſſe of ſpirit, and tenderneſſe of heart; in relieuing and raiſing vp his afflicted bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſo the communion of Saints may be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peace: Galath. 6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Here is matter of triall in this ſtate of infirmities,<note place="margin">4 To trie our eſtate in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification by infirmities.</note> which ſeemes common to all; whether yet wee are ſuch as are renued in Chriſt, to whom our ſinne ſhall not be imputed: namely, If</p>
            <p n="1">1. Wee hate all ſinne indifferently with a perfect hatred.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Striue vnfainedly againſt all ſinnes, euen the leaſt infirmities, not allowing our ſelues in the leaſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Iudge our ſelues dayly for ſinnes particular ſo for as we know, or are iuſtly chalenged therewith.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Condemne we ſecret corruptions and motions to euill.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Wholly relie on Chriſt for pardon for ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Hunger after death in regard of ſinne: Rom. 7.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Endure reproofe patiently, and amend.</p>
            <p n="8">8. If we feele the power of ſin daily weakned in vs.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Eſpecially of ſuch ſinnes which haue moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed heretofore.</p>
            <p n="10">10. And mourne vnfainedly for the ſinnes of others.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21476:21"/>10. Labouring to pluck others out of the fire, and warning them by our example.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Of comfort. That we haue right in Chriſt.</note>Thirdly, this ſerues for comfort, and that many wayes, As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that God hath left infirmities in vs: therefore haue we hence aſſurance of our right in Chriſt, who came to ſaue ſinners, and ſhall haue experience of the power of Chriſt, in the dayly ſubduing, and maſtering of our corruptions. And therefore</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">To preuent deſpaire.</note>2. Let vs not deſpaire in our greateſt tentations, ſeeing the greater miſerie, the greater mercie. As it is God our Father that hath left ſinne in vs, yea in the deareſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 1.8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.19.20.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3, 4. <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.6, 7.</note> to aduance his free and conſtant loue: ſo hath he giuen his Sonne to reueale this loue vnto vs by the operation of the Spirit, ſhedding it abroad in our hearts, through the dayly aſſurance of the pardon of our ſinnes, and continuall enabling to conquer the ſame: Rom. 5.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Not to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine our caſe ſingular.</note>3. To this end let vs not thinke our caſe ſingular, ſeeing the beſt haue not been exempted from infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whereby Satan would driue vs to deſpaire; but rather the greater our infirmities are, the greater expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience may we looke for of the mercies of our God, who will lay no more vpon vs then we ſhall be able to endure, 1. Cor. 10.13: but will giue an iſſue with the temptation, that ſo wee may be able to beare it.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">That infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall not feſter in vs. <hi>Iob</hi> 33.15 <hi>Acts</hi> 2.36, 37, 38.</note>4. Laſtly, though we haue infirmities; yet let this comfort vs, that our God wil not let them feſter in vs, but by the power of our conſcience, or miniſterie of the word, or by ſome outward chaſtiſment, &amp;c. we ſhal know our iniquitie; that ſo we may performe ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable repentance: and this is the next obſeruation that followeth in the text, out of the practiſe of our Sauiour with his Church; who doth not flatter her in her ſinne, by concealing the ſame, (as a falſe Prophet would haue winked at it, and onely ſtood vpon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, yea happily aſcribe that which was not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21476:21"/>
true) but deales faithfully with her. As he commends her for her good parts: ſo hee reproues her for that euill of her decay.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>teacheth vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Doctrine.</hi> Sinne to be reproued. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Reaſons.</hi>
               </note> that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee muſt reproue our brother plainely for his ſinne:</hi> So doe wee teſtifie, and approue;</p>
            <p n="1">1. The faithfulneſſe of our calling and dutie vnto God, in deliuering the whole counſell of God, as well reproofe for ſinne, as prayſe for well doing. 2. Tim. 3.16. 2. Tim. 4.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our loue to our brother, both in preuenting Gods iudgements by our reproofes, or elſe ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them vnto a ſinner. 3. At leaſt we iuſtifie God, 4. and make the ſinner without excuſe: Ezech. 33. 5. and ſaue our owne ſoules. 6. As alſo hereby wee prouoke him to repentance, and ſo by renewed repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to perfection: Leuit. 19.17.</p>
            <p>And ſhall wee not hereby put the Chriſtian to the tryall of his ſoundnes. If he will endure reproofe, there is hope of him, he is beſt able to beare it, he will make beſt vſe of it? Tit. 1.15. or is not this the meanes to make him ſound. Is not this a meanes to caſt off the hypocrite, and ſo to rid the Church of her moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous enemy.</p>
            <p>And this 1. condemneth the flatterer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. Of reproofe to the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring teacher.</note> that either will ſee no euill in his brother, but is ſtill beating vpon the good that is in him, puffing him vp with conceit thereof; or if he ſee any euill, will not reprooue him plainely, but either excuſe it, or diminiſh it, or daube it vp, hardning him in his ſinne, &amp;c. Ezech. 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are here reprooued,<note place="margin">2. Of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious that cals darkenes light, and light darkenes 3. Of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter of perſons.</note> that iuſtifie the wicked and condemne the righteous: Eſay 5.21. whereas our Sauiour iuſtifies the good, and condemnes the euill.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As alſo, they that ſtumble at ſtrawes, and make mole-hils mountaines; omitting the ſinnes of great ones, or the great ſinnes of their brethren: for fauour and affection, but enforcing to the vtmoſt, euery light
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21476:22"/>
eſcape in the godly, or their enemies; putting more thereto, yea, taking occaſion thereby to diſgrace their profeſſion, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whereas our Sauiour Chriſt, heere ſpares not the greateſt and moſt famous Church, and whatſoeuer is amiſſe in her, lets her know plainely of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Of the people. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.</note>The people alſo are here condemned, that hate thoſe that reprooue them, and rather heape vnto themſelues ſuch teachers as will flatter them in their ſinne, then intertaine thoſe that deale faithfully in reproouing: Amos 5.11. Micah. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Vſe of inſtruction. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6 5. <hi>Eſay</hi> 58.1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.2.</note>Secondly, here is inſtruction, 1. to prayſe God for faithfull teaching, when God cuts downe by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and conuinceth the world of ſinne. 2 And alſo to mourn where the Church is peſtered with flatterers; that cry all is well, Peace, peace; all the congregation is holy: Ieremy 6. Numb. 16. Ieremy 28. Ezech. 34.13, 14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Heere is matter of tryall both for Miniſter and People. If the one will rebuke ſharply, and the other brooken. If the Miniſter wil not ceaſe to reprooue, till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e haue either conuerted, or conuinced. If the hearer will deſire to be ſmitten till he doe amend, yea when he doth his beſt, ſtill deſires to be humbled &amp; ſearched, that ſtill he may increaſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Wee learne heere by our Sauiours example how to reprooue for ſinne: namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Exemplary, not being pertakers with him in his ſinnes, but by our contrary conſtancie and good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample iuſtifying our reproofe, taking away all excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and this hath place alwayes when other meanes of reproofe will not be admitted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Truly, not chalenging of what is not, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning all for ſome, nor being caryed with heare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayes or ſurmiſes, but as we know, and what we know: <hi>Thou haſt loſt thy firſt loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Sinne, how to be reproued.</note>3. Plainely: <hi>Thou art the man,</hi> 2. Sam. 12.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21476:22"/>4. Particularly: Letting him ſee his particular ſinne, not in the clouds, not generally: and yet here we may vſe ſometimes Parables, and propoſe it in another caſe to prouoke vs to apply vſe to our ſelues. 2. Sam. 12.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Louingly, not with reproachfull tearmes, not with imperious and inſolent vpbraydings, but with grace, and compaſſion, conſidering our ſelues, and preuenting obſtinacie and imputation of malice, vſing to this end inſinuations of our loue to preuaile the better, Rom. 9. and hazarding our vttermoſt to ſaue a ſoule, not behinde his backe, but to his face, adding the promiſes of the Goſpel if he doe repent, and ſo vſing all meanes to giue him hope of recouery.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Powerfully: To humble him for his ſinne, by denouncing the wrath of God againſt the ſame: <hi>I haue ſomewhat againſt thee:</hi> that is, I haue a controuerſie with thee, I am angrie, I will be auenged of thee for it, adding to our reproofe, denunciation of vengeance.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Conſtantly and ſeaſonably, not letting him lye in it, taking the fit time, &amp;c. as <hi>Abigail</hi> did, 1. Sam. 25. meeting with the beginnings of euill, and not giuing ouer, till either wee haue reclaymed, or made inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Impartially and ſincerely, not ſparing the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt nor deareſt vnto vs; no nor the houſe of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 7.8. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.</note> Eſay 58.1. no not the moſt excellent Church; not <hi>Dauid,</hi> though a King; not our children, not any, <hi>Eli,</hi> 1. Sam. 2.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, heere is great comfort,<note place="margin">3. Vſe, of <hi>comfort.</hi>
               </note> that being reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for ſinne, we are iudged in this life; and ſo by the grace of God being brought to repentance, we ſhall not be iudged in the life to come: 1. Cor. 11.31, 32.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in that the holy Ghoſt teſtifieth heere,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctrine</hi> 4. The leaſt ſin in the Saints is ſufficient to make the</note> that Chriſt doth come againſt his Church for this ſin: here we learne, That though God loueth alwayes the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his children; yet he is diſpleaſe with their ſin:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21476:23"/>
he will come agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt them for it, and chaſtiſe them for the ſame: Pſal. 89. 2. Sam. 8. &amp;c. Ezech. 18. And that becauſe he is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Righteous, and hateth iniquitie, Pſal. 5.4. and therefore will not endure it in his owne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is mercifull, and therefore will not ſuffer ſinne to dwell in his children: but by his corrections will clenſe them: Eſay 1.25. Eſay 27. Iere. 19. Pſal. 89.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſinnes of his children doe more grieue him, and indeed are more grieuous in themſelues: Firſt, becauſe</p>
            <p>They haue more grace to reſiſt. Secondly, doe giue more offence to the weake. Thirdly, open the mouth of the wicked more to blaſpheme God and his truth: 2. Sam. 12.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the wicked may haue their vengeance here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſealed vp, in that the Lord ſpareth not his owne children: Prou. 11.32.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That his children might not be condemned fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That he might weane them from the world, and prouoke them to draw neere vnto him in prayer, and ſo haue in our ſelues further experience of his loue in the iſſues thereof.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Their ſinne is not theirs, but proceeds from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and the old man, which he therefore remoueth by his chaſtiſements, that ſo he might manifeſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme his loue more and more to their perſons in fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to glorie.</p>
            <p>But how ſtande it with Gods iuſtice to puniſh ſinne in the Elect which he hath puniſhed in his Sonne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> He doth not puniſh ſinne in vs as he did in his Sonne according to the exactneſſe of his iuſtice, and defect of our ſinne, for then we ſhall neuer be able to abide it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He doth not intend to puniſh ſinne, but to amend the ſinner, and ſo qualifies his corrections according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21476:23"/>
As accompanying them with the word, giuing vs ſtrength to beare them, or framing them to our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, miniſtring abundant conſolations to conteruaile them, and giuing a gratious iſſue out of them, either ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the rod, or geuing patience to endure it.</p>
            <p>And this ſerueth,</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to thoſe that by reaſon of proſperity flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe that are impatient vnder the rod deſeruing the ſame.</p>
               </note> To condemne the wicked that flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their righteouſneſſe, becauſe they proſper, and are not plagued like others, nor afflicted as the ſinners, ſeeing they are fatted vp hereby to the day of ſlaughter, and the elect by afflictions prepared to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe: Ierem. 12.3. Act. 14.23, 24. Iob. 21. Pſal. 17.14:</p>
            <p n="2">2. To reprooue the ſinners that prouoke the Lord by their ſinne to become their enemie, and then being afflicted, complaine of wrong, and condemne the loue and faithfulneſſe of God, as if in chaſtiſing them he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, ſeeing of very loue and faithfulneſſe he doth correct them: Pſal. 119. Pſal. 73. Iob 6.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">
                  <p n="3">3. Thoſe that iudge peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of men by outward things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>Inſtruction how to keepe God our friend.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient vnder the rod.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To try our eſtate by the vſe of the croſſe.</p>
               </note> To reprooue the world that iudge of men by theſe outward things, ſeeing all things are alike vnto all men: Eccl. 9.1.</p>
            <p>Secondly, here is inſtruction: 1. To teach vs how to keepe God to be our friend: namely, by keeping our ſelues from ſinne, or elſe by renued repentance, dayly renouncing, and reforming the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To beare patiently the hand of God, ſeeing we haue deſerued hell; and this affliction which is but for a moment, will procure vnto vs an ineſtimable weight of glory: 2. Cor. 5.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To trie our eſtate vnder the rod, namely, 1. if we feele the Lords diſpleaſure, and ſo feare and depart from euill: Prou. 14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If wee can finde comfort in the word.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And wait patiently on our God in our greateſt afflictions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Not ſeeking ſo much the remoueall, as to haue the corrections ſanctified vnto vs.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21476:24"/>5. Either by bringing ſome ſinne paſt to light, and iudging for it, or elſe preuenting ſinne to come.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Making vs more tender in conſcience,</p>
            <p n="7">7. More compaſſionate to our brethren,</p>
            <p n="8">8. More out of loue with the world,</p>
            <p n="9">9. More to long after heauen,</p>
            <p n="10">10. More zealous in holy duties, more iealous of our ſelues, more confident on God, more readie for death.</p>
            <p>And thus doth the holy Ghoſt amplifie the ſinne of this Church, by ſignifying that the Lord is angrie with her for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">1. But let vs conſider what this ſinne is, namely, That ſhe hath left her firſt loue, a ſinne of omiſſion, ſhe hath failed in that zeale, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How the ſaints though leauing their firſt loue, yet may be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that they faint not.</note>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But how may ſhe be ſayd to haue left her firſt loue, ſeeing ſhe hath formerly the teſtimonie that ſhe endured patiently, and did not faint?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> She might faile in the meaſure of her loue, though not in the ſubſtance and trueth thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. She might faile in the outward action, though not in the inward purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. She might haue been formerly zealous, but now ſhe was decayed, and her preſent decay might not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preuented breed a further relapſe, and ſo threaten either ſome grieuous ſcourge to pluck her out of this pit, or elſe might occaſion finall Apoſtaſie.</p>
            <p n="4">4. She might maintaine the doctrine of the Goſpell, though to the enduring of manifold afflictions for the ſame, and yet neglect the holie diſcipline, and ſo grow remiſſe and careleſſe in the practice of godlines.</p>
            <p n="5">5. She might not be ſo zealous as ſhe was, and yet haue ſo much zeale as not to giue ouer finally; for a time ſhe might be cooled, but not quenched in her zeale, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And yet wee ſee the Lord is not ſatisfied herewith, but ſhe muſt recouer what ſhe hath loſt, and ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21476:24"/>
in holineſſe, nor vtterly reiect vs for our failings yet would not he haue vs lie in them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Wherein obſerue we the care of the Lord Ieſus vnto his Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctrine</hi> 5.</note> that though ſhee was not ouertaken with any groſſe and apparant euils, that ſhe did not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together faile in doing of good, yet hee doth here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue her for ſome meaſure of decay, for omitting what ſhe ſhould haue done, intending thereby to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke her to perfection, and to recouer her of her fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, that ſo ſhe may grow to perfect holineſſe.</p>
            <p>Whence we may further learne, that the Saints of God are to be reprooued fos ſinnes of omiſsion, euen for omitting or neglecting that which they ſhould do, yea for failing in the meaſure thereof, aſwel for groſſe and apparant breaches of the will of God. Thus haue the Prophets reprooued the people of God, for failing in what they ſhould haue done, and for careleſneſſe in holy dueties.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Eli</hi> chalenged of the Lord, for neglecting to reprooue his ſonnes, 1 Sam. 2. Thus are the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians charged for neglecting due preparation to the Holy Sacrament, for neglecting the due execution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the inceſtuous perſon, 1. Cor. 5.2.3. 1. Cor. 11.23.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reaſons hereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Saints doe not eaſily take notice of theſe failings, if they auoyd ſcandalous euils, if they do in any ſort performe outward duties, yet they fayle in the meaſure, as not performing them in zeale and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and herein they many times thinke they may bee excuſed, becauſe they are not yet perfect; becauſe they are ſubiect to infirmities: or by carnall wiſedome bee induced to more moderation, (as they call it) or abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in them; yea happily vnder pretence of Chriſtian liberty, may haue ſome allowance hereunto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is that, wherein the Saints doe moſt fayle in, and may moſt dangerouſly deceiue themſelues here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; as</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21476:25"/>3. That theſe ſinnes of Omiſsion may be occaſions to giue vs vp to groſſe and open ſinnes, euen to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit many foule offences againſt the Law of God; as cauſing the Lord to leaue vs to our owne luſts, that ſo neglecting what we ſhould doe, we may commit what we ſhould not, to the confounding of our carnal confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and prouoking to more zeale, as 2. Sam. 12. Are not many ouertaken with the ſinnes of the time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot mourne for them, or couragiouſly remooue them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Theſe ſinnes of Omiſsion doe moſt grieue Gods Spirit, and chalenge the power of ſanctification: moſt hinder our growth in grace, and are dangerous occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to hypocriſie and lukewarmeneſſe.</p>
            <p>And this ſerueth, to reprooue the faſhion of the Times, which is either not to reprooue at all, or at the moſt to reprooue for groſſe and open ſinnes, as for fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in what wee ſhould doe, theſe are either not touched at all, or rather excuſed and iuſtified vnder the pretence of infirmities, and in that ſpecially the power of godlineſſe is generally chalenged of too much more then needs; therefore, this meaſure is approoued, as being what fleſh and blood can doe, what is common with the time, what will beſt ſerue the looſeneſſe and indifferency thereof, what will beſt ſecure vs againſt the ſnares thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is matter of tryall, that if we take aſwell to heart our faylings in what we ſhould doe, yea be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in our wants, when wee haue done our beſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel as for groſſe and open prophaneſſes, this is a good teſtimony of the power of Grace, that the Lord hath begun his worke in vs, and ſo by this narrow tryall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to make vs better.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wee are hereby alſo taught how to deale with our owne hearts, euen to bee iealous of our ſelues, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, for ſayling in holy dueties, to examine our hearts principally in this caſe, how wee are colde in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21476:25"/>
prayer, inſenſible of Gods iudgement, that we cannot mourne for the ſinnes of the Time, that wee do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue the common ſinnes thereof, the abominable ſwearing, prophaning of the Sabbaths, &amp;c. for this ſhall be a meanes to keepe vs from the like abuſes, this ſhalbe a gratious helpe to increaſe in holy dueties, and ſo to ſubmit to a conſcionable miniſtery to this end, comforting our ſelues, that if wee belong to God, our gratious Lord will not let vs ſcape in the leaſt ſayling, but if his worde will not preuaile, he will come againſt vs with ſome ſecret or open chaſtiſement, to recouer vs betimes, and ſo to preuent vs from Apoſtaſie, that we may increaſe and follow hard after the marke. And this is that which we further learne herein.</p>
            <p>That though the Lord accept the purpoſe of the heart, and will not quench the ſmoaking flaxe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctrine.</hi> 6.</note> yet he would haue vs recouer our ſelues, and grow in grace, and follow hard after the marke; we muſt abound in grace, and be plentifull in good works;<note place="margin">The elect muſt goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere in grace, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> we muſt doe the firſt worke, nay, wee muſt thriue in well doing, expreſſing outwardly what wee inwardly deſire, and ſubduing the whole man to the obedience of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: 1. Col. 1. Pet. 2.1.3. Epheſ. 1. Phil. 2. Pet. 1.8. Pſalm. 92. Iob 17.9. 1. Theſ. 5. perſeuering with all patience and conſtancie vnto the end, Eph. 6.13.</p>
            <p>And that, Firſt, becauſe the Lord hath commanded, That wee ſhould be holy, as he is holy, 1. Pet. 1.13,<note place="margin">Reaſons.</note> 14, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt Ieſus hath deſerued to make vs perfit, by his perfect obedience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And by his Spirit dayly dwelleth in vs, to leade vs into all truth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hereby we make ſure our election, and attaine to the certaine knowledge thereof, 2. Pet. 1.10. Ioh. 7.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Hereby we make our ſelues meete for that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inheritance, 1. Col. 11.12.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21476:26"/>6. Hereby wee prouoke others to glorifie God, Matth. 5.16, 17. and ſtrengthen the weake.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Wee daunt and confound the enemies of the Goſpell, 1. Pet. 2. ſtopping the mouth of all iniquitie and reproach.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And adorne and beautifie our glorious profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1. Phil. 27.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And gaine more glorie to our bleſſed God, Math. 5.10.</p>
            <p>And this ſerueth,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſes.</hi> 1. Of <hi>reprooſe</hi> to thoſe that deceiuer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with good intents and motions. Of ſuch as go backeward.</note>To condemne, 1. all thoſe that flatter their hearts with good intents, when they are vtterly voide of good fruits, Prou. 3. Eſa. 29.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as ſtent their meaſure of holineſſe by fleſh and blood, and ſuch carnall Rules as ſquare thereto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As alſo thoſe, that vpon preſumption that they are better then others, ceaſe to better themſelues, and ſo ſtanding at a ſtay in religion, goe backward therein, 1. Cor. 4. Reuel. 3.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">As feare to be noted of ſingularitie.</note>4. And thoſe likewiſe that feare to abound in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, zeale, &amp;c. leſt they be accounted ſingular noted men, preciſe, vaine-glorious, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">As iuſtifie decayes.</note>5. And theſe eſpecially, that haue not only ſlacked their zeale in religion, but doe iuſtifie this decay, as being now more wiſe, ſober, &amp;c. in their profeſſion, where as before they were fierie, raſh, indiſcreet, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Of <hi>inſtruction,</hi> how to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe. Meanes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie. 1. Corrupt iudgement.</note>Secondly, here is inſtruction, and that firſt, we muſt labour to increaſe and grow conſtant in godlineſſe, and that by theſe meanes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. By auoyding the meanes of Apoſtaſie, which are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Corruption of iudgement,</hi> and that,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt concerning Holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We may be too holy:</p>
            <p n="2">2. That our forefathers were ſaued with leſſe, and therefore, what need we ſtriue for more?</p>
            <p n="3">3. That wee haue beene too forward already, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21476:26"/>
therefore it is now wiſedome to abate, to be more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or meaſure the worſhip of God by proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That ſeeing we cannot be perfect, therefore it is in vaine to labour thereto.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That there is no time paſt to ſerue God; If wee can doe it on our death beds it will ſerue the turne.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the beſt and freeſt ſeruice of God is to make no bones of ſin, becauſe this is true peace of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, liberty this argues, the aboliſhing of ſinne by his death, to commit it greedily without remorſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That wee may ſerue God and the world too. Luke 16.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That leſſe will ſerue the turne, becauſe many doe leſſe, and we hope are ſaued, Acts 14.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That Gods mercie doth more abound in our failings, Rom. 6.1.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That we need not to be ſo perfect, ſeeing Chriſt hath finiſhed all for vs: ſeeing Chriſt hath therefore perfited all things, that we might grow to perfection, Heb. 12.1, 2. Iohn 15.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That the ſeruice of God is a matter of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie: if we doeit, it is well? but if we faile, God will be mercifull.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Wee muſt take heed of corrupt iudgement, concerning Apoſtaſie, And that on the right hand,</hi> As that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Decay in former zeale and meaſure of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is not Apoſtaſie, but rather a reedifying of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer raſhneſſe, and ignorance, by ſpirituall wiſedome, teaching vs more moderation and humility, not to preſume aboue others, to maintaine ſociety and peace by returning rather vnto others, then to be ſo ſtrict, as to bring them vnto vs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is Apoſtaſie to admit any change of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſeeing we know but in part, and ſo are ſubiect
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21476:27"/>
vnto error, and therefore we may be, and are often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and therefore muſt change our opinions, and this change is not a decay, but rather meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in godlineſſe,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thar it is Apoſtaſie to differ in iudgement, and ſo in practiſe from a Church otherwiſe truely groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and eſtabliſhed: ſeeing the Lord giues not to all a like meaſure of light, neither to all, at one time, what is neceſſary. And therefore either we may not yet ſee what is fit, and ſo are not to bee condemned Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, for what wee know not; And can wee conſent with good conſcience to what we know not; or elſe it may pleaſe God to let vs ſee more then happily is diſcerned, or will be acknowledged, Rom. 14. for what Church is without it imperfections? And ſhall we ſhut our eyes againſt any light that ſhineth, ought wee not to practize, as we are conuinced, and being conuerted, ought wee not to ſtrengthen the brethren? ought wee not to grow vp to perfect holineſſe; And therefore ſeeing we forſake not the ſociety for it imperfections, but rather walke therewith in the common light, and if we differ from it, wherein it is ſhort of perfection, do we not hereby let it ſee it imperfection, and ſo by our wiſe difference lead it to perfection; and ſhall wee then be accounted reuolters from the Church?</p>
            <p>Eſpecially if <hi>Bethel</hi> become to be <hi>Bethauen,</hi> if in the beginning it was not ſo; if <hi>Epheſus</hi> haue forſaken her firſt loue; If the faithfull Citie, whoſe faith was once publiſhed through the world, bee now become an harlot, ſhall wee bee condemned as Apoſtates from that curſed Synagogue which is ſo fallen away from it former purity. Ought wee not rather to prouoke her to doe the firſt workes: and if ſhee will not hearken, ſhall wee not ſtill proteſt againſt her? ſhall wee now meaſure our ſelues by her crooken lines, that ſo being partaker with her in her ſinnes, wee may bee partaker with her in her plagues. But of this more hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21476:27"/>
               <hi>Secondly, Wee muſt auoyde corrupt iudgement on the left hand, concerning Apoſtaſit,</hi> As</p>
            <p n="1">1. That euery fayling in Religion, euery breach of Gods holy will is properly Apoſtaſie: for then the beſt muſt be Apoſtates; all will bee ſubiest hereunto. Becauſe though euery ſinne, yea the leaſt, makes way for Apoſtaſie, if we lie therein without repentance, and fall to excuſe and allow our ſelues therein, yet by the mercy of God the Saints recouer, and ſo their faylings by the ſpeciall indulgence of the Almighty, are meanes of their more ſound and ſpeedy proceeding in the worke of grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And therefore farre bee it from vs to conclude, That any the moſt grieuous ſinne in the Elect, is Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie; That is, ſuch as excludes all hope and meanes of repentance; ſeeing though in it ſelfe it deſerue that God ſhould vtterly forſake vs, and ſo giue vs vp vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to forſake him, and fall away from him; yet becauſe God is our father, and wil not reward vs after our ſins, nor deale with vs after our iniquities; but howſoeuer he forſake vs for a while, leauing vs to theſe corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yea to be chaſtened for them, yet in wrath hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members mercy, ſanctifying theſe corrections to bring vs to repentance, by opening our eyes to ſee our ſin, and humbling vs with the ſenſe of them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that ſo wee might deny our ſelues, and hunger af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mercy in Chriſt Ieſus. Doeth hee not now returne vnto vs in great compaſſions, enabling vs by faith to lay holde vpon Chriſt in him to apprehend the pardon of former ſinne; through him to obtaine grace, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent future ſinnes, and ſo to walke more humbly and conſtantly with our God, and ſo by him to perfect the worke which he hath begun in vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſecond meanes of Apoſtaſie is, Corrupt practize:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Corrupt practize.</note> 
               <hi>And that on the left hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. When either wee liue by examples of the greateſt:</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21476:28"/>2. Or by the louer of the word of God, Matth. 5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or by the ſtreame of the time:</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or onely by the lawes of men:</p>
            <p n="5">5. Or follow the moſt in religion:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, On the right hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>When we grow ſpiritually proud of well doing:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Or grow to ſingularitie, and ſo to forſake the fellowſhippe vpon pretence of their corruptions, that wee may not bee defiled with them. Eſay 65.5.6. Hebr. 10.23.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or affect curious, and vnneceſſarie knowledge, to puffe vp, and not to edifie. 1. Cor. 8.2.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or ſtudie onely to know, making no conſcience to practize as we know. 2. Col. 4.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Or ſtand more vpon trifles and circumſtance then many matters.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Or ſerue God onely ſo farre as we gaine thereby, auoyding afflictions as hinderances thereto.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Or pretending, becauſe of afflictions, that either now we haue no leaſure, or elſe it is in vaine, or too late to ſerue him.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Or grow ſecure and dead in the performance of holy duties, performing them for cuſtome, carnally, hypocritically, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <note place="margin">Libertine.</note>9. Or grow inconſtant in holy duties; intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſet times, of prayers, hearing the word, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Or grow negligent in conuerting others.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Or admit of humane inuentions, with the worſhip of God.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And vpon pretence of peace, giue way in the leaſt againſt conviction of conſcience.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Or prooue vnthankfull vnto God for his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular mercies, 1. Rom.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Or fall into groſſe ſinnes, and lie in them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance: Pſal. 51.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Or iudge vncharitably of our brethren, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing our compaſſions from them:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21476:28"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Motiues to prouoke vs to conſtancie in weldoing.</note> 
               <hi>conſider we theſe motiues to make vs abound in good workes, and grow conſtant therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider we the faithfulneſſe of our God, who loueth to the end. Ioh. 13.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Remember we the continual ſeruice of the Saints in heauen, they inceſſantly glorifie God, and alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually: 1. Theſſ. 4. Reuel. 4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider wee the power of Ieſus Chriſt ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines to couer our imperfections, and to ſtrengthen vs to perfection: Heb. 12.1, 2. and to this end makes continuall interceſsion for vs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Know wee that the Comforter doth abide with vs for euer, Ioh. 17. <hi>to lead vs into all trueth:</hi> and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in all holineſſe: Ioh. 15.16.</p>
            <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4, 15.</note> Conſider we that <hi>the righteous can ſcarcely be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi> 1. Pet. 4.15. and what paines the beſt haue taken toward heauen.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Remember we that Ieſus Chriſt hath taken away all the rigour of weldoing, and yet enables vs by his ſpirit, to perfection, accepting our weakeſt endeuours, ſo they bee ſound, and enabling of vs to fulfill all righteouſneſſe in due ſeaſon.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Diſcerne we often how wee haue failed hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and this ſhal prouoke to more induſtrie hereafter.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And lay wee to heart the ſudden comming of Chriſt, and ſo we ſhall be prouoked to make haſte.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And propoſe wee vnto our ſelues that glorious Crowne, and ſo we ſhall fight that good fight of faith, and finiſh our courſe with ioy.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Obſerue we the prouidence of our gratious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in turning about all things, that they ſhall worke together for the beſt to further vs to happineſſe. Rom. 8.28.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As cauſing our greateſt afflictions to be meanes of remoouing all lets, eſpecially our ſinnes, and ſpurres to perfection, Eſay 1.25.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And making our very ſinnes matter to preuent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21476:29"/>
or ſubdue ſinne, and ſo to prouoke vs to more endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of holineſſe, by how much we haue bene caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, and what ſhall then ſeparate vs from the loue of God? what ſhall not further vs to haſten to perfection? Rom. 8.33.34.35.</p>
            <p n="11">11. To this end, take we a view of the ſpeciall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges of godlineſſe, which are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it onely hath the promiſe of this life, aſwel as of a better.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It onely can giue vs ſound Comfort in our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt troubles,</p>
            <p n="3">3. And giue vs certaine victory ouer them all.</p>
            <p>Onely this ſanctifieth all Gods bleſſings vnto vs, that they may bee pledges of eternall life, 1. Tim. 4.5.</p>
            <p>This onelie giues contentment in all occaſions, and ſo doeth poſſeſſe vs of heauen in this life, 1. Tim. 6.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And ſeeing that in our Fathers Houſe are many Manſions, and thoſe that are moſt faithfull, ſhall haue greater increaſe of glorie, Therefore, let this encourage to increaſe in grace, that ſo we may bee partakers of greater happineſſe. Laſtlie,</p>
            <p n="13">13. Conſider wee how vnwearied the wicked are in euill, what policie they vſe to continue therein, vſing variety of Obiects to preuent loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe and ſatiety; arming themſelues with diuerſitie of meanes, whereby they may bee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to accompliſh their luſtes, and with more pleaſure enioy them longer. And ſhall they take more paines to goe to hell, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to Heauen? Shall they bee ſtill ſtriuing, and neuer wearie, to their owne Condemnation? and ſhall not wee bee ſtill endeauouring to make ſure our Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, practize we theſe meanes of Growth and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21476:29"/>1. Retaine wee ſoundneſſe of iudgement, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the power of godlineſſe?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doe we all things from the ground of the heart, as in the ſight of God? 1. Theſſ. 1.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Cleaue wee ſtill to the power of the worde, and ſtriue wee to increaſe in knowledge? 1. Phil. 1. Coll.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Practize we conſtantly the dueties of pietie and charitie, not ſeruing God by ſpurs, but keeping a conſtant courſe in holineſſe, that ſo the ſeruice of God may be more eaſie and comfortable.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Watch wee daylie ouer our hearts, in a true ſearching and examining the ſame, Pſalm. 4.5.6.</p>
            <p n="6">6. See that wee renew our repentance, as often as we ſinne.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Labour wee the conuerſion of our brethren, and iudge we charitably of them?</p>
            <p n="8">8. Make wee conſcience eſpecially of Sabbaoth duties, becauſe our powerfull practize thereof ſhall better enable to a generall encreaſe, and to conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie therein. And,</p>
            <p n="9">9. Auoide we curioſitie of knowledge and medling in others affaires.</p>
            <p n="10">10. And ſticke we not in the beginnings and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Religion? Hebr. 6.1.</p>
            <p n="11">11. And becauſe wee ſhall bee ſure to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many enemies that will ſeeke to hinder vs in this ſpirituall groweth; therefore put wee on the whole armour of God, that ſo we may reſiſt in the euill day, Epheſ. 6.11.12.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Eſpecially ſeeing the loue of the world will mainely endeauour to preſſe vs downe, and hinder our proceeding vpon pretence of prouiding things neceſſarie; &amp;c. therefore, that wee may in nothing be carefull, let our requeſts be manifeſt vnto God in prayers.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21476:30"/>13. And labour wee true contentation in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer outward meaſure the Lord hath diſpenſed, that ſo we may ſtill hunger after ſpirituall graces.</p>
            <p n="14">14. And prepare we our ſoules daily to afflictions, ſubmit we to whatſoeuer our louing Father ſhall lead vs into; that ſo carnall ſecuritie may bee preuented, our corruptions purged, and wee daily prouoked to perfection.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Quicken we and enlarge our deſires of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, and this wil be a meanes to ſpurre vs forward to practize.</p>
            <p>Meaſure wee not our condition by any meaſure ate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained, but ſtill forget we what is behinde, and haſten to that before.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Walke wee alwayes in feare of our ſelues, and ſuſpect we all our workes, yea then moſt, when we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy greateſt graces: Pro. 28.13. and maintaine wee ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of Conſcience, in all things.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Remember we our ends, and vncertaintie of our life, and the account we muſt make: 2. Cor. 5.10.11.</p>
            <p n="18">18. And reſigne we our ſelues daily into the hands of our God, reſting on his prouidence, 1. Pet. 5. Mat. 6.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Entertaine wee cheerefully the motions of the Spirit, and put them in practize diligently, Eph. 4.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhall we grow conſtant in well doing, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere vnto the end.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Meane to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in the ſenſe of our failing.</note>1. Meane while let it ſtay vs from Apoſtaſie, that our gratious God requires no more then hee giues, if hee giue vs but one Talent, hee wil not require accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to three; and therefore though wee be farre from what we ſhould be, or what others are, yet let not this diſcourage vs in our preſent meaſure, or from attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning further, becauſe he which hath giuen others more is the ſame alſo vnto vs, and will bee in like meaſure, both accepting what he giues for the preſent, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting of his owne worke in due ſeaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That though wee are ſometimes ebbing, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21476:30"/>
ſometimes flowing in the meaſure of holineſſe, yet our God is alwayes the ſame vnto vs. And therefore mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure wee not his loue, by our different meaſure of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; but rather reſolue we, that as when we increaſe more, we haue more cauſe to loue him; becauſe hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers our endeauours: ſo when we ſeeme to goe back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, we haue then cauſe to loue and truſt him more, that ſo hee may recouer vs; as wee haue more need of his loue when wee faile, to lead vs forward againe; ſo we haue as great need of his loue when we haue done our beſt, to emptie vs of all carnall reſpects of vaine-glory, &amp;c. that ſo it may appeare his onely loue hath occaſioned this increaſe, all this ſeruice ſhall redound to his glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That in the worke of grace wee muſt liue by Faith, and not by ſenſe, not meaſuring our eſtate by what wee are in our ſelues, but by what wee are in Chriſt; not what we are for the preſent, but what wee ſhall be in the life to come: And therefore comfort we ourſelues, that as the leaſt ſparke of grace is an euidence that we are ingrafted in the Vine, ſo being the Vine we ſhall be daylie purged and prepared to bring foorth more fruite; that what wee doe for the preſent ſhalbe accepted as perfect in Chriſt, and the more ſenſe wee haue of the imperfection thereof, the more may we be aſſured of our intereſt in Chriſt Ieſus, the more ſhal we be prouoked ſtill to be found in Chriſt, not hauing our owne righteouſneſſe, that ſo in him and through him the worke may be perfited.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. <hi>Make wee tryall of increaſe by theſe markes:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That wee grow in euery part, aſwell inward as outward.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we diſcerne our corruptions more, and are more humbled for them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That our affections to the world are more leſſened and quieted.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21476:31"/>4. That we are more contuetned with our eſtates, and can more caſt our care on God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That we are more willing to endure afflictions, and ready to lay downe our liues for the Name of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That wee can more grieue for the ſinnes of the time, and yet labour more hartilie the conuerſion of ſinners.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That wee are more ſober and wiſe in the vſe of Chriſtian libertie.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That wee are more cheerefull and able to holy dueties, and ſo doe more hunger after our diſſolution, and are willing to die.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That he can be emptied of all, by reſpects, yea of all reſpect vnto our ſelues for the glory of God.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That wee finde ſuch ſinnes moſt weakened, to which formerly we haue bene moſt ſubiect.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That howſoeuer we differ in practize, yet ſtill our deſires are more enflamed, eſpecially vpon our fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to more conſtant obedience.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie. <hi>For our comfort</hi> learne wee, that our God, that commands perſeuerance, giues grace to the ſame, and therefore we ſhall continue, and not finally decay: wee ſhall leaue out firſt loue, but not looſe it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: 1. Philip. 6. Iohn 13. Luke 22.33.</p>
            <p>Wherein note, That euery conuert hath a firſt loue, that is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 7. Euery true conuert hath a firſt loue.</note> when God hath reuealed his loue vnto him in Chriſt, and by the Spirit of God, it is <hi>ſhed abroad in his heart,</hi> then is the heart of a ſinner inflamed to <hi>loue God</hi> againe, then is it enlarged with <hi>ioy vnſpeakable</hi> and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, 1. Pet. 17. for ſo great ſaluation: then doeth it ſtriue to expreſſe it thankfulneſſe vnto God, for ſo great mercie: then is loue as <hi>ſtrong as death, much wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter can not quench it,</hi> Cant. 8.</p>
            <p>And this is called his <hi>firſt loue:</hi> and it is diſcerned by theſe markes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. By his renouncing of all, in compariſon of it,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21476:31"/>
and parting with the deareſt for the enioying of it:<note place="margin">Firſt loue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by markes. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. <hi>Coloſſ</hi> 3.1.</note> ſo did the Apoſtles forſake all in <hi>act:</hi> ſo muſt we forſake all in <hi>affection,</hi> and in act too, ſo farre as it may hinder our enioying of Chriſt: <hi>Zacheus,</hi> Luke 19.6.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When we endure any affliction for the Wordes ſake, 1. Theſſ. 1.9.10. and that with great ioy in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt: Hebr. 10. Epheſ. 1. ſubmitting our ſelues to the power of the word, though it be neuer ſo bitter to the fleſh, and croſſe the luſts thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When we reuerence highly the Miniſters of the Goſpell, Galath. 3.4. thinking nothing too deare for them. Act. 16.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When we cleare our conſcience of all ſinne, by which our ſweet fellowſhip with Chriſt may bee hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred: ſo <hi>Zacheus,</hi> Luke 19. not being aſhamed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our particular ſinnes, and renouncing them vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When for Chriſts ſake <hi>we loue his poore members,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.16, 17.</note> and impart of our worldly goods bountifully to their reliefe, Luke 19. <hi>Zacheus.</hi> 1. Ioh. 2. Ioh. 13. Pſal. 16.2.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When wee continue in the powerfull meanes of the diuine worſhip. Act. 2.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When we conſult not with fleſh and blood, nor communicate with it, but doe vtterly renounce the ſame in regarde of heauen, Act. 9. Galath. 2. Matth. 8. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And being rauiſhed with the ſweetneſſe of the loue of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.33.</note> wee enlarge our ſelues to declare the ſame to our brethren, labouring to bring them to Chriſt, by plucking them out of the fire: Ioh. 1.18. Iude 22.</p>
            <p>The wiſedome and mercie of our God in vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his children vpon their conuerſion this liuely and ardent affection of holy loue is manifold.<note place="margin">Reaſons of this firſt loue.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt hereby to ſcale vnto them the trueth and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of this bleſſed Change, by this ſenſible and ſweet
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21476:32"/>
change of their affections, that whereas before they could not reliſh and brooke the power of the worde, neither had any delight in the excellent, but eſteemed their perſons contemptible and odious, deemed of their wayes as madneſſe or hypocriſie; now finding by the mercie of God their hearts enflamed to the loue of the worde, though it vtterly confound all former hopes, and cut off wholly all future expectations for the fleſh, and withall pretending ſuch to bee moſt deare vnto them who are hated of the world, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of outward appearance, are not able to requite our loue, and yet becauſe they are in Chriſt, are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for his ſake to be beloued; may wee not hence aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly conclude vnto our ſoules, that wee are tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from death to life, becauſe wee loue the brethren; is not this our euidence, that wee are now choſen out of the world, becauſe we loue thoſe whom the world hates? is not this an argument that wee are now in Chriſt, becauſe his loue onely conſtraines vs to loue his members? and ſeeing our loue vnto them is, to make them like vnto vs, is it not our teſtimony, that we are conuerted vnto Chriſt? and could wee ſubmit to that word which is ſo reiected of the world, ſo irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to our corruptions, vnleſſe the loue of Chriſt did conſtraine vs in obedience to his Maieſtie; vnleſſe this loue of Chriſt did hereby prouoke to haue all our ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations brought in ſubiection by the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that ſo wee might retaine nothing to grieue the bleſſed Spirit, vnleſſe we were ouercome by the power of Chriſts loue, to receiue the ſtampe of his Spirit, and furniture of his graces, whereby wee might in ſome meaſure ſhewe our loue vnto our Chriſt, could wee poſſibly receiue the worde in ſuch affliction, and yet with ſuch ioye in the holy Ghoſt, vnleſſe the loue of Chriſt did ouerflow in our hearts, to ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp all thoſe troubles, vnleſſe all ſuch troubles were hereby counteruailed with vnſpeakable Comforts?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21476:32"/>And had we not need of ſome ſpeciall meanes alſo to preſerue vs from falling away, though we haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted how ſweet the Lord Ieſus is: yea certainely our old enemie will now ſeeke by all meanes to re-enter againe, and hee wants not his occaſions, euen from the eſtate of our firſt conuerſion to attempt the ſame.</p>
            <p>For either now vpon our conuerſion, the world will ſteppe in with it glorious and pleaſant baites of proſperity, and great matters to ſearch and blaſt (if it be poſſible the birth in the bud, or if it cannot diuert and withdraw vs from the right end of our calling; yet at the leaſt to coole and hinder vs in the purſuit of the true end, and that by pretence of our Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; becauſe now we haue right in the beſt, and why may we not vſe them who more fitly for theſe who are better able to vſe them; eſpecially if we ſhalbe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to meaſure our inward eſtate by them.</p>
            <p>Or if this will not preuaile, but that it is the will of our gratious God, that by manifold tribulations wee muſt enter into the kingdome of heauen: then Satan will put in on the other ſide to drowne the birth by whole flonds of tribulations, Reu. 12. ſtirring vp our own houſe to become our enemies, becauſe we wil not be ruled by them, becauſe our contrary courſes doe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly condemne them, ſtirring vp the great ones to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute vs, as enemies to gouernment, diſquieters of the common peace, yea rather then fayle, adding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to affliction, labouring to perſwade vs, that becauſe we are thus afflicted, therefore God hates vs, and ſo we are deceiued in our eſtate, we are not the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of God.</p>
            <p>Againſt all theſe ſerues this ſpeciall grace of our firſt Loue, the power whereof is ſuch, that it proues both an excellent preſeruatiue againſt the allurements of proſperity; as hauing ſo rauiſhed the heart &amp; taken it vp to an higher queſt, that the loue of the world is eſteemed no better then doung in ſteed of louing the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21476:33"/>
ſame our holy feare is procured, leſt it may infect vs; and therefore holy wiſedome gained to haue as little to doe with as we may, leſt it do infect vs, and ſo alſo becomes a gratious remedy againſt the flames of affliction; as ſo ſelling our hearts in the aſſurance of Gods loue, that all things ſhall worke together for the beſt, ſo preparing vs by the loue of Chriſt to encounter any afflictions, ſo enabling vs for the loue of Chriſt to endure the greateſt troubles, ſo aſſuring vs, that through Chriſt Ieſus we ſhalbe more the conquerours ouer them, ſo ſweetning all our troubles vnto vs, that we ſhalbe prouoked to loue our God the more in that hee accounts vs worthie to ſuffer with his ſonne Ieſus, ſo confirming vnto vs that thoſe light afflictions which are but for a moment, ſhall procure vnto vs an ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable weight of glorie in the Heauen.</p>
            <p>This is our firſt loue, theſe are the markes thereof, and by the ſame it is graciouſly preſerued, and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vſe.</hi> To <hi>condemne</hi> flaſhes and taſtes.</p>
                  <p>To <hi>trie</hi> our conuerſion.</p>
               </note> 1. Whereby all thoſe ſudden flaſhes, and fained and inconſtant affections of hypocrites are reiected: Heb. 6.4. and,</p>
            <p n="2">2. We put to the tryall, for the ſoundneſſe of our conuerſion, if we haue found ſuch a loue in our hearts by ſuch euident markes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The world is heere condemned, that boaſts of the fauour of God, when it hath no argument of it conuerſion by this loue:<note place="margin">
                  <p>To reprooue the worlds deceit.</p>
                  <p>To comfort the Saints.</p>
               </note> nay, eſteemeth it a wonder and madneſſe to be conuerted.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And the Saints are comforted, that ſeeing their loue vnto God dependeth on his loue vnchangeable to them. 1. Ioh. 4.1. Therefore as his is vnchangeable, Ioh. 13.1. ſo ſhall theirs bee; well they may <hi>leaue</hi> it, but they ſhall neuer <hi>loſe</hi> it. And yet it is a great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they leaue their loue: Although of a certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 6.</note>The Saints may leaue their firſt loue, ſo did <hi>Dauid,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21476:33"/>
Peter, Salomon,</hi> &amp;c. Pſal. 51. Galat. 2. 1. King 11.<note place="margin">The Elect may leaue their firſt loue.</note> And the reaſons are,</p>
            <p>Becauſe as the fire is ſlacked by two meanes, either by withdrawing fuell from it, or putting water, or aſhes thereto:</p>
            <p>So there are two meanes,<note place="margin">And by what meanes.</note> whereby the loue of the Saints doth decay in them,</p>
            <p>Either when they faile in ſuch meanes as doe nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the ſame: or,</p>
            <p>Doo adde ſuch, as may corrupt and coole: Namely,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Meanes of leauing firſt loue</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting that ſhould nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh it.</p>
               </note> when either they,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Neglect the powerfull miniſterie of the word, &amp;c. 1. Theſſ. 5.19.20. ſubmitting to carnal or luckleſſe meanes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The conſtant practize of priuate and publike prayer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or the fellowſhippe of the Saints, Hebr. 10.24.25.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or the motions of the Spirit:</p>
            <p n="5">5. Or neglect to examine their hearts dayly.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Or faile in daylie repentance.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Or neglect to conoert others.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Or abate of holy order and diſcipline which holds vp the power of godlineſſe, as if now wee could be lawes vnto our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Or elſe doe adde that which may corrupt:</p>
            <p n="1">1. As <hi>ſpirituall pride</hi> of Gods graces.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Carnall policie,</hi> ſubiecting religion to the ſame.<note place="margin">2. adding what may coole and quench it.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Proſperitie,</hi> and ſetting their hearts thereon through couetouſneſſe: Pſalm. 119. Luke 18.1. Tim. 6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Abuſe of Chriſtian libertie,</hi> in the enioying of pleaſures, &amp;c. 1. Cor. 10 1. Cor. 8. and vſe of things in different.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A corrupt and carnall Miniſtery:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Spirituall pride,</hi> an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to leaue our firſt loue and hovv.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>ſpirituall pride,</hi> as Conuerts are ſubiect hereto in regard.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:21476:34"/>1. That now not being as others, yea, as themſelues were, yea, being in ſome meaſure made partakers of the <hi>diuine nature,</hi> and aduanced to the hope of ſo glorious an inheritance;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.</note> may they not hereby be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed to <hi>iuſtifie</hi> themſelues, and <hi>deſpiſe their brethren:</hi> to condemne, where they ſhould endeauour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert? &amp;c. Eſay 5.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Euen <hi>their deſire to keepe themſelues in this eſtate,</hi> may bee an occaſion to Satan to breed ſpirituall pride in them. As namely, that being now pluckt out of the common condemnation, and ſeparated from the world and wicked ones, by their effectuall calling; may not the Saints vpon pretence to keepe themſelues vnſpotted and vndefiled, grow to ſingularitie, and ſo to ſeparation, which are very dangerous branches of ſpirituall pride.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>execution alſo of their callings</hi> is ſubiect to much ſpirituall pride.</p>
            <p>Either they may neglect altogether their <hi>ciuill cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> as too baſe, and derogatorie from the prouidence of God, and their Chriſtian libertie, which is a fruit of ſpirituall pride,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.9.</note> ſeeing the Lord hath impoſed theſe callings to humble them. Or elſe they may ſo carry themſelues in their Chriſtian callings, as by their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſitie, diſcontent, &amp;c. they ſhall not obſcurely diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much ſpirituall pride.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>ſpeciall prouidence of the Almightie,</hi> in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to perfection, and diſpoſing of his graces diuerſly, may alſo through the ſubtiltie of Satan bee an occaſion of much ſpirituall pride, And that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either in regarde of ſuch chaſtiſements which the Lord exerciſeth their nature to clenſe the ſame, in the impatient bearing whereof, pride is diſcouered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or elſe the <hi>proſperitie of the wicked,</hi> may bee an occaſion of ſpirituall pride, as being prouoked by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to fret and repine thereat: Pſal. 37.1. Ierem. 12. Iob. 1.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21476:34"/>3. Either the fals of others may giue occaſion of this pride, as prouoking them to the iudging of their brethren, and condemning their eſtates.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or the more eminent graces which the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes on other, may prouoke to enuy and diſcontent, and ſo diſcouer pride, yea, may further occaſion a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of themſelues, as if becauſe we are ſhort of others, therefore they are nothing, therefore they may doubt of their eſtates, or elſe,</p>
            <p n="5">5. This abaſing of themſelues in compariſon of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, may tend to affect commendation from others, and ſo bewray this inward Pride.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Or they may reſt in themſelues on the ſenſe of their encreaſings, and ſo robbing God of his glory, ſhall diſcouer their pride.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Or they may bee puffed vp with this, that they are low in their owne eyes, can deſpiſe the world, can endure afflictions, can reprooue ſinne, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Either they may be puffed vp with thoſe <hi>wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliuerances,</hi> which the Lord in his mercie beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on them in their conduction to glory, 2. Cor. 1. ver. 9, 10. 2. Cor. 12.7,</p>
            <p n="9">9. Or elſe they may reioyce at the deſtruction of their enemies, and ſo be tainted with ſpirituall pride: Iob 31.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Either they may be <hi>haſtie</hi> in <hi>expecting the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> and ſo for want of patience, diſcouer ſpirituall pride: Heb. 10.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Or elſe <hi>deſire death,</hi> in regard of their continual troubles, and ſo diſcouer their pride, in not wayting the Lords leyſure: Iob. 3. Ionas 4.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Either they may be croſſed in their expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo preferring their credits before Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, bewray their pryde: Ionas 4.1.2.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Or elſe, beyond their hope and expectation, they may be endued with extraordinary graces, and ſo are ſubiect to be <hi>exalted aboue meaſure:</hi> 2. Cor. 12.7, 8.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21476:35"/>Thus may the Saints bee ſubiect to ſpirituall pride, and ſo thereby giue occaſion of the loſſe of their firſt loue.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lord <hi>reſiſting the proud,</hi> and bringing low the mountaines; emptying the high minded, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing grace to the humble: 1. Pet. 5.5.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Or iudging others, they are left to iudge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30.</note>2. Their pride making them <hi>ſecure, vncharitable,</hi> and ſo not vſing their talents, they are for a time taken away.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Spirit hereby being <hi>grieued,</hi> ceaſeth to worke in them, nay happily leaues them to grieuous buffetings.</p>
            <p>Therefore to preuent this tentation, and ouercome the ſame:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider wee whence wee came, and if wee did iuſtly ſtrip our ſelues of all, if we conferred nothing to the attayning of grace; but rather were our greateſt enemies in wiſhing the ſame, ſhall we now be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the leaſt? ſhall wee not bee humbled in the greateſt? what haue wee which wee haue not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Lay we to heart, how we entertaine the graces of God, at the beſt vnprofitable, generally colde and careleſſe, defiling the worke by juncture of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And yea, ouerthrowing the worke by our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence therein, our reioycing and boaſting thereof, and may we not feare that this dead Fly will corrupt the moſt pretious oyntment, that if we robbe God of his glory, he will depriue vs of the comfort, either wee looſe our labour for the preſent, or ſhalbe ſtripped of Gods graces, that we may labour no longer. Hath not Lunacie bene an effect of this ſort of ſinne in many bountifully endowed? Is not barrenneſſe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon plague hereof in the ordinary Chriſtian?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Obſerue wee the Prouidence of God in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe diſpenſation of his bleſſings, though hee giue to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21476:35"/>
ſome more, yet is not the leaſt ſufficient if it bee in trueth, and is it not then in trueth, being lodged by a lowly ſpirit, is not the greater meaſure beſtowed on others, ours alſo for vſe: is it not vſefull for vs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke to perfection? is it not auailable to humble vs in our leſſer meaſure, to ſubmit our ſpirits to the ſpirit of the Prophets, to ſend vs dayly to the tents of the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards? is it not a meanes to nouriſh loue? doth it not ſubmit vs to the will of our heauenly Father, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend more vpon his mercy, to craue his aſſiſtance more earneſtly, to ſubmit to afflictions, to haſten after perfection in a better life.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Diſcerne wee wiſely the prouidence of God in leading vs to perfection, and this alſo will bee a grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous meanes to preuent ſpirituall pride; for ſeeing the Lord ſhewes his power in weakeneſſe, that hee may haue the glory, ſeeing he brings light out of darkenes to confound all reioycing in the fleſh, working out of our very ſinnes a way of encreaſe by humbling vs thereby in our ſelues, and cauſing vs to deny our own righteouſneſſe, and ſtill ſending vs vnto Chriſt, to bee renued by his grace; haue we any cauſe to be proud of our ſinnes, to rejoyce in our confuſion, can wee deny our ſelues truely if wee haue confidence in the fleſh? can we be enabled in Chriſt, vnleſſe wee bee wholly emptied in our ſelues? and ſeeing affliction followeth ſinners, and our ſinne in Gods juſtice eternall death: If now the Lord ſhall not only take away the ſting of our Troubles, but make them comfortable pils to purge our Corruption? is not his power wonderfull, to bring light out of darkeneſſe? is not his mercy peereleſſe, that he only may haue the glory, ſhall we be proud of afflictions, that are the puniſhments of ſinne, at leaſt no way likely of themſelues to raiſe ſuch good vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And ſay the Lord ſhould deliuer vs out of greater tribulations, ſeeing yet the ſinne remaines with vs,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21476:36"/>
may wee not feare that though wee bee made whole, yet a worſe thing may befall vs? are not new afflictions dayly to bee expected; and is there here any time to behold the ſunne when it ſhineth?</p>
            <p n="6">6. At the beſt, iudge wee wiſely of our beſt meaſure of grace; is it either any other then what the Saints haue gone before vs in, who yet notwithſtanding, through pride,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 26.</note> and the effects thereof haue taken ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a foul fall. Remember we <hi>Peters</hi> vaine boaſting, and what a plunge it put him to. Conſider <hi>Dauids</hi> pride in numbring of his people, &amp; did he not ſmart deeply for the ſame, was not his humilitie the beſt meanes to make his peace againe? 2. Sam. 24.15, 16.</p>
            <p>Or is it ſuch, but that ſtill wee are not perfect, and therefore muſt wee not forget what is behinde, that wee may haſten to what is before? Philip. 3.12.13.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And alas, what is all wee haue in compariſon of our Lord and Maſter Ieſus Chriſt, hath hee not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vs to bee lowly and meeke? hath hee not done all for vs, that wee may boaſt of nothing? did hee not walke before vs in great patience and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, euen humbling himſelfe to the death for our ſakes? is not all our holineſſe a drop of that Ocean, leſſe then a drop in compariſon thereof? and ſhall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ride on horſebacke, when their maſter went on foote?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10,</note> ſhall wee bee proud of his graces, when hee was ſo abaſed in the greateſt meaſure of his owne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore practiſe wee thus:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. View we our ſelues often in the glaſſe of the Law to abaſe vs throughly:</p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſee wee a farre off into the glorious inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,<note place="margin">How to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent this pride.</note> ſo farre exceeding any worth of our weldoing: are the afflictions of this life worthy of the glory that ſhall bee reuealed? Rom. 8.24. who are wee that God ſhould thus aduance vs?</p>
            <p n="3">3. In ſteed of iudging others, let vs dayly examine
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21476:36"/>
our ſelues, ſo ſhall wee bee more compaſſionare of our brethren, conſidering our ſelues: Galat. 6.1. ſo ſhall we ſtill thinke vilelyer of our ſelues, that ſo we may be fitter for mercy from our God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And labour wee dayly to renue our life in Chriſt, that wee may haue ſtill to reioyce in him, and not in our ſelues; that his glory may ſwallow vp all pride of fleſh, and his loue may ſtill preuaile in vs, to the further denyall of our ſelues, that ſo ſtill wee may be found in Chriſt, not hauing our own righteouſnes; that being dayly perfited by his grace, we may bee found of him in peace at his glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To this end bee wee willing to endure afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and maintaine we tenderneſſe of conſcience in all our wayes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And obſerue we wiſely our inward corruptions, labour we to diſcerne the deceitfulneſſe of our hearts, and ſhall we not abhorre our ſelues becauſe we know not our hearts? ſhall wee not much more bee abaſed, knowing them to be ſo abominable, ſo froward, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, ſo touchie and full of horrible wickedneſſe, ſuch blaſphemous thoughts, ſuch filthy motions? if we do not tremble hereat, is it not becauſe yet the feare of God hath not ſeized vpon vs, becauſe yet we do not endeauour to worſhip God in Spirit and truth, Ioh. 4.24.25.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And ſo dayly prepare we our ſelues to death and iudgement: Is here any time to be puffed vp, ſeeing we muſt paſſe through horrors? is it not wiſedome to fight loe, that we may enter in at the ſtraight gate? ſhall the righteous very hardly bee ſaued, and ſhall wee not then work out our ſaluation with feare and trembling? Phil. 2.12. Math. 7.11.12.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And ſeeing many ſeeke to enter in, and ſhall not bee able, Luke 13.21. ought wee not dayly to ſuſpect our ſelues? ſhall not he that ſtandeth, take heed leſt he
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21476:37"/>
fall, ſhall we be high minded, or not rather euer feare our ſelues, leaſt we alſo bee deceiued in our ſtanding, and ſo depryued of our hope.</p>
            <p>Laſtly. That we be not deceiued in the judgement of ſpitituall pride, and ſo be juſtly chalenged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. To ſtand vpon aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation no pride.</note>Know we that it is not pride and preſumption to be aſſured of our ſaluation as the Papiſts chalenge, ſeeing God hath commanded vs to make ſure our election, and hath giuen vs his word and Spirit to ſeale it vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs; but rather pryde to queſtion Gods truth, not to beleeue his word, not to accept ſo pretious a jewell.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Neither to labour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</note>2. It is not ſpirituall pride to labour to perfection, though we exceed our ſelues, and goe before others, not ſhuting our religion to the will and ability of man; but extending it wiſely to the rule of the word, and example of Chriſt, ſeeing God hath commanded it, and Chriſt hath begun it, and hee will perfect it; and all things worke together for the beſt vnto his Elect; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is pride to dreame of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when we wil vſe no meanes thereto; nay, groſſe preſumption and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency in ſuch as ſeeme to condemne vs of pride, for labouring after perfection, ſeeing they all perſwade themſelues that they haue already attayned it: is it not the common voyce, that all is well, wee need no meanes of building, we hate to be reprooued; we haue bene alwayes of the ſame beleefe, we feare we may be too holy: are not theſe the ordinary dreames of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perfection: and therefore, if they haue attayned this perfection with ſuch eaſe, will they fault vs that take ſuch paynes for it, ſhould they not rather pity vs, and further that we may attayne it more eaſily; or if they condemne for labouring to perfection: doe they not condemne themſelues,<note place="margin">3. No not to confeſſe Chriſt in the time of triall.</note> that they neuer had it, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it cannot be had without great labour.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Neither is it ſpirituall pride to make a good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth, to confeſſe the Lord before men, to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21476:37"/>
ſticke to the truth in time of trial: is not this a denying of our ſelues to confeſſe the Lord? Is it not an abaſing of our ſelues that God may haue the glory? Will it not be a pride in the fleſh to humble vs? Is it not a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of our ſoundneſſe that we will endure for Chriſt? Is it not a ſpurre to perfection? Rather, it is pride to deny our Maſter, as if we were aſhamed of him. It is horrible Pride of life, and loue of the world that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this deniall, we dare not confeſſe him becauſe we loue the praiſe of men more then the praiſe of God. If we were truely humbled, we would in all things glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God. If we ſet not by our fleſh, we would not quitch at any troubles: Remember what cauſed <hi>Peter</hi> to deny his Maſter, and the Lord giues vs vnderſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And is it not an imputation of pride when we are vniuſtly challenged to maintaine our Innocency. We iuſtifie our ſelues, we will be found in no fault, we will condemne our Iudges of wrongfull meaſure. Is it not the practiſe of the world to iuſtifie the wicked, and condemne the righteous? And yet it thinketh to doe God good ſeruice, in cenſuring the children of God, becauſe they are contrary to it, in excuſing and approuing the wicked becauſe they ſort with it waies. Are the beſt without faults and may they not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be condemned. Is not the beſt done in hypocriſie? And therefore are they not worthy to be caſt out of the Synagogues? Thus doth the world ſtumble at the infirmities of the Saints, and becauſe they are faulty in ſome things, doth therefore conclude that nothing is ſound. And ought we then to giue way vnto theſe their ſlanders? Is not the cauſe the Lords, that is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in challenged, ſhall we not harden them in their ſuit hereby, and ſo preuent them from ſound repentance, ſhall we not betray the peace of our conſciences, and cauſe the Lord to take that from vs which we dare not iuſtifie? Indeed though man compared with God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21476:38"/>
be righteous, though we muſt daily deny our own righteouſnes before God, that we may be found in Chriſt to be cloathed with his righteouſnes: yet ſeeing the Lord hath done great things for vs? ſhall we not in thankfulneſſe acknowledge Gods graces in vs? ſhal we not propoſe our ſelues, heere by examples to our brethren: Nay ſaith holy <hi>Iob</hi> God forbid that I ſhould iuſtifie you. I will neuer take away mine innocency from my ſelfe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 27.6.</note> And is it not humility in vs to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what we haue receiued, had we not need of low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirits, to incounter the malice of the world, becauſe we will not forſake our Innocency and vndergoe ſuch afflictions which hence will be raiſed againſt vs? Is it not an argument of ſound deniall of our ſelues, that hereby we ſeeke rather the glory of God then our owne: that hereby we labour the confirmation of the weake. And ſeeing the gifts of grace are ſuch wonders to the world, ſuch eye-ſores, and in ſo baſe account therewith, is it not a gracious abaſing of our ſelues to reioyce in that which is ſo offenſiue to the world, to triumph and boaſt of ſuch gracious gifts, which are ſo debaſed by it? ſurely if we ſhall take our ayme aright, it is rather pride in the world to condemne another mans ſeruant? do they know our hearts? will they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally cenſure vs hypocrytes becauſe ſome are ſuch? and becauſe the beſt are not without their failing they condemn our profeſſion as if it taught no better? Bleſſed be God we eſteeme not to be iudged of them nor of mans iudgement;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 44.</note> he which iudgeth vs is the Lord: to him we ſtand, to him we fall: as for the world well may it diſcouer it malice and pride, in condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the generation of the iuſt, but they muſt know that the Saints ſhall iudge the earth: if they condemne vs becauſe we faile, then do we much more condemne them that are ſo far behind vs. And is it not a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full condemnation of the world that they which with one blaſt condemn vs to be too ſhort, that ſo they may
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21476:38"/>
iuſtifie themſelues, do alſo euen with the ſame breath condemne vs that we are too forward, to zealous, that ſo their deceitfull meaſure may paſſe more currantly? do they not herein condemne themſelues wherein they cenſure vs? If wee haue our faults, why do they not helpe vs forward; and if we haue got ſome ground why doe they then condemne vs for increaſe, ſeeing they condemne vs for failings? ſhall we happily diue into the myſtery thereof? do they not condemne vs for failing, becauſe they would diſcourage vs to go forward? do they not condemne vs for going forward, becauſe we condemne them for being behind vs? do they not condemne our fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings, becauſe they would hereby take occaſion to condemne the word, as if it occaſioned and iuſtified ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ſo they might harden their hearts, in the baſe account of the word, and pu ſuit of their worldly courſes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo put vs from the moſt liuely meanes, which ſhould raiſe vs vp againe, and ſo enable vs to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? And do they not condemne on the other ſide, our proceedings in grace, is counterfeitings, madnes, &amp;c. becauſe the wiſedome of God is fooliſhneſſe vnto them: they neuer yet taſted of the loue of Chriſt, elſe would they thinke they could neuer do him too much ſeruice? And therfore ſeeing that which is highly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of men is abhomination in the ſight of God: as we might haue cauſe to diſtrſt our condition if it were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of the world, ſo haue we a found euidence of the truth of grace, that the world hates vs, not for our euils, as they pretend (for they could let vs alone, if our wayes did not ſhame and confound them) but for the Image of our God renewed in vs. And ſhall not the haters of God be found lyars, ſhall they not wiſh to die the death of the righteous, do they not imitate our waies, though they deny the power of them? they dare not ſet foot to foot by vs. Who ſo is wiſe let him vnderſtand theſe things?</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:21476:39"/>5. To conclude, it is the common cenſure of the world, that whatſoeuer iumpes not with it, ſtoopes not to it lure, it is pride, vaine-glory, and whereas though it may be a marke of an abiect and degenerate ſpirit to be ſwayed thereby, yet to be contrary to the faſhion thereof, muſt needs argue great humility; ſo to leaue our greateſt earthly content: ſo to expoſe our ſelues to a world of troubles.</p>
            <p>Thus the world calles light darkneſſe, and darkneſſe light, eſteeming that pride which indeed is true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</p>
            <p>Shall we now take a further ſcantling what this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall pride may be, ſurely I take it, it conſiſts in theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt in preſuming aboue that is meet in matter of knowledge. And that when we prie into thoſe hidden myſteries which either are fit to be knowne of, or are apparant only to the diuine Nature.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when we vaniſh in idle and curious ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, tending only to ſenſe and ſingularity, and not to edification. 1 Tim. 4.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when we affect knowledge for comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or ornament, and not for reformation of life.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſpirituall pride is ſeene in matter of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that either in reſpect of our ſelues, or others.</p>
            <p>In regard of our ſelues we may be ouertaken with ſpirituall pride.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we ſtand more vpon publike deuotions then priuate humiliation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we reſt more in the forme then in the power of Religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we reſt in our ſelues, for well doing; and not on the power of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If we challenge merit for our workes; and not rely on the mercy of God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If we arrogate more vnto our ſelues then either is truth or conuenient.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:21476:39"/>6. If imagine that we may be preſent in this life, and haue an ouerplus of righteouſneſſe for others.</p>
            <p>And will not follow our Maſter, through the fire.</p>
            <p>In regard of others we may be tainted with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall pride.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we forſake the fellowſhip, and are not equall with thoſe of the lower ſort, leauing the Church for corruptions therein.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we iudge peremptorily of any before the time.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we giue not vnto each his due, howſoeuer we are the Lords and depend only vpon him. Mat. 11.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If we cannot become all vnto all, that ſo we may win ſome vnto Chriſt. 1. Cor. 9.</p>
            <p>Thus may we diſcerne ſome footſteps of ſpirituall pride, &amp; thus haue you heard, how to maſter the ſame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, touching <hi>policy:</hi> by it,<note place="margin">2 Policie, a meanes of cooling our firſt loue.</note> I meane that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which ciuill gouernment diſcouereth in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it affaires, for the adorning &amp; preſeruing thereof. This how ſoeuer it may be an handmaid to Religion, yet carrieth ſome ſway in the manner thereof: as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In ordering, the time, and place,<note place="margin">Policy, how a friend to Religion.</note> and outward decency for the diuine worſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In compelling the outward man, to the outward forme and meanes of religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As alſo, in executing the holy cenſures of the Church, vpon the refractary and obſtinate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And in protecting the innocency and vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Saints, from the rage and wrongs of the wicked: and,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Puniſhing the enemies of the Church.</p>
            <p>Yet may it alſo proue an <hi>enemy</hi> to ſincerity, and ſo be an occaſion (if we be guided thereby) to leaue our firſt loue, and that in theſe reſpects: As,</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">How an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and ſo a meanes of leauing our firſt loue.</note> when it vndertakes to <hi>iudge</hi> and <hi>authorize</hi> the rule of religion: namely the word of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When it adioynes to the ſame, the <hi>inuentions of man,</hi> making it equall with the word of truth.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21476:40"/>3. When it ſtands more vpon the <hi>forme</hi> then the power of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When it excludes the ſubſtance of religion for the outward complement thereof.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">The practiſe of popery in maintaining their religion.</note>5. When it becomes a meanes to iuſtifie the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and condemne the righteous: Eſay 5. Mat. 27.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When it preſumes to limit ſincerity to times, perſons: and,</p>
            <p n="7">7. When it inſulteth and lords it ouer the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by inquiſition into the ſecrets of the heart, and violent forcing the ſame, contrary to the tenderneſſe, and true information thereof.</p>
            <p n="8">8. When it faſhions the forme of religion according to the frame of worldly gouernment: as Antichriſt patched vp his anarchy, partly from the Iewiſh Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, partly from the forme of the heathniſh Empire.</p>
            <p>Thus may policy be an enemy to Religion, and ſo a meanes of the leauing of our firſt loue.</p>
            <p>And thus may we learne to preuent this great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in matter of religion we conſult not with fleſh and blood, pinning neither our iudgement nor practiſe vpon the ſleeues of men. Gal. 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we admit no humane inuention, as part of Gods worſhip. Mat. 15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And conſidering that the wiſedome of the fleſh is enmity againſt God, reſolue we to endure the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions of the world in the worſhip of God, and that, that is ſincereſt, which the word moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That in all matter of diuine worſhip we be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and informed according to the word, as well for matter as manner agreeable thereunto.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That we do all things as in the preſence of God out of the good purpoſe of our hearts, to be approued of him in the inward man, and not with bodily ſeruice to be ſeene of men: Mat. 6.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:21476:40"/>6. That we are more conſcionable in priuate duties in the cloſet, family, ſanctifiyng the publike worſhip by priuate preparation, and trying the publike worſhip by priuate examination.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That we meaſure not the worſhip of God, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by any meaſure we haue already attained: as if we had holineſſe enough, or by any outward ſucceſſe thereof in the world.</p>
            <p n="8">8. As by the acceptance of men; by proſperity, or by any particular iſſue.</p>
            <p n="9">9. For the preſent that in the greateſt meaſure of ſanctification we ſtand not vpon the euidence of our owne conſcience, As to be iuſtified thereby, though we know nothing by our ſelues, but ſtill deny our owne righteouſnes, that we may be found in Chriſt to be ſtill enabled by his righteouſneſſe to haue the teſtimony of the acceptance of our perſons, and ſo to haue the comfort not only of the acceptance of preſent ſeruice, but to be enabled by Chriſt to conſtant obedience. 1. Cor. 4.4.5. Phil. 3.10.11.12.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That in the worſhip of God we be not miſled by carnall ends, as profit, pleaſure, vaine-glory, &amp;c. But that in all things we purpoſe the glory of God, and the ſaluation of our ſoules, ſubordinate thereunto. 1. Cor. 10.31.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That in our beſt meaſure we acknowledge our ſelues vnprofitable ſeruants, and ſo caſt our ſelues vpon the meere mercie of God in IESVS CHRIST. Luke 17.10.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, And ſo may alſo Proſperity coole firſt loue.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If either hauing much, we ſet our hearts vpon it.<note place="margin">Proſperity an occaſion to coole our firſt loue and how?</note> Pſal. 62.10. and ſo are withdrawne to execute the luſts of our hearts:</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or are afraid of afflictions, and decline them by carnall meanes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or meaſure our eſtate in grace by our proſperity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or are not willing to be abaſed, as we do abound.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:21476:41"/>5. Or grow ſecure and vncharitable hereby, either deſpiſing our poore brethren, or inſulting ouer them. 1. Pet. 5. much leſſe being inlarged in compaſſion of their affliction,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6.</note> or open handed to relieue them: or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe conſtancy of this tickliſh eſtate vnto our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Or grow to deſpiſe the ſimplicity of the Goſpell, as if it were then but in it infancy. And ſo as power is in our hands adorning the worſhip of God with vaine pompe and outward complements. As if this were an argument of the increaſe and perfection of religion, that it is now more glorious &amp; acceptable to the world</p>
            <p n="7">7. Laſtly, whereas proſperity vſually puffes vp with a conceit of goodnes, if now therfore being aloft, when we haue brought religion to our lure, as to countenance our greatneſſe, and ſort with our exceſſe, we ſhall now (as the manner is) grow to eſteem baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of religion, as ſtooping to our luſts, and ſo either neglect the power thereof in our obedience thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or reſt in the forme thereof, contenting our ſelues with carnall and corrupt meanes: will not this corrupt the iudgement, and ſo make way for apoſtaſie, will not this coole our zeale, and dead our hearts, making vs confeſſe, indifferent, lukewarme, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And therefore that proſperity may not work theſe effects in vs,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Know we, that where God giues more, there he requires more at our hands.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That hereby we are preuented of many lets which might hinder our proceeding, and ſupplied with many helps to do more good, to abound in thankſgiuings.</p>
            <p>And therefore carry we our ſelues thus in our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward encreaſing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Acknowledging that from God we haue receiued it, and therefore ſhame we to honour God with our ſubſtance and with the firſt fruits of our increaſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be we alwaies jealous of eſtates, eſpecially when we moſt abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that ſo being humbled in our outward
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21476:41"/>
meaſure, we may grow in the inward.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Imploying our Talents now more plentifully to the good of others, eſpecially to further them to grace, not contenting our ſelues to giue almes for bodily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, vnleſſe we alſo tender ſome good for the ſoule; enlarging our ſelues, where grace is more enlarged: and ſo learning to bee equall with thoſe of the lower ſort, if they be equall with vs, or exceed vs in the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Taking now our oportunity to frequent the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and cleauing to the power of the word, ſtill to humble and rouſe vs vp.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Being ready to vndergoe any afflictions, rather then abate one jot of our ſincerity.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And ſtill in our greateſt libertie, being lawes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelues, not to giue libertie to the fleſh, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now to make tryall of the conqueſt of our luſts, by how much we haue power to execute the ſame, Galat. 5.11.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Vſing the world as though wee vſed it not, 1. Cor. 7.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And ſtill as ſtrangers and pilgrims, looking for a Citie which is aboue, and eſteeming all as doung in compariſon of Chriſt, and the glory that ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, Philip. 3.8.9.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>See more of the right vſe of proſperity in the daylie Sacrifice, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. And ſo alſo by abuſe of our Chriſtian libertie we may leaue our firſt loue; as hereafter ſhall more fully be declared; where the remedie hereof is alſo propoſed.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie. A principall meanes and occaſion to leaue our firſt loue to abate our zeale and conſcience of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, is a carnall and corrupt miniſtery.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When either the word is deliuered with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing words of mans wiſedome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or elſe not applyed and layd cloſe to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21476:42"/>
condition of the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or not confirmed by the holy conuerſation and patient endurings of the Miniſter.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or mingled with curious queſtions, and corrupt doctrines.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Or aymes onely at carnall peace, and making good our preſent meaſure, and doeth not labour by ſound reproofes and ſearchings, to lead along to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Or wants the power of the holy cenſures of the Church, to bridle the profane, &amp; caſt out the obſtinat.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Or peruerteth the diſcipline to worldly ends, to harden the wicked in their ſin, and diſcourage from perfection.</p>
            <p>And can this chooſe but coole and abate the power of godlineſſe?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Will not the people rather ſtumble at the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt examples, then be ordered by the word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doth not this mixture of humane ornaments, queſtion the perfection of the word, as if it were not of it ſelfe able to conuince the conſcience: doth it not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually cauſe the word to reſt in the eare, and not ſinke downe to the heart, and ſo becauſe it mooues not, therefore to conclude that either it is not the word of God; or els we haue no need of it, becauſe it moues not</p>
            <p>Will any diſcerne his ſaylings, vnleſſe it be particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly layde to him, vnleſſe his conſcience be convinced therewith, and compelled by the ſenſe of Gods wrath to forſake his ſinne. And,</p>
            <p>Is it not a dangerous occaſion to condemne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the power of the word, which might bring him to repentance, when he can haue a <hi>Zidkiah</hi> to flatter him in his ſinne, an <hi>Amaziah</hi> to promiſe him a neerer way to Heauen, to wiſh him not to bee ſo ſcrupulous, to pronounce life to him that is dead in his ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, if here the practize ſhall be rather to fill his head with knowledge, and to puffe him vp with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21476:42"/>
curious and vaine ſpeculations, ſhall not this rather preuaile, to perſwade him that his caſe is better, then bring him to the ſight of his particular faylings?</p>
            <p>And if now for want of skill in diuiding the word, or conſcience to giue each his portion in due ſeaſon; either the wicked ſhall be juſtified, and the righteous condemned, or the poore ſoule ſhalbe ſcanted of it or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary food, ſhal it not be diſcouraged on the one ſide, and pined on the other, for want of due nouriſhment?</p>
            <p>Laſtly. If inſteed of fiſh, the poore ſoule ſhall be fed with ſcorpions, with corrupt doctrine to poyſon his ſoule, ſhall not his ſpirits faint, and his ſoule draw nere vnto the murtherers?</p>
            <p>The remedie therefore herein is,</p>
            <p n="1">1, That we daylie ſee our owne faylings, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelues to the word, to bee reformed thereby; becauſe the maine reaſon why wee are peſtered with ſuch carnall meanes, is, becauſe wee either not ſee our want of it, and ſo is tendered by the iuſt Lord to harden vs further, or elſe in our carnall wiſedome wee heape vnto our ſelues teachers according to our owne luſts, that may further blinde our eyes, &amp; harden our hearts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we, aſmuch as lieth in vs, ſtill keepe our ſelues to a powerfull miniſtery, changing our habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons rather then our food, that ſo by it we may bee ſtill quickened and kept afoote, howſoeuer we may ſome times heare others, yet let vs ſtill try the ſpirits, &amp; take that which is good, mourning for the hand of God, and here ſpecially reſting on the anoynting, which ſhal teach vs all things.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Labouring to be lawes vnto our ſelues in theſe lawleſſe times, and what wee cannot attaine abroad, to endeauour in our families to be Kings, and Prieſts, and Prophets in our generall callings, and in our ciuil to; as farre as we may poſſibly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Eſpecially, auoyde we hypocriſie in diuine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, labour we ſimplicity and ſincerity of heart in all
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21476:43"/>
our actions, that ſo we may not neede ſuch deceitfull cloakes to maske it vnder, that wee may not be giuen vp to be deceiued by them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And keepe we our ſelues cloſe to the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints, not forſaking the ſame for ſuch corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therein; or for feare to bee defiled and corrupted by them, leaſt we depriuing our ſelues of the benefits, we may receiue by them, and ſo be iuſtly beſt to decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, that ſtudie to cary diſciples after them, and to make them twofolde more the children of hell then they were before, Math. 23.11.12.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And keepe we our ſelues vndefiled and vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the world, auoyd wee groſſe ſinnes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous wickedneſſe, that ſo wee may not need of ſuch deceiuers to iuſtifie by their example, to warrant and ſmother by vnſeaſonable tender of mercy. Laſtly.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Renue we our repentance dayly for all knowne euils, diſcerne we the deceitfulneſſe of the heart, and inward corruptions thereof, that ſo wee may bee more willing to haue it ſearched by a powerfull miniſtery, that ſo we may with more euidence ſtand before it, as hauing intereſt therein; hauing ſtill need of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And ſo our abuſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie.</note>Thus may we leaue our firſt loue: by theſe meanes may our zeale be cooled and abated.</p>
            <p>And this ſerueth,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</hi> 1. Of tryall.</note>1. For our tryall whether euer we had any firſt loue, or no: namely, if we ſhall finde that by theſe meanes we haue bene cooled therein.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Of comfort.</note>2. And ſo for our comfort and found direction, that if we euer had this firſt loue, we ſhall recouer it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and,</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</note>3. That we may know how to recouer it, by vſing aright ſuch meanes, as being abuſed, haue beene the occaſion of this decay: the manner whereof is laide downe hereafter.</p>
            <p>And this ſerueth further,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">4. Of reproofe</note>1. For reproofe of our times, who may bee iuſtly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21476:43"/>
charged to haue left our firſt loue, by trying our ſelues by the former meanes, whereby this firſt loue is ſlaked.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And yet leſt this generall reproofe may bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the diſgrace of the power of godlineſſe, and diſcouragement of ſuch who deſire to walke with God in a dayly encreaſe: therefore ſeeing God hath a few names in <hi>Sardis,</hi> that endeauour to keepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnſpotted of the world, and ſo are not onely ſignes and wonders in the world, becauſe they will not runne with it into the ſame exceſſe; but are therefore chalenged of reuolting and falling from their loue: for their further eſtabliſhing and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>Know wee, that wee may bee ſubiect to a falſe imputation of <hi>leauing our firſt loue,</hi> in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
            <p>As 1.<note place="margin">
                  <p>The Saints may be vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged to haue left their firſt loue, and how.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 22. And that, firſt in the true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning vſe of our Chriſtian libertie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee ſubmit ourſelues to lawful autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In that we are endowed with outward proſperity.</p>
               </note> when vpon the iuſt conſideration of the nature of our Chriſtian liberty, as being ſpirituall, wee limit our zeale within the bounds of our callings: ſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto God the things that are his, that wee deny not alſo vnto Ceſar that which is. This moderation, howſoeuer with the Anabaptiſt it be traduced as luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmeneſſe, and temporizing with the world, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd affliction: yet indeed it is an holy rectifying and ordering of our zeale by humility and wiſedome, that ſo it may hold out, and bee perfited through patience, and that from the commandement of the Lord our God: Rom. 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may be falſely charged to haue left our firſt loue, when wee are outwardly encreaſed with tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bleſſings. As if becauſe proſperity is apt to coole, by making vs ſecure, and forgetfull of our God: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt needes follow, that whereſoeuer there is outward abundance, there is inward leanneſſe and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe: Pſal. 106.15. Which imputation is heereby proued to be moſt vniuſt.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:21476:44"/>1. Both becauſe the Saints of God haue increaſed outwardly, and thriuen inwardly too, as <hi>Abraham, Dauid,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The vertue of that promiſe makes hereunto: that if all things (then ſurely outward bleſſings) ſhall worke together for the good of the elect, Rom. 8.29. eſpecially ſeeing the Lord giueth grace to vſe theſe gifts aright.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note>1. And ſeeing godlineſſe hath the promiſe of this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> life aſwell as of a better; <hi>and</hi> the more the Saints par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the mercy of God, the more their thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and obedience doeth increaſe; <hi>and</hi> beeing knit <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> vnto the Lord with more bonds, <hi>ſeeing</hi> the more they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> receiue, the more they feare themſelues; <hi>and</hi> ſo by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> imparting liberally vnto others, doe eaſe themſelues of the burthen;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.20. <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> approue their loue vnto God, by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> their vnfained loue vnto his Saints: <hi>as hereby</hi> they are more deepely intereſſed in the prayers of the Saints, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> ſo is heauen more enlarged to the encreaſe of their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> loue: The Lord heares the prayers of the poore, and enlargeth the hearts of his ſtewards,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7.8.</note> to loue that God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> more feruently, that ſo enables them to comfort o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And ſo being faithfull in a little, they are ſtill encreaſed:<note place="margin">See the dayly ſacrifice for the right vſe of proſperity. 3. Spirituall wiſedome in auoyding of troubles, an occaſion to charge vs with loſſe of firſt loue.</note> vntill being full of grace and abounding in euery good worke, they are made meete partakers of that glorious inheritance: 1. Colloſſ. 12. Math. 25. 1. Cor. 15.</p>
            <p>And may not out ſpirituall wiſedome in auoyding of vnneceſſary troubles, expoſe vs ſometimes to this falſe imputation, that we haue left our firſt loue?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Yea ſurely, if either by wiſe and modeſt anſwers we auoyd troubles.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or by concealing of that trueth, which wee are not bound in conſcience to diſcouer, we ſo eſcape.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or by auoyding the rage of our enemies, when our time is not yet come, wee are yet freed from trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles by remouing from our habitations.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21476:44"/>4. Or by changing our habits and features, wee ſo auoyd the fury of the aduerſary: if by any of theſe, through the bleſſing of God we eſcape ſuch troubles, which others, for want of this wiſedome, are ouerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with; preſently we are charged with want of zeal, we are condemned to bee lukewarme, to haue left our firſt loue: and, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Eſpecially if wee vſe our goods, as a meanes to redeeme the body from trouble, oh, this is cenſured as vnlawfull; and ſo auoyding troubles as by vnlawfull meanes, wee are challenged of cowardize, want of zeale, corruption, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>An imputation how vniuſt and vncharitable it is, may appeare by theſe circumſtances:</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">
                  <p>And cleared from this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. Faith how, and whom to be giuen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and miniſter, and why.</p>
               </note> Becauſe we are not bound to giue an account of our faith to euery priuate man, but only to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and whomſoeuer hath lawful authority to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it at our hands, as the Miniſter, and ſuch as haue charge ouer vs. And that, becauſe</p>
            <p>Hereby they may haue comfort in diſcharge of their duety, that they haue not laboured in vaine: or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. May be humbled in our want of profiting and growing in knowledge, and ſo encreaſe their paines and prayers for vs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are in Gods ſtead, and in refuſing to giue an account vnto them, wee deny and renounce euen God himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They may be prouoked hereby to perſeuerance and maintenance of the trueth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though they muſt not bee Lords ouer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; to make, or alter the trueth, yet they are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes vnto the conſcience concerning the trueth, yea they are approuers and maintainers thereof, to the comfort of the beleeuer, and furtherance of his faith. And therefore,</p>
            <p>Though we giue not account of our faith, either</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the ſcorner, that hereby will take occaſion
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21476:45"/>
to inſult and blaſpheme our God and his ſacred truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or to the open enemy, that as he hath no calling to require,<note place="margin">Faith to whom not to be giuen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of.</note> ſo we haue warrant to conceale it, as being bound to preſerue life, and not caſt pearles to ſwine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or to the ignorant, that deſireth not informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereby, leſt we beare the aire, &amp; run before we are called, expoſe our profeſſion to contempt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or to the priuate Chriſtian, otherwiſe then in a caſe of neceſſity on our parts, to remoue a falſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and on his part, to guide him that is in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and deſires our helpe.</p>
            <p>Yet doe we not herein betray our faith; but rather wiſely maintaine the honour, and preſerue the vertue therof, both in defending the ſame from the reproches of the wicked, as alſo in reſeruing the vſe thereof to it fit ſeaſon and occaſion, when our God ſhalbe beſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, our profeſſion iuſtified, and brethren informed and confirmed thereby. And this is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When wee haue an eſpeciall calling to witneſſe a good profeſſion, as being inwardly furniſhed with gifts, and outwardly led foorth by the Spirit, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the cauſe of Chriſt Ieſus our Sauiour.</p>
            <p>The one of theſe we ſhall diſcerne;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">How to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne inward ſufficiencie to make open profeſsion of ſaith in the time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note>1. By ſound knowledge of the cauſe in particular, which we are to make good by whatſoeuer ſufferings, ſo that our iudgements are throughly informed, and ſo our conſciences conuinced with the trueth, doe finde reſt and comfort therein: Epheſ. 3. Phil. 1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By our ardent loue vnto that trueth which wee haue apprehended, and hearty deſire, that by any our neuer ſo great affliction, it may bee glorified in the hearts of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Philip.</hi> 27.</note>3 By our eſpeciall apprehenſion of Gods ſingular mercy towards vs, in accounting vs ſo worthy as to make profeſſion of that truth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence we euen long and deſire to taſte of that cup which the profeſſion of that truth may coſt vs.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21476:45"/>5. Yet ſo, as that our moſt ardent deſires are ſubiect to contrary buffetings for feare of our owne inability in our ſelues: and therefore,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Rather deſiring the grace of the Spirit ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct vs in the combat, that Gods cauſe may be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in our conſtancy therein; then we in any ſort mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified thereby, nay that we ſhall haue in reſpect of the fleſh, any good iſſue out of them, howſoeuer we haue many gracious promiſes, yea likelihoods for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And therefore ſimply ſubmitting our ſelues to the will of our gratious Father, rather to vndergoe any the moſt grieuous extremity, then the leaſt diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may redound to his glorious truth:</p>
            <p n="8">8. Finding in our ſelues a gratious contentment in our God, ariſing vpon long experience of the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the world, and faithfulneſſe of our gracious Father: and,</p>
            <p n="9">9. So diſcerning in our ſelues a readines to death, as being prepared thereto by daily mortification, and experience of our ſweet ſociety with our bleſſed God.</p>
            <p n="10">10. As that withall we eſpecially for this end deſire life, euen to witneſſe a good profeſſion, and giue glory vnto our God, in auouching and ſealing vp his eternall truth, with our moment any ſufferings. To this end,</p>
            <p n="11">11. Finding in our ſelues an ability of faith, relying rather on Gods promiſe to guide vs with his counſell, then our owne experience, to wade thorow the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</p>
            <p>Thus may we diſcerne inward ſufficiency to make profeſſion of our faith.</p>
            <p>And for outward calling,<note place="margin">How to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward calling to make pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profeſſion of faith in troubles,</note> and leading forth by the Spirit thereunto, there are theſe markes of it:</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of vs: as that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We haue already publiſhed and declared that truth, and ſo now much more (it being called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) are to iuſtifie the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:21476:46"/>2. Are alſo prouoked by our people, that haue depended on vs, to make good the ſame for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of their faith; leſt our ſuppreſſing or deniall, may ſhake, and make ſhipwracke thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Are eſpecially called thereto by the Magiſtrate, who may require a reaſon thereof, and forced by the gainſayings of the enemy, to defend the ſame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in reſpect of the truth. And that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When it is openly reſiſted and gainſaid of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe generation, not onely priuately and indirectly: and when,</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the ſuppreſſing thereof, the glory of our God is neceſſarily impeached, the power of religion vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, &amp;c. otherwiſe in matters</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Wherein we may be ſilent.</note>1. Of difference, which reach not thus far, we may be ſilent, reſpecting the peace of the Church, and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling rather with our God in prayer for the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch breaches, and by all priuate and peaceable meanes, rather enduring an inconuenience or couering an infirmity, then by any publike oppoſition, making a rent and diuiſion in the Church of God:</p>
            <p n="2">2. As alſo, if our perſons rather in malice are aimed at, then the truth oppugned, we may auoide the rage, by flying, concealing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. At leaſtwiſe, though we be not altogether ſilent: yet ſo far we may conceale the truth: 1. As it is not demanded: 2. And may ſatisfie the honeſt purpoſe of the queſtioner: 3. Yea, may happily, by ſtumbling of him, and turning his edge vpon another, ſo thereby diuert his malice from our ſelues. So did our Sauiour put the Phariſies and Sadduces together, and thereby eſcaped. So did he for a time goe aſide, and walked no more openly, neither committed himſelfe vnto them, becauſe he knew what was in them, and his time was not come.</p>
            <p>Nay, may we not ſhape ſuch an anſwer to our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, not only to conceale part of truth, as <hi>Samuel</hi> did.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21476:46"/>
1. Sam. 16. but euen to giue vp the wicked to their owne counſels, that will not obey the truth; bidding them goe vp and proſper, as <hi>Michaiah</hi> did, 2. King. 22. yea in an holy deriſion, vpbraiding their carnall confidence: <hi>Reioyce oh young man, and take thy fill.</hi> Eccl. 11. And ſeeing they will not be reclaimed, and hate to be reformed: may not <hi>the prudent keepe ſilence</hi> in ſuch euill times? 2. Chron. 2. Amos 5. Or ſo only ſpeake, as to leaue the incorrigible to their luſts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 9.</note> ceaſing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke a ſcorner, that we may wiſely auoid his hatred, and ſo pronouncing the wrath of God againſt him, in yeelding him vp to his owne luſts; as that he may bleſſe his ſoule in this fearefull liberty, and we by this wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may maintaine our holy liberty. Oh that we were wiſe to conſider of theſe things, and to whom the arme of the Lord ſhall reueale them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſe</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>For the waies of the Lord are righteous, and the iuſt ſhall walke in them, but the wicked ſhall fall therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>changing of our features and habits</hi> for a time, to auoid vnneceſſary trouble: herein, I take it,<note place="margin">Names and habits whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they may be changed, and how far. Names not to be changed.</note> we may thus far be iuſtified. As though</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Not to change our names.</hi> And that becauſe they are of a <hi>diuine</hi> inſtitution, as well as <hi>ciuill;</hi> impoſed not only to make <hi>diſtinction</hi> of our perſons from others, but to be <hi>witneſſes,</hi> and <hi>pledges of our profeſſion,</hi> and both <hi>memorials</hi> of Gods former mercies towards vs, as alſo <hi>euidences</hi> of Gods euerlaſting couenant with vs, to be our protector and preſeruer for euer. And therefore not to be denied if we be demanded the ſame, leſt therein we <hi>deny our faith:</hi> neither to be changed, becauſe our profeſſion muſt not be changed. Eſpecially ſeeing by deniall, or changing, we ſhall not onely not aduantage our ſelues to the thing we intend: namely, not to be knowne, ſeeing by other markes of proportion, or complexion, we may be bewrayed: but being diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, we ſhall hereby adde vnto our affliction, not only being iuſtly exempted out of Gods protection,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21476:47"/>
by reiecting the badge thereof, our names, but expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alſo the rather to the rage of man, as being tainted hereby with diſſimulation, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abrahams</hi> name chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and no warrant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this was done by God, and the caſe different. Feature.</note>Adde we hereunto, that not only we haue not any preſident in the Scripture for the like in this caſe, but alſo this changing of names is practiſed by ſuch, as, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their iudgements, or liues, or both, deny the Lord that hath bought them, namely Ieſuites, Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, Theeues, Couſeners, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For <hi>our feature,</hi> ſo farre as that may be altered by changing the faſhion of the haire, beard, &amp;c. this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but ciuill, and differing according to the diuers guiſe of each nation, ſo no painting or diſfiguring, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring to nature, or denied by ciuility, and religion, be added; I ſee not but this liberty may be vſed, in a caſe of neceſſity, for the preſeruation of life: ſo it ſtand with our callings, and tend to Gods glory.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Apparell may be changed.</note>The like we may determine concerning <hi>change of apparell,</hi> as being a ciuill thing, and therefore both ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to a religious end, the preſeruation of life, with a good conſcience, and alſo ſubiect to change, according to the diuers guiſe of nations, callings, condition, and occaſion, of proſperity, or aduerſity, keeping our ſelues within the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our Chriſtian liberty, becomming all vnto all; as to win others, ſo to preſerue our ſelues for their good;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Phil.</hi>
               </note> as moſt deſirous to be with Chriſt, which is the beſt of all, &amp; yet ready to follow the Lord in any good occaſion, for the preſeruation of life to benefit the Saints, and make ſure our owne election: <hi>Prouided</hi> that we,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Keepe our ſelues within the compaſſe of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and ciuill callings.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.</note>2. That we change not that which is vſuall to the <hi>other ſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That wee <hi>deny not our profeſsion,</hi> if this meanes will not conceale vs, being demanded particularly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That wee ſimply intend, in our preſeruation,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21476:47"/>
               <hi>Gods glory,</hi> for the benefiting of others.</p>
            <p>A fourth occaſion of this falſe imputation that wee haue left our firſt loue,<note place="margin">A fourth oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, is the vſe of ſpiritual wiſedome in reprouing for ſinne.</note> is our <hi>diſcretion in reproouing ſinne,</hi> when either wee ceaſe to reproue ſcorners, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our ſoules doe not ceaſe to weepe in ſecret for them, and our contrary conuerſation is a conuiction of them, or reproue priuatly, and generally: If in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, yet making difference of perſons in regard of their calling and quality of their ſinne; ſauing ſome with feare, and yet raiſing vp others with the ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Gal. 6.1. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Which imputation how vnjuſt it is, may appeare by the rules of the holy Ghoſt; 1. Tim. 5. 1. Mat. 19. And alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the <hi>practiſe of the Saints: Nathan.</hi> 2. Sam. 12. <hi>Paul:</hi> Compare the practiſe in reprouing the Church of Corinth, firſt Epiſtle 11. chap. and the Church of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. 3. chap. but aboue all, the practiſe of our Sauiour is peereleſſe, in his different reproofe of the Scribes and Phariſes: Mat. 23. Luke 11. and of his diſciples. Mat. 8. Mat. 26.27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A fift occaſion</hi> of this vniuſt challenge,<note place="margin">A fifth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> that wee may looſe our firſt loue, is, when the hand of God lying heauily vpon vs in ſome outward emptying, becauſe our eſtate is decayed outwardly, therefore the world concludes a decay within: eſpecially, if wee ſurceaſe in a meaſure ſuch dueties of charity, wherein before when our cup ouerflowed; we abounded towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12.13.</note> Which by this may appeare to be moſt vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; becauſe it is the purpoſe of the heart which God reſpects, which may bee no leſſe open to our brother, though our purſe bee ſtraitned, yea beeing ſcanted of this outward deuotion,<note place="margin">A ſixth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for our families. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.</note> may be more enlarged in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall almes, to procure mercy for the ſoule, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment in all eſtates: Act, 3.6.</p>
            <p>A <hi>ſixth occaſion</hi> there is alſo of this falſe imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when we rectifie our charity by wiſedome to our
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21476:48"/>
ſelues, ſo diſtributing to others, as that we prouide for our owne, leſt we be worſe then infidels, and ſo louing our neighbour, as that wee prooue not cruell to our ſelues; ſo diuiding to others, that wee preferre the houſhold of faith, Gal. 6.10. both doing the beſt good, and, as wee may, continue and hold out longeſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For which, ſeeing we haue the warrant of the holy Ghoſt, as we ought to auoyd all appearance of this euil by moderation, in our procuring and vſage of theſe things: ſo need we not feare hereby any cooling of our loue. Onely make we this vſe of this vniuſt imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as to ſuſpect our ſelues inregard of our carnal loue, and to try our abyding in the loue of God, by ſuch a loue vnto our ſelues, as may prouide for the fleſh, to the humbling and mortifying of the ſame, as may further our ſelues and others, to thoſe durable riches, which are at the right hand of our God for euermore.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A ſeuenth oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to this vniuſt chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, that we haue loſt our firſt loue, is the vſe of our Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Tim</hi> 4.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</note>Laſtly, wee may be falſely charged to haue left our firſt loue:</p>
            <p>When encreaſing of knowledge of our right in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur Chriſt, and from him in theſe outward things wee take liberty for the vſe of ſome things, (which before wee refrained, as being either not informed, or not throughly reſolued concerning them) either becauſe they are indifferent, and ſo <hi>are all ours in Chriſt,</hi> and being ſanctified by the word and prayer, may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vſed, ſeeing <hi>to the pure all things are pure.</hi> Or elſe being ſimply good, are now of conſcience to bee em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, and cheerefully practiſed, that they may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vs to the chiefeſt good. Which, how falſe an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation it is, ſeeing the rules of the Word, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Saints haue made good: 1. Cor. 9. Gal. 2. &amp;c. Therefore let vs feare the cooling of our loue,<note place="margin">The right vſe of Chriſtian liberty in things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.9.</note> in the vſe of this liberty, ſo that our conſciences be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and practiſe warranted by <hi>theſe rules:</hi> namely firſt,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the meanes of our encreaſe in knowledge be the <hi>word of trueth,</hi> not the <hi>authority of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:21476:48"/>2. <hi>That wee be able to diſcerne betweene things that differ:</hi> not ſtumbling as euil things vnder the pretence of indifferencie; not ſubiecting things ſimply good, to the nature of things indifferent, making the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worſhip of God, a matter of indifferency, as the preaching of the Goſpell, catechiſing, faſting, &amp;c. yea thruſting out the ſubſtance of holineſſe for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement thereof. That as wee deſpiſe not order, ſo it further true deuotion: ſo we reſt not in the outſide and make an idole of bodily ſeruice; Rom. 14.1. Philip. 9.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That in this liberty we offend not our Chriſtian brother: neither the Magiſtrate, by refuſing what hee lawfully impoſeth; nor the weake brother,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 13.</note> by not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming him in the true vſe of theſe things; or vſing what may juſtly giue occaſion, either of doubting in faith, or corruption in life: 1. Cor. 8. Rom. 14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That herein alſo wee not onely auoyde what may hurt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but in all ſpiritual wiſedome doe that which may further to the beſt good, euen the ſaluation of the ſoule: 1. Cor. 9.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And all this to the onely praiſe of our glorious God, through Ieſus Chriſt: 1. Cor. 10.31.</p>
            <p>Thus may wee bee falſly charged to haue left our firſt loue, and thus may we be eſtabliſhed againſt theſe falſe imputations.</p>
            <p>But ſay, what others faſten vpon me,<note place="margin">8. Whether want of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of former comforts may be a iuſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation that we haue left our firſt loue.</note> that I feare in my ſelfe, I feele not that joy and inward comfort I ſometimes had: theſe ouerflowings and extraordinary ſweetneſſe, though I faint after them, and refreſh my ſoule with the meditation thereof, yet I finde them not ſo abound and runne ouer, as in former times: may I not hereby conjecture, that I haue loſt my firſt loue? nay may I not feare that all is loſt?</p>
            <p>Nay now I finde it contrary with me; inſteed of ioy I am ouerwhelmed with ſorrowes, inſteed of Gods gratious preſence, I feare hee hath forſaken mee, I
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21476:49"/>
haue no anſwere in prayer, no comfort in any duety; the ſorrowes of the deepe doe ſeaze vpon me, and the jawes of hell doe gape vpon me.</p>
            <p>Surely the Lord giue thee wiſedome heerein, that thou doeſt not wrong thine owne heart, and prejudice the wiſedome and mercy of thy God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Remember that thou liueſt by faith, &amp; not by ſenſe; 2. Cor. 3.7. though thou ſeeſt no outward meanes, yet thy ſaith will aſſure thee, that God is able, &amp; will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide him a ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered herein. <hi>Iob.</hi> 13 15.</note> Gen. 22. Yea though thou haſt no inward feeling of comfort, yet ſhalt thou truſt in God, euen though he kill thee. <hi>And</hi> this is the victory of thy <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> faith, euen to beleeue aboue feeling: thus is thy faith perfited, euen laying holde on things not ſeene, when it is depriued of the ſenſe of things paſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</note> &amp; preſent. <hi>And</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> may not thy God withdraw theſe comforts from thee, for the further tryal of thy faith and loue vnto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; that thogh thou want that comfort which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore thou haſt had, yet ſtil thou canſt giue glory vnto thy God, in beleeuing his word, and enlarge thy loue vnto his Maieſty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20.</note> euen when he ſeemes to haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> thee? <hi>And</hi> canſt thou haue a better tryall of the power &amp; purenes of thy faith, then aboue hope to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue vnder hope in the promiſes of thy God, ſubiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy chiefeſt good vnto the glory of thy God? and through want of preſent ſenſe being guided to forget what thou haſt enioyed, leſt through ſpirituall pride thou mighteſt reſt therin, &amp; rob God of his glory,thou doeſt the rather make haſte to that which is before, by the power of thy faith ſeeing a farre off, yea, laying faſt hold on eternall life, by renuing thy ſtrength in Ieſus Chriſt? And ſeeing wee are now aſſured of the trueth of our conuerſion, by this ſeale of Gods loue ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in our hearts, working in vs a feare of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, and refreſhing our hearts with vnſpeakeable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts: haue we now ſuch need of the continuance of them, as if all were loſt becauſe we ſtill feele them not:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21476:49"/>
or we could not goe forward without the daily ſence thereof? will we ſtill be children, that haue neede of dandling and entticing with ſuch toies, or rather are we not growing to be men: and ſo to be hardned with trials and ſtrange abaſings. And is it not beſt to be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within, that ſo we may be fitter for any outward emptying. Is it not fit to be a while diſuſed of theſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ioyes, that ſo we may moſt hunger after euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioy, that we more earneſtly labour and haſten thereafter. And may we not giue our God iuſt cauſe to withdraw his countenance from vs, by falling into groſſe ſinne, doting on the fading ioyes of the world, &amp;c. and ſo we may be ſo wiſely ſcanted of perfect ioy, as that ſtill we ſhal be recompenced with what is fitter for vs for the preſent, with what may further vs to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall comforts.</p>
            <p>Is not the Lord herein wonderfull, that by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing ſenſe of preſent ioy, he both purgeth vs of ſuch euils as may corrupt the ſame, namely ſpirituall pride and ſecurity, and alſo cauſeth vs hereby to lay faſter hold on Ieſus Chriſt, who only muſt perfect the worke that is begun in vs? And canſt thou expreſſe thy loue in greater meaſure vnto thy God, then to loue him then, when he ſeemes to haue forſaken thee? then to follow after him when he ſeemes to run from thee? doth not this aduance the ſincerity of thy loue? doth not this exceedingly approue thy conformity to thy Sauiour, that as he was contented to be abaſed in himſelfe, yea to become of no reputation, that thou maiſt be accepted; ſo thou art contented to be emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, that God may be glorified, thou canſt willingly want preſent comfort, that thy God may haue vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned worſhip, when now, not ſo much for thine owne ſake as for his glory, thou doſt beleeue in him, when though he kill thee, yet thou wilt truſt in him? And canſt thou be a looſer, where the Lord is ſuch a gainer by thee? canſt thou leaue thy loue, when the Lord
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21476:50"/>
doth purpoſe to trie the ſoundneſſe of it, when the Lord prouoketh thee to liue by faith, when by the power of faith he will thus enable thee to lay hold of eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note>Surely as this is the life of faith to exceed preſent ſenſe; ſo this want of preſent comfort thus conceiued, and applied, ſhall be both a meanes to enable thee to make better vſe of ſuch ioy, when the Lord ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine turne his countenance vpon thee: and in the meane time miniſter exceding comfort vnto thy ſoule that thou doſt conſtantly beleeue in,<note place="margin">Reſolution herein.</note> and vnfainedly loue the Lord thy God. And therfore doubt not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of any decay of thy loue vnto thy God, becauſe the Lord in his wiſedome, for thy triall, withdrawes the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> preſent pledges of his loue from thee. <hi>For</hi> neither couldſt thou endure at all, in thy ſenſe of this want of preſent comfort, if thy God did not ſecretly vphold thee with inward and vnſpeakable conſolations. <hi>And</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> in that thou diſcerneſt want of ioy, may it not be ſo much becauſe thou wanteſt that which thou haſt had,<note place="margin">Note.</note> as that by faith thou apprehendeſt that vnſpeakeable ioy which thou haſt not: which that it doth euacuate and empty thee of ſenſe of preſent comfort, it is no more maruell, then that the glorious light of the Sun ſhould obſcure the light of a candle, or that a drop ſhold not be diſcerned being caſt into the main ocean.</p>
            <p>Only for thy full ſatisfaction herein, examine thy heart in this caſe, by theſe rules;</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Triall hereof.</note>Firſt, that <hi>thou haſt not giuen thy God iuſt occaſion to withdraw theſe comforts from thee: either.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Occaſions of leauing our firſt loue,</note>1. By not priſing them highly, and inualuably:</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or by not being throwly humbled with them: elſe</p>
            <p n="3">3. Through beholding of the Sun when it ſhined thou waſt dazled and puffed vp therewith.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And ſo didſt not imploy them to the beſt vſe of thy Maſter, aduancing his glory, and to the good of thy brother.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb facs="tcp:21476:50"/>5. Either thou didſt meaſure the infinite loue of thy God by them, &amp; ſo didſt ouerrate theſe comforts.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Or elſe thou didſt corrupt them by mingling them with the fleſh, and making them ſerue the luſts thereof.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Either thou conceiuedſt baſely of the meanes that conuaied theſe comforts vnto thee, namely, the miniſtery of the word, dreaming of reuelations and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary meanes,</p>
            <p n="8">8. Or elſe being ouerioyed with theſe comforts, thou becameſt preſumptuous and idle, neglecting thy calling which God hath appointed to humble thee, and thereby to fit thee to greater comforts.</p>
            <p>Or if thou haſt giuen thy gracious God iuſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (as who doth not) yet ſtill thou art ready to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy God, and condemne thy ſelfe, and therefore here</p>
            <p>Secondly, examine thy iudgement and <hi>affections</hi> in the want of theſe preſent comforts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Yet that thou eſteeme not thy caſe deſperate for want of them: Neither,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be ſo contented with this diſpenſation of thy God, but that it reioyceth thee vnfainedly to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what thou haſt felt, and ſo eſteem thy caſe formerly better then now.</p>
            <p>That thou acknowledge it iuſt with God to ſtrip thee of this meaſure, yea that thou haſt deſerued vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be forſaken of him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yea it reioyceth thee at the heart to obſerue the happy end glorious condition of ſuch excellent ones that are rauiſhed with this loue of Chriſt, that are thus enflamed with zeale of Gods glory, walke thus cheerfully and conſtantly in their holy calling, that ſo though thou haſt cauſe to mourne for thine owne particular, yet withall thou canſt reioyce for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ioy, and ſo intereſt thy ſelfe hereby in the ſame.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb facs="tcp:21476:51"/>4. Thou doſt vnfainedly mourne for the want of this gratious aſpect, and withall</p>
            <p n="5">5. Doſt vnfainedly hunger after the returne, and increaſe thereof. And to this end</p>
            <p n="6">6. Doſt vſe conſcionably, and reioyce in, the meanes of the preaching of the Goſpell, and effectuall prayer for the recouery of the ſame. Cant. 1. &amp; 5.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Yea doſt labour to confer with the Saints, and holy ones, making triall of their feelings, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereby thy dulnes, by prouoking their prayers &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And waiteſt patiently the leiſure of thy God, for the returne of comfort, as may ſtand with his glory reſoluing thy ſelfe, that his grace is ſufficient for thee.</p>
            <p>Thus if thou art reſolued in thy iudgement, and art thus eſtabliſhed in thy affections,</p>
            <p>The leſſe thou feeleſt the loue of thy God, the more is the triall of thy loue towards him; and the more he tries thy loue, the more is his loue towards thee, and therefore thy loue to him muſt needs be enlarged: which thou doſt expreſſe by thy faith, in beleeuing beyond thy feeling, and hereby giuing glory vnto God, thou doſt grow in his fauour by the power whereof thou art increaſed in his obedience, and ſo followeſt hard after the marke, to obtaine that crowne of glory.</p>
            <p>If now it ſhall pleaſe thy gratious God to humble thee yet more and more, and ſo leauing thee yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be buffeted by Satan, who will now ſtep in to take aduantage of this thy iealouſie, and doubting of the loſſe of thy firſt loue, thereby to call in queſtion the truth of thy conuerſion. And ſo inferring that thou haſt been vtterly deceiued, that all thy former labovr hath been in vaine, ſhall thereby confound all thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hopes, and ſo prouoke thee to a kind of deſpaire, as if now it were in vaine, or loo late to begin againe; and ſo hereby procure thee to neglect the true meanes
<pb facs="tcp:21476:51"/>
As being that which rather will now more condemne thee, and ſo ſhall tender thee the vſe of carnall reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, either for the preſent comfort of thy appalled conſcience, or at leaſt to dampe and lay it aſleep in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſecurity.</p>
            <p>That thou mayſt now reſiſt the deuill, and gratiouſly preuent an vtter and irrecouerable downefall, haue thou alwayes in readineſſe theſe preſeruatiues.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that thou neuer waſt, neither canſt euer be ſo low brought in this pit of deſpaire;<note place="margin">1. Remember the ſufferings of thy Sauiour &amp;c.</note> but that thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour taſted farre more deepely of this cup for thy ſake, when his ſoule being heauy vnto the death, he cryed out in the anguiſh and bitternes of his ſoule, that his God had forſaken him: And ſeeing he is ſuch an high Prieſt, as therefore was ſubiect to our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that he might haue compaſſion on vs, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all our greateſt infirmities and abaſings vnto vs, by theſe his ſufferings: ſeeing hee was therefore thus tempted, that he might ſuccour vs in our greateſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; and by his agonies hath taken away the ſting of our greateſt defections,<note place="margin">His glorious conqueſts.</note> that ſo they ſhall not onely not hurt vs; but alſo prooue gratious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiues vnto vs, to preuent worſe euils, ſeeing hee hath ouercome that heauy diſtreſſe, and now triumphs for vs in Heauen, and makes continuall interceſſion for vs, in our greateſt emptyings; ſeeing his fulneſſe of joy is ours already in title and poſſeſſion; yea, ſo farre in vſe as may fit vs to the like fulneſſe: therefore, alſo in Chriſt are we more then conquerours, and that wee may haue experience of our glorious victory in him: therefore it pleaſeth our good God to leaue vs thus far to this heauy diſtreſſe; that ſo in theſe our ſufferings, wee may bee conformable to our Head, and thereby haue a teſtimony, that wee are his true and louing members, who in all our ſorrowes had his portion at the full. And ſo ſuffering with our Sauiour in this bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter agony, we may not onely as liuely members fulfill
<pb facs="tcp:21476:52"/>
in our ſoule and body, the ſufferings of our Sauiour: but ſeeing he is now gone vp, and will draw vs all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore will he alſo plucke vs vp vnto him, euen out of this horrible pit; and make our triumph and victory to bee more glorious, by how much wee haue endured with him, and for him greater afflictions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. That it is an argument wee are truely conuerted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Satan chalengeth the ſame, and ſeekes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter.</note>Eſpecially if we conſider, that were wee not pluckt out of Satans poſſeſſion, did not the ſtronger man now poſſeſſe vs, we ſhould be quiet and nouzelled in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. That ſtrong man would not now ſeeke to reenter in againe; hee would not thus queſtion and labour to confound our bleſſed hope, if our hope were onely in this life, becauſe now wee are trauayling towardes Heauen; therefore doth hee thus labour either to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoynt, or at leaſt to interrupt our journey thither, and at leaſt hereby to make it more vncomfortable and tedious vnto vs. And is it not good for to haue this experience of his malice, that ſo wee may ſtill be put to the tryall of our ſound walking in this way, that we may walke more humbly and watchfully with our God,<note place="margin">3. That theſe inward bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings preuent outward baits of pleaſure.</note> that ſo we may more heartyly faint and long to be at our journeyes end: that ſo we may make more ſpeed to come to the wiſhed hauen? Doeth not our wiſe and gratious God turne about this malice of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan in troubling vs within, to preuent many worſe baites and allurements of the world, and the pleaſures thereof, which might happily more diſtract vs out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and hinder our journey which happily would take more place with vs, if we failed with a conſtant gate of inward peace and joy. Is not this an vndoubted teſtimony of the ſoundneſſe of our conuerſion. Is not this a gratious meanes to growth and perſeuerance? If now in the next place, it ſhalbe ſuggeſted, that thogh indeed our Sauior Chriſt endured ſuch bitter agonies, yet he was God, and ſo by the power of his Deity, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercame theſe extremities: as for vs, we may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume vpon any ſuch power, and therefore may not
<pb facs="tcp:21476:52"/>
expect the like iſſue? Conſider wee that whatſoeuer power the Lord Ieſus was inueſted withall, it belongs alſo vnto vs, becauſe Chriſt is ours;<note place="margin">3. That God is able to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.</note> and the ſame power which raiſed vp Ieſus from the dead, will alſo raiſe vs vp out of our loweſt abaſings. And therefore, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wee cannot yet bee perſwaded of the particular will of our God in our preſent recouery: howſoeuer this ſenſe of our owne vnworthineſſe may for the preſent ſtand between the ſight of Gods loue and our faith, that we cannot apprehend what wee ſo heartily deſire, yet let the power of our faith breake through the fogge of our deſert, and aſcend freely to the power of God, perſwading our ſelues that our God is able to recouer vs to what we would, or at leaſt to ſuſtaine vs in our greateſt extremity. And,<note place="margin">1. Prooued from the ſenſe of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent decay.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Haue we not a liuely euidence hereof euen from our preſent condition, whether we conſider our vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which ſeeks to blind the eye of our faith, or reſpect our preſent abaſing, which intends to ſink vs in deſpair: for if we ſhal lay to hart what we haue deſerued, might we not long agoe haue been plunged into the ſenſe of theſe torments which now wee feare? might not hell haue deuoured vtterly, which now doth but gape vpon vs. Nay if wee ſhall acknowledge vnfainedly our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent deſert,<note place="margin">2 From the conſcience of our deſert, and ſo what we might haue fallen into thereby.</note> might we not be giuen vp to a deeper mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of diſtreſſe, then poſſibly we could beare? might we not breake out into more deſperate blaſphemings and horrors, to violence againſt our ſelues, then yet by Gods mercy wee are left vnto? ſurely if wee conſider what Satan would haue, we may build vpon it; that as it is our damnation which he aymes at, ſo hee cares not how ſoon he finiſh his work, that ſo he may haue more worke to encreaſe his own damnation. He would not be contented to ſcarre vs onely with the feare of hell,<note place="margin">4. That God is ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs, and willing to helpe vs.</note> but his deſire is to fill vp hell with ſpeed, &amp; ſo to plunge vs in irrecouerable torments. And therefore as we may behold here the power of our God in bridling Satan,
<pb facs="tcp:21476:53"/>
not that he hath not his full ſwing at vs, that yet wee are not paſt hope. So if we ſhall lay here unto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of our vnworthineſſe, wee may ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the loue of God appeareth alſo in this his diſpenſation, not dealing with vs according to our deſerts; but in this ſhew of his anger, remembring mercy, and ſuſtayning vs by his mighty power from ſinking vtterly.</p>
            <p>And therefore, that we may hence gather this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that though we fall, yet wee ſhall riſe againe; becauſe the Lord puts vnder his hand, ſeeing Satan will now put hard to vs, that the time is paſt, that our hope is periſhed from the earth; therefore learne wee thus to expell theſe fiery darts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, conſider wee that Satan is a lier from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,<note place="margin">5. That the time is paſt.</note> and therefore conclude wee that the time is not paſt. The rather</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe wee muſt know that the times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are in the Lord, onely to diſpoſe and determine of; It is councell to Satan preſumption ſo to conclude.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wee haue hereby a gratious euidence, that the time is not paſt: becauſe wee yet liue, and are capable of mercy, and the meanes of mercy are yet tendered vnto vs; yea, wee haue need of Gods mercy, we feele the want of it, and therefore it belongs vnto vs: now is the time to be partaker thereof, ſeeing our God is an helper in the needfull time of trouble: Nay, we hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily deſire it, and neglect no meanes to obtayne the ſame, ſeeking this comfort where it may bee found: and therefore they that ſeeke, ſhall finde, and if wee knocke, it ſhall bee opened vnto vs, our will is to be deliuered, as it is of God, and not our ſelues, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his gift, hee will perfect the ſame in fulfilling our deſires; it argues him willing to helpe vs, becauſe hee giues the will to deſire it, and our will ſhall bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, till he accompliſh it.</p>
            <p>If yet our gratious God differ to helpe vs; If hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
<pb facs="tcp:21476:53"/>
our afflictions encreaſe,<note place="margin">6 The ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the ſhorter and more comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table iſſne.</note> euen while we ſeeme to be deliuered from them. If the more we pray the leſſe comfort we find, the more we are put off, the more Sathan rageth, and ſo happily prouokes to impatiency or deiects with diſtruſt. Know we for a certainty, that the more the diuell fareth the ſhorter, is his time, the more we pray and obtaine not, the more is obedience tried. That we pray becauſe we are commanded, the more is our faith tried, that we can wait on our God with patience, that ſo patience may bring forth his perfect worke. The leſſe comfort we haue for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, in any ſeruice of God, the more is behind in the acceptable time.</p>
            <p>Meane time know we, that it is no meane portion of comfort to hunger after Gods countenance though yet we haue it not; It cannot but yeeld ſound com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the poore ſoule, to be contented with the will of God, yea though the Lord ſhould kill him, yet not to caſt away his confidence: and yet to obey his will in hungring after a further meaſure, that ſo it may be vnto vs as we doe beleeue.</p>
            <p>And ſhall beggars be their owne caruers herein,<note place="margin">7 This ſerues to renue and trie the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our repentance.</note> doth not God know what is fitteſt for vs. Haue we not prouoked our God to deale far more ſharply with vs, and is it not his mercy that we are not vtterly conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, are we fit to be comforted, before we are healed? And do not our great ſinnes require a ſharpe corraſiue can we be brought to ſound repentance, till we be caſt out of our ſelues, and but by a ſentence of death; euen by the terrors of hell muſt we not haue ſome ſence of what we haue deſerued, that ſo we may by repentance auoide the vengeance to come. And may it not now ſo fall out that the Lord will not heare our prayers, becauſe we regard iniquity in our hand, ſhall Iſrael preuaile, while the excommunicate thing remaines. Are we fit for the comfort and ioy of Gods fauour ſo long as our ſinne ſtands before him to grieue his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21476:54"/>
muſt he not goe vnto his place, that we may ſeeke him diligently?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8 God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what is fitteſt for vs, and he doth what is beſt for our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition to bring vs to repentance</note>And therefore in ſtead of complaining on God, that he hath done vs wrong herein, let vs in the name of God complaine againſt our ſelues. What is it which he could haue done, which he hath not done vnto vs? And what haue not we done againſt him which we ſhould not doe: how haue we not in all things requited him euill for good. And therefore in ſtead of deſiring com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, let vs ſearch and trie our hearts how we haue offended our gratious God, let vs iudge our ſelues that we may not be iudged of him: ſo ſhall we take Satans office out of his hands in accuſing of our ſelues,<note place="margin">9 The way to preuent ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and iudge our ſelues.</note> ſo ſhall we ſtop his mouth, and confound his malice, and making hereby our way vnto the throne of grace, we ſhall find the blood of Ieſus to ſpeake better things for vs then the blod of <hi>Abel,</hi> firſt to waſh vs thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from our ſinnes: and then to miniſter ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto our ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">10 That we are not the greateſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note>For our further comfort herein: becauſe when we are about this practiſe of iudging of our ſelues, and the Lord by this inward rod drawes vs thereto: It is now Satans policie to keepe vs in theſe diſtractions, and ſo to ſucke vs in deſpaire, by perſwadings that our caſe herein is ſingular! Either none are ſo grieuous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as we are, or elſe none ſo deeply plunged in this extremity as our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Therefore learne we this, to reſiſt his fiery darts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, though we ſhould be the greateſt of all ſinners, yet ſhall the mercy of God appeare the greater in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning ſo grieuous a ſinner, more glory ſhall redound to his name, in being ſo incomparably mercifull: more loue is due from ſo great a ſinner, more care to pleaſe ſo bountifull a Father.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it will not appeare that we are greater ſinners then any: ſo long as we feele our ſinnes and deſire to be eaſed of them: ſeeing theſe two things
<pb facs="tcp:21476:54"/>
make vp the meaſure of ſinne:<note place="margin">Who is the greateſt ſinner</note> either not to feele ſinne at all, by reaſon of hardneſſe of heart, and the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence being paſt ſeeking, or elſe to deſpiſe and reiect the remedy againſt ſinne: though we haue ſome ſenſe thereof either through Pride that we need it not, or through deſpaire that we thinke it will doe no good.</p>
            <p>Thirdly though we are not the greateſt ſinners in compariſon of others:<note place="margin">11 It is not vnprofitable to commence our ſelues to be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſinner.</note> yet ſhall it not be amiſſe to comence our ſelues to be ſuch: partly becauſe we know our owne eſtate beſt, and not others; and therefore in this reſpect we may eſteem our caſe more hainous then any other: and partly becauſe we are more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with the loue of Chriſt, and ſo in the abundance of his loue doe diſcerne our vnworthineſſe and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions more and more in our ſelues. That ſo ſtill we may more deny our ſelues, and labour to be found in Chriſt, not hauing our owne righteouſneſſe: ought we not in charity to thinke others better then our ſelues, may we not hope the beſt of the worſt, becauſe the Lord may recouer them: And is there any outwardly ſo vile, but that our hearts tell vs we find far more fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full corruptions within vs, then poſſibly we can chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge others by that which appeareth outwardly: and ſhall not our charity to others call vs more into our ſelues, that ſo we may more narrowly ſearch our owne hearts, more iudge our ſelues, that we may not be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of the world? ſhall not the ſence of our vileneſſe make vs more compaſſionate vnto others, that ſo the Lord may haue compaſſion on vs? And can we be too vile in our eies, that ſo we may hunger more earneſtly after the mercy of God? And therefore though others may be greater ſinners then we, yet is it wiſedome for vs to feele our ſelues to be the greateſt, that ſo there may be no place left for going further on the ſcore, that we may now thinke it ſufficient that we haue ſpent the time paſt, yea too much that we haue already ſo prouoked our God, that we may not differ our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb facs="tcp:21476:55"/>
any longer, that the meanes of God may not be reiected of vs. If we wiſely conſider the policy of ſatan herein, howſoeuer he lay to vs that we are the greateſt of all ſinners, yet hereby he intends to plunge vs deeper in ſinne, to driue vs to deſpaire, that ſo we may deſpiſe mercy, &amp; ſo depriue our ſelues of the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of it. And therefore to admit wee were the greateſt ſinners, though we feele our ſelues to be in worſe caſe then any, this ſhall be a meanes to be more emptied in our ſelues, the more to faint after the mercy of God in Chriſt Ieſus. Nay is it not ſatans po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie by perſwading vs that we are of all ſinners the chiefe, if he cannot plunge vs in deſpaire, yet to make vs ſecure and careleſſe: We know the worſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs make no bones of ſinne, let vs not trouble our ſelues with any ſuch reckoning, Gods mercies are greater, Chriſt merit is ſufficient, doe we what we can Gods purpoſe can not be altered. Thus doth ſatan play vpon the left hand, and on right, now vrging to deſpaire, becauſe neuer any ſo bad as we, then prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to preſumption, be we neuer ſo bad. And doth not our wiſe and gracious God bring light of this darkneſſe, that becauſe we are ſo vile therefore we not preſume any further. It is the wonder of Gods loue to tender grace to ſo great ſinners, and ſhalbe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our father to giue hope to ſuch caſtawayes: it ſhall be our greater comfort that he accepts ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne wretches: It ſhall be our greater care now to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme the time, and to labour more abundantly in more powerfull obedience, to teſtifie againe our loue to ſo exceeding bountifull a Sauiour. And ſhall we then doubt that our God will againe receiue vs into fauour, who hath ſo freely loued vs being his enemies. And therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To this end call to mind former mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</note>Be we wiſe now to call to mind the dayes of old, remember we that the fauour of God hath formerly ſhined vpon vs, meditate we of the wonderfull things
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21476:55"/>
that the Lord hath done for our ſoules, and can the Lord forget to be mercifull? ſhall the couenant of the day and night be broken,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 33.20.21.22.</note> that then ſhould not be day and night in their ſeaſon. Then may the couenant of the Lord be broken with his ſeruants; ſurely al the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of Heauen cannot bee numbred, neither the ſand of the ſea meaſured, ſo will the Lord multiply his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies vnto his children, ſo will he neuer faile them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12 3. <hi>Eſay</hi> 49.15.</note> nor forſake them: though a mother ſhould forget the fruit of her wombe, yet wil I not forget thee, ſaith the Lord, though I correct thee in iudgement, yet will I not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly caſt thee off: Ierem. 30.11. ſaith the Lord: for I am God in the midſt of thee, whom I loue, I loue vnto the end: Ioh. 13.2. and therefore for a while haue I forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thee, yet in euerlaſting compaſsions will I gather thee againe, Eſay 54.8. As I haue ſworne that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Noah</hi> ſhall no more goe ouer the earth; ſo haue I ſworne, that I will not be angry with thee (for euer) nor rebuke thee (to thy deſtruction) yea well may the mountaines remoue, and the hils fall downe; though heauen and earth ſhall paſſe, and the night and the day ſhal be no more: neither yet ſhall the couenant of my peace fall away ſayth the Lord that hath compaſſion on thee; for my word endureth for euer; I haue ſworne by my holineſſe, that I will not faile <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what ſhal then ſeparat thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of God,<note place="margin">13. That all the Saints haue drunke of this cup vnto thee.</note> hall thy greateſt ſins ſerue to magnifie the loue of God vnto thee. Oh, but here Satan doth reply that herin thy caſe is ſingular, neuer any ſo deiected and caſt down as thou art: the ſaints of God haue paſſed their time more cheerfully, they haue been confident in God, reſolut of his fauour: they haue been heard of the Lord, in their greateſt extremities, they haue been deliuered &amp; reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued again and therfore, ſeing thou remaineſt ſtil in this agony, &amp; canſt find no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, hath not the Lord forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, that reiects thy praiers, that neglects thy teares, ſeeing thy afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> encreaſed, thou ſeeſt no end therof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21476:56"/>Surely the Lord giue vs vnderſtanding in al things, ſay our caſe were ſuch as neuer were any like vnto vs, yet may not the Lord doe with vs what he will? if he ſhould caſt vs into hell, ſhould we not deſire his glory aboue all things? And if by this our greater abaſing, he intends to propoſe vs as enſamples to them which ſhal beleeue in time to come, to make vs preſidents of his exceeding mercies; ſhall not he haue the more glory, and we haue the more comfort in the end? And yet for our preſent comfort herein; is there any tentation here befallen vs, that belongs not vnto man? that the Saints of olde haue not gone before vs in, that euery childe of God, more or leſſe, muſt certainely vndergoe: nay, haue not many of Gods children exceeded vs in this temptation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.1.6.2. <hi>Pſal</hi> 77.</note> conſider wee the example of <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> of <hi>Ieremie</hi> and the reſt? haue not the venome of Gods arrowes drunke vp their ſpirits? haue they not broken out into many bitter complaints and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, through the extremity of their paines? haue they not euen ſeemed to forſake the Lord, and giuen ouer their intereſt in his loue and goodneſſe, Ier. 20. And hath the gratious Lord yet kept thee from theſe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible out-breakings? or mayſt thou happily bee left ſo farre as the worſt? yet ſeeing our gratious God hath reſtored euery one of them; yea, then refreſhed them when they haue bene at the worſt, wll he not alſo raiſe thee vp againe, oh thou of litle faith?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">14 That God differs our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing in great mercy.</note>If thou thinkeſt he will not, becauſe he doth it not, conſider how long this rod hath lien vpon thy betters, and canſt thou not bee content to ſtay the Lords lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as well as they; ſhall not the Lord recompence thy longer ſtay with more durable comforts? Had not <hi>Dauid</hi> theſe buffetings euen all his life? haue not many of Gods deare children beene exerciſed heerewith to their death, yea in their death haue been hereby ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to the world, as if they died deſperately, vnto whom their holy life &amp; doctrine was a condemnation,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21476:56"/>
becauſe they would not bee reclaimed thereby; and ſhall this encourage to prophaneſſe, and exclude vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly repentance, to ſee ſuch die ſo vncomfortably, whoſe life was ſo conformable to the word, ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the world. And therefore though I cannot heere promiſe thee any time when the Lord will returne thy captiuity, and refreſh thee with former comfort; yet I dare promiſe thee that there is a time of refreſhing, Act. 3.19. at hand. And whatſoeuer thy emptying bee now, yet then thou ſhalt be filled with the fulneſſe of God, and ſo enioy at his right hand pleaſures for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more; yea all thy abaſings in this life, ſhalbe meanes to further and haſten thee thereunto; if thy afflictions are at the worſt, they will haue the ſooner end, and thine euerlaſting ioyes ſhalbe begun the ſooner; though it ſhould by thy death, yet thou ſhalt be a great gainer by it. And I dare promiſe thee further, that the Lord will lay no more vpon thee then thou art able to endure, 2. Cor. 10.13. but will giue an iſſue with the tentation, that thou mayſt be able to beare it, though the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous periſheth, and no man regards it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 57.1.2.</note> yet they are but taken away from the euils to come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſhal reſt in their beds, &amp; ſorow ſhal flie away.<note place="margin">15. That we muſt not iudge our ſelues by our tenrations.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Only here let me adjure thee to ſtay thy ſelfe herein by theſe rules; Firſt, that thy God will not eſteeme of thee, as thou art in thy tentations, they proceed of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans malice, and thine own infirmity; &amp; therefore thy gratious Father will not impute them vnto thee: yea thou ſtriue againſt them, &amp; condemneſt them, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy louing Father will not condemne thee for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Secondly, be thou wiſe to iudge of thy better part, thou ſtriueſt and canſt not preuaile, thou prayſt, and art not heard: what then, are thy prayers not heard at all, becauſe thy particular requeſt is not granted? Is not thy perſon euerlaſtingly accepted, and ſo a cuppe of colde water ſhall not looſe his rewarde. In the name of GOD I adiure thee therefore not to iudge
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21476:57"/>
peremptorily of thine eſtate by any preſent or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar action or ſucceſſe. Is not the Lord wiſe to turne thy ſinnes to good, and will he then let thy true endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours fall to the ground? though hee anſwers not thy prayer in yeelding thy particular requeſt, yet doth hee not anſwer it better, in giuing thee ſtill grace to pray vnto him, doth he not recompence thee bountifully in teaching thee patience to wait vpon him, and muſt not patience bring foorth the perfect worke? hadſt thou not then need of patience, when thou haſt done the will of God. that thou mayſt receiue the reward: and what is the reward thou waiteſt for? is it only that thy prayers may bee granted for the preſent? mayſt thou hereby happily haue thy reward already, and ſo to bee depriued of that great recompence of reward. And doth not the Lord begin this recompence in anſwering thy prayers to what is fit for thee? doth he not prepare thee to this recompence, by enabling thee hereby in patience to poſſeſſe thy ſoule, and to waite the good pleaſure of God? doth hee not hereby teach thee to commit thy ſoule in well doing into the hand of thy gratious Creator, that ſo thou mayſt work out thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in feare and trembling, and ſo be made meet for that glorious inheritance.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">To auoyd idleneſſe, and walke faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in our callings, tenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer failings.</note>3. And therefore let my adjure bee pretious vnto thee not to diſquiet thy ſelfe for delay of comfort, but rather to take heed of idlenes and curiouſity whereunto Satan will now labour to draw thee, as taking aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of thy dumpiſhnes and diſtraction. Be diligent in Gods feare, ſo farre as thou knoweſt in thy calling God hath placed thee in, &amp; iudge thy heart ſoundly for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſailings, and then I dare aſſure thee thou ſhalt not want comfort in thy obedience vnto God, if fit for thee for the preſent, and the more thou fitteſt thy ſelfe hereby for ioy, the ſooner it ſhall returne, either in this life, if thy wayes are now conſtant and more ſpirituall or elſe in the life to come neuer to faile againe. But of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21476:57"/>
this more hereafter, and commenced, and eſpecially in a treatiſe (if God will) to bee publiſhed to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, called <hi>the Cure of a wounded Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If yet thou art doubtfull of thy abiding in loue: As thou maiſt decay; ſo thou art iealous of thy ſelf herein:</p>
            <p>I ſay vnto thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.13. How to know whether we haue left our firſt loue. By theſe markes.</note> Bleſſed is the man that feareth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies.</p>
            <p>And that thou maiſt be reſolued, whether thou art decaied or no, obſerue for thy triall theſe markes therof: which are apparant ſymptomes of the leauing our firſt loue.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Know thou that if thou haſt loſt that peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, wherby thou waſt wont to come with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes into the preſence of thy God, and powre out thy ſoule in ſtrong cries and teares vnto thy God, and ſo canſt not pray with that euidence, as in former times, with that patience and conſtancy ouercomming thy God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If thou groweſt fearefull of troubles, and vſeſt carnall policy to preuent them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If thou groweſt worldly and couetous, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing thy hand from the neceſſities of thy brother, and neglecting the occaſions of charity, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If thou groweſt negligent in hearing the word, contenting thy ſelfe either with none, or an vneffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Miniſtery.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If thou canſt diſpenſe with thy ſelfe in vaine ſports and recreations, gaming, vaine talke, &amp;c. wherof here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore thou madeſt ſome conſcience, waſting thy time and wit in them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If thou canſt frame to all companies, and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize with each, as preſuming vpon thy protection, from thy Chriſtian calling. Epheſ. 5.1.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If thou art afraid of death, and neglecteſt the daily and conſtant examination of thy waies, and holy duties in priuate, vnto thy God.</p>
            <p n="8">8. If thou canſt ſo ioy in theſe earthly things, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21476:58"/>
not to feele a loathſomneſſe in them, or not to vſe them as ſparkes to increaſe the fire of thy ſpirituall ioy.</p>
            <p n="9">9. If thou meaſureſt the happineſſe of the life to come, by that ſenſe which for the preſent thou haſt thereof; thou doſt not liue by faith, and therefore thou haſt left thy firſt loue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Symptomes that follow the leuuing of our firſt loue.</note>And for thy comfort obſerue herein an eſpeciall mercy of thy God, that there <hi>will follow this loſſe of loue:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Inward trouble of conſcience,</hi> which will giue thee no reſt, till thou haſt reſolued thy caſe with God, and recouered: Pſal 6.38. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some outward <hi>ſenſible ſtripe,</hi> either in thy goods, perſon, children, to open thine eyes the better, and bring thee to repentance, Iob. 33.15.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Now the world will not faile to flatter thee, and as it were to owne thee, that ſo thou maiſt ſuſpect thy ſelfe the rather.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And yet that thou maiſt diſcerne the worlds loue, thou ſhalt not want ſome mocke and reproach, to caſt the durt of thy decay in thy face, that ſo thou maiſt be aſhamed and confounded in this decay.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And happily thou maiſt be giuen vp to ſome <hi>groſſe ſinne,</hi> the more to diſcredit thee with the world, that ſo thou maiſt not be corrupted with the flattery thereof.</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>thus thou maiſt recouer out of this decay:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">How to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer firſt loue.</note>1. Reſt vpon the <hi>promiſes of thy God,</hi> that thou ſhalt recouer, out of any effects that proceed from thence, and thy latter end ſhall be better then the beginning.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Meditate on the <hi>former experience</hi> of the ioy of the ſpirit, that ſo thou maiſt preſſe the Lord from his wonted mercies. Pſal. 77. 1. Sam, 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider the meanes that the Lord vſed to plant this ioy and loue in thy heart, and by the ſame know, that he will renue this worke, and therfore at no hand be driuen from the meanes. Cant. 1. Cant. 4.5.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:21476:58"/>4. Reſolue <hi>that thy former eſtate was better then now:</hi> Oſe 2.8.9. and therefore returne to thy firſt loue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that ſo the Lord may renue and increaſe thy loue vnto him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Acquaint the <hi>experienced ſouldier</hi> with this thy eſtate, that ſo he may be a meanes to quicken thee againe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Giue we not ouer our purſuit of theſe comforts: ſpare we no paines: thinke we all time too little, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we extraordinary afflictions, as faſting, and ſo groning vnder the burden, and deteſting our ſelues: giue we the Lord no reſt, till he hath returned to his reſt, and recouered our decaies. Cant. 5.</p>
            <p>To this end vſe we the meanes before ſet downe to recouer from Apoſtaſie.</p>
            <p>And be we comforted, that we ſhall not altogether looſe our labour, though we haue left this loue.</p>
            <p>How far we ſhall recouer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either we ſhall recouer what we haue loſt in the ſame kinde, namely the like ioy and extraordinary comforts of thee</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or elſe if we haue it not in this fruit of our loue, yet we ſhall be ſure to recouer in another kind, which ſhall be more profitable to further vs to happineſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the leſſe we feele this loue, the more we ſhall expreſſe our care to vſe all holy meanes whereby we may recouer it againe:</p>
            <p n="4">4. The more we ſhall learne to liue by faith in the expectation of a greater meaſure,</p>
            <p n="5">5. The more compaſſionate thou ſhall be to others that are caſt downe by this affliction, and ſo labour more earneſtly to raiſe them vp againe; that ſo toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them, thou maiſt be perfected. Heb. 11. <hi>vlt.</hi> that ſo maintaining the fellowſhip here on earth, thou maiſt be better fitted to the communion in Heauen.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And as thou haſt hereby greater occaſion to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the mercy of thy God in not leauing thee alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21476:59"/>
in ſuſtaining thee ſo wonderfully, and ſaue thee in this thy decay, ſo ſhalt thou be prouoked here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to truſt more perfectly thy God, though he ſhould abaſe thee further, not only in leauing thee to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward triall of a languiſhing ſpirit, and eclipſe of ioy, but, as the manner of Gods prouidence is to prepare vs by theſe inward afflictions to outward troubles, for the further triall of our faith, and increaſe of his power and mercy in our protection and deliuerance. If now it ſhall pleaſe our glorious God to lead vs through fire and water, to pronounce a ſentence of death againſt vs, that we may not truſt in ourſelues, but in the liuing God which raiſeth from the dead. That ſo after we haue ſuffered a little, we might be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to eternall ioyes: that ſo in our outward ſufferings our inward conſolations may abound? Is not here a gracious recompence of our former loſſe? Is not here a maruellous meanes ſo to reſtore the ſame? that God may haue the glory, that we by this meanes may be prepared vnto glory? ſhall not our loue be now glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly tried in ſuffering for the will of God? ſhall it not be much more teſtified in enduring ſo great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions? ſhall it not hereby be purged of all ſelfe-loue and carnall reſpects, that ſo it may be fitted to fulneſſe of ioy? ſhall not our patience here be tried, in waiting the good pleaſure of our God, that ſo we may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and intire, wanting nothing. 1. Iam. 3.4.</p>
            <p>Surely howſoeuer it fall, yet let it comfort vs that the holy Ghoſt doth not here challenge the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> that it hath loſt all her loue, or that it hath ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely loſt her firſt loue, but only that it hath left it for a time, and therefore it may recouer againe. And it hath but left her firſt loue, not altogether is bereft of all loue: well may it leaue it firſt loue, but it ſhall not looſe all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And for our further ſatisfaction, take we</hi> theſe rules that we are ſoundly in ſome meaſure recouered, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21476:59"/>
haue regained true ioy and comfort of our ſaluation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If our ioy beeing reſtored, wee are alſo more enabled in the practiſe of godlineſſe, growing more in grace, and in obedience to the word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If our ioy bee daylie accompanied with ſorrow for ſinne, and feare of our ſelues that wee may fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, with more ſobriety in the vſe of worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and more hunger after durable ioyes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If wee are more weaned from the loue of the world, and take leſſe ioy in the fleſh, and earthly things: knowing no man after the fleſh.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If we can reioyce in the further encreaſe of the Church, and flouriſhing eſtate thereof abroad, though it go not ſo well with our owne particular.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And can alſo weepe with them that languiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, though our owne cup run ouer.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Still ſubmitting our ſelfe to the croſſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And triumphing in our greateſt tribulations.</p>
            <p n="8">8. If our ioy be powerfull, to raiſe vs daily from ſinne, that ſo renuing our repentance it may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</p>
            <p n="9">9. If it be ſincere and pure, not ſo much reſting in our ſelues, as that God may haue the glory, euen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting our ſelues that for Gods ſake principally we haue done his will, and not for any by reſpects vnto our ſelues.</p>
            <p>And this is the laſt leſſon to be obſerued out of this Scripture: Namely;</p>
            <p>That the Saints ſhall not looſe vtterly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 7. The Saints ſhall not looſe their firſt loue <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. <hi>Oſe.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 27.</note> though they may leaue for a time their firſt loue: Luk. 11. Pſal. 92. 2, Tim. 4.19.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Lord hath promiſed to continue his loue towards them: Ioh. 13. 1. Ioh. 17. Ierem. 31.33. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their afflictions doe tend to their perſeuerance, as purging out their ſinnes; Eſay 1.25.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their ſinnes turne to their continuance in grace:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21476:60"/>
1. as making them afraid of ſinne: 2. and more expert to conquer the ſame: 3. more fit for grace, by making them more humble and hungry after it: 4. more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to others, and therfore mouing the Lord to haue more compaſſion on them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His hand is continually put vnder vs in our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt failings, and therefore wee ſhall riſe againe: Pſal. 37.24.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His end in leauing vs for a time, is to make vs take faſter holde on him, to make vs more deny our ſelues, that we may be found in Ieſus Chriſt in heauen.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Their Sauiour liueth, and triumpheth, to make them more then conquerours: Rom. 8.36.37. Ioh. 12.32. and to draw vp all after him.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The ſpirit and word ſhall abide in them, to hold them on in grace: Ioh. 15.</p>
            <p>And therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. This condemneth the blaſphemie of Papiſts, who teach, that the Saints may fall finally, and therein doe impeach the power and faithfulneſſe of God; or that they may ſo looſe their faith for the preſent, that it muſt be repaired anew againe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It checketh the inſolencie of the wicked, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth at the fals of the Saints, and inſult ouer them, ſeeing that though they fall, they ſhal riſe againe: Mic. 7.9. Pſal. 41.11.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As alſo it reprooueth the infidelity of the Saints, who doubt of their recouery, and wrong the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, and power of their faith, grieue the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit, and deny in a ſort the merit of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Heere is firſt inſtruction for the world, to iuſtifie Gods faithfulneſſe, ſeeing hee doth not forſake for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: Lam. 3.24.25.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Heere the Saints are leſſoned, as to feare their fals, and not to ſinne vpon preſumption of recouery; ſo not to diſtruſt of Gods mercy in their greateſt fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, ſeeing the Lord is faithfull, and they ſhall reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21476:60"/>
thogh not ſo ſenſible a meaſure as before they had yet ſufficient to fit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the enioying of that happineſſe that the Lord Ieſus hath purchaſed for them. And therefore let them vſe the holy meanes that they may recouer, namely ſuch as are before laid downe, in the recouery out of apoſtaſie, and regaining firſt loue, and hold out to the end. And if happily with all our labour we ſhall yet be to ſeeke of what we would haue: For the further ſatisfying and comforting of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, obſerue we thdſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that it is one thing to leaue our firſt loue, and to be luke-warme neither hot nor cold.</p>
            <p>We may not haue ſuch feeling of Gods loue as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly we had,<note place="margin">Difference between leauing firſt loue and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſſe.</note> and this may prouoke vs to more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry to recouer againe, as the ioy of Gods ſpirit may be an occaſion by reaſon of ſpirituall pride, that we may remit of our zeale, and yet we may ſtill be reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in iudgement: what ſhould be done though hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily in our practiſe we may abate of what we haue formrly done. 1. Wheretas luke-warmneſſe ariſeth frome a peruerſe and deceiued iudgement, that we are rich, we want nothing, and therefore what need we now be ſo earneſt and painful, why may we nor abate of our labours, and ſit downe and take our eaſe, may we not be wholly, &amp;c. 2. Hereupon it is another note of luke-warmneſſe to grow indifferent to any ſide; to be between both, ready to entertaine what may ſtand with the ſtreame, and ſo to runne with the tide as occaſion ſerueth. But it is not ſo with ſuch as haue ſimply loſt their firſt loue, they are neuer quiet till they haue recouered againe: they cannot endure any other loue to ſhare in their affections, oh it reioyceth them to conſider what a true and faithfull loue they had; they are now more fond of him, when he abſents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at euery ſtone muſt be rowled, all corners ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, to find him againe. Cant. 5. and they giue not ouer till they haue recouered him.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:21476:61"/>2. That there is great oddes between leauing our firſt loue, and looſing it altogether: we may leaue, in regard of a former meaſure, and yet hold a true gaine which ſhall cleere vs of luke-warmneſſe: and though we leaue a meaſure, yet we looſe not all, becauſe the leaſt remaining will be a meanes to recouer againe, if not ſo much as we haue had, yet ſo much as ſhall ſerue both to keepe from finall apoſtaſie, and further to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory.</p>
            <p n="6">6 And therefore here is matter of exceeding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to the elect of God, not to truſt their owne vnbeleeuing hearts, much leſſe Satans lies; but to reſt on the faithfulneſſe of God, not iudging themſelues by what they are in their decay, but by what they were in their firſt loue: and ſo preſſing the Lord in his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe, and their former experience, they ſhall be vpheld in their greateſt failings, by a ſecret power, and in good time the Lord will appeare vnto them to bring foorth their righteouſneſſe as the light, and their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing as the noone day, that ſo their latter end may be better then their beginning.</p>
            <closer>Glory be to the Lord Ieſus.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
